<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2023-07-23</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>The Philosophical is the Personal</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1800.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1800</id>
    <issued>2023-07-23</issued>
    <modified>2023-07-23</modified>
    <summary>After further reflection on my post about the siren song of systemic solutions, I've come up with a generalization that I'm trying on for size: the philosophical is the personal....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Siren Song of Systemic Solutions</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1799.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1799</id>
    <issued>2023-07-21</issued>
    <modified>2023-07-21</modified>
    <summary>One often hears that "systemic problems require systemic solutions." Although I used to agree, now I'm not so sure....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Incomplete Enlightenment</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1798.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1798</id>
    <issued>2023-07-09</issued>
    <modified>2023-07-09</modified>
    <summary>The other day I glanced briefly at Ray Dalio's book Principles, which made something of a splash when it was published a few years ago. I decided not to read the book (for now) because I wasn't impressed by the few sections I looked at; in particular, he seems to reduce the art of living to two steps:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophical Parsimony</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1797.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1797</id>
    <issued>2023-07-10</issued>
    <modified>2023-07-10</modified>
    <summary>If "say implies do" - if the beliefs that you profess are constrained by consistency with the behaviors you enact - then doesn't that severely limit the scope of philosophical speculation?...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Behavior and Belief</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1796.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1796</id>
    <issued>2023-07-08</issued>
    <modified>2023-07-08</modified>
    <summary>A few years ago when I needed to fly across the country to attend to some urgent family matters, I spotted an older woman at the airport wearing a button that said "I'm With Greta." The irony is that if she really were with Greta and believed, in the marrow of her bones, that human activity is causing a climate emergency, she wouldn't have been about to board an airplane, since jet travel is just about the worst thing you can do to generate greenhouse gases. In a similar vein, I've heard friends say how much they want to fly to Italy so that they can visit Venice before it is inundated by rising sea levels (caused in no small part by so many people flying to Italy so that they can visit Venice before it is inundated by rising sea levels). And don't get me started on the thousands of activists and bureaucrats who fly around the world to attend climate conferences....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Mind the Gap</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1795.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1795</id>
    <issued>2023-07-08</issued>
    <modified>2023-07-08</modified>
    <summary>In my recent post about discovering the best we can do, I mentioned the inevitability of a gap between the ideal and the real, especially for those who have high standards of personal behavior. This leads to the question: how do you figure out where you fall short?...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
