<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2023-06-07</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>George Winston, RIP</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1785.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1785</id>
    <issued>2023-06-07</issued>
    <modified>2023-06-07</modified>
    <summary>I was saddened yesterday to learn (via my friend Wayne Bethanis) that pianist-composer George Winston has died. Every solo performer of original music - not just pianists but guitarists and everyone else - owes him a debt of gratitude, for he was one of the few who blazed the trail of modern instrumental music, starting with his album Autumn in 1980. Although his music was often called "new age", he preferred the evocative term "rural folk piano". Many streams came together in his music: folk, blues, jazz, classical, rock, gospel, rhythm and blues, Hawaiian, and more. Yet he fused them into a seamless whole that was uniquely his own....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle on Fulfillment</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1784.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1784</id>
    <issued>2023-06-01</issued>
    <modified>2023-06-01</modified>
    <summary>The more deeply I ponder Aristotle's conception of eudaimonia (usually translated as "happiness" or more recently sometimes as "flourishing"), the more radical it seems....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ways of Life and Lines of Work</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1783.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1783</id>
    <issued>2023-06-01</issued>
    <modified>2023-06-01</modified>
    <summary>Because labor is so central to human existence, throughout history various thinkers have speculated about what the Buddhist eightfold path calls "right livelihood" for those who would seek and practice wisdom. For instance, both the Stoic Musonius Rufus and the Confucian Wu Yubi advocated subsistence farming as a noble line of work. The Taoist sage Chuang Tzu tells a beautiful story about the artistry of a lowly butcher. Although officially Aristotle downplayed the value of mechanical pursuits like housebuilding and even music-making, nevertheless he frequently used craftsmen as models of practical thinking and he applied the lessons of craftsmanship to ethical reflection. In recent times, Matthew Crawford titled one of his books "shop class as soul craft" and has argued that working in the trades enables you to bring your whole self to your productive activities. And so on....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ways of Life</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1782.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1782</id>
    <issued>2023-05-17</issued>
    <modified>2023-05-17</modified>
    <summary>Having last week explored what philosophers do, I thought I'd broaden that theme by looking at ways of life in general, not only philosophy as a way of life....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Open Reading Interview</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1781.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1781</id>
    <issued>2023-05-11</issued>
    <modified>2023-05-11</modified>
    <summary>Three weeks ago I had the honor of being interviewed by Sal Inglima of Boston Free Radio for his Open Readings show. We had a great time talking about the fine art of poetry translation. Sal read aloud my translation of a German poem about the eve of World War II by philosopher Walter Kaufmann and I read my translation of Sappho fragment 16 as well as two of my own poems: Ancient Fire (from the eponymous collection) and Brief Wisdom (from Songs of Zarathustra, my book about Friedrich Nietzsche). Enjoy!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What Philosophers Do</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1780.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1780</id>
    <issued>2023-05-11</issued>
    <modified>2023-05-11</modified>
    <summary>If philosophy is a way of life, then what are the characteristic activities of philosophers? (I mean, of course, not professors of philosophy, but people who love and practice the minerval arts of wisdom.)...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
