<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2023-08-09</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Daily Reflection</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1808.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1808</id>
    <issued>2023-08-09</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-09</modified>
    <summary>As a counterpart to my morning practice of daily forethought, I've also been engaging in daily reflection every evening. This habit was made famous by the ancient Stoic Seneca in Book III of his dialogue On Anger, where he mentions that his teacher Sextius asked himself these three probing questions before going to sleep: "What bad habit of yours have you cured today? What vice have you checked? In what respect are you better?" Some of my questions are more positive, but still geared toward living a more examined life:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Daily Forethought</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1807.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1807</id>
    <issued>2023-08-07</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-07</modified>
    <summary>In pursuit of a more examined life, I've been honing my daily habits. Taking a hint from the ancient Stoics, first thing in the morning I've been thinking about the day ahead and then at the end of the day I've been reflecting on how the day went. Here's a snapshot of what this looks like for me (I'll split this up into two posts, one prospective and one retrospective)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tao Te Ching ยง11: Emptiness</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1806.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1806</id>
    <issued>2023-08-03</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-03</modified>
    <summary>Following up on yesterday's post about the Tao Te Ching, here's another poem that I might set to music (chapter 11 in the standard order). My provisional rendering is as follows:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tao Te Ching ยง1: The Gateway</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1805.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1805</id>
    <issued>2023-08-02</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-02</modified>
    <summary>For many years I have admired, and puzzled over, the Tao Te Ching. This classic text of Chinese philosophy is wise, poetic, suggestive, paradoxial, even inscrutable. Because I don't know classical Chinese, I'm forced to read multiple translations - a task made easy by the fact that it's one of the most translated works in all of world literature. Yet, not knowing the original language, I'm always unsure whether I really understand its message. It's one of my "best friend books" and I return to it every few years....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Republic of Letters</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1804.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1804</id>
    <issued>2023-07-31</issued>
    <modified>2023-07-31</modified>
    <summary>About 600 years ago, some farsighted intellectual explorers in Europe created a long-distance communication network they called the Republic of Letters; indeed, it was almost something like a network of networks (an internet!), since it connected local networks in various towns and cities with each other. The way it worked is that individual people would exchange handwritten letters and manuscripts, and eventually printed pamphlets and books, with correspondents in other parts of the network. Those correspondents would then write back to the original sender and also share insights with others to whom they were connected (whether local or distant). It was also expected that participants would help to grow the network by recruiting new members. This network, which flourished from about 1400 to 1800, played a significant role in fostering the Renaissance, the Scientific Revolution, the Enlightenment, and the early Industrial Revolution....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Always Be Reading</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1803.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1803</id>
    <issued>2023-07-30</issued>
    <modified>2023-07-30</modified>
    <summary>In my recent post about the value of re-reading, I mentioned that I regularly seek out new books and authors. For me, at least, here's how that works....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
