<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2023-01-19</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>The Seven Pillars of Friendship</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1760.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1760</id>
    <issued>2023-01-19</issued>
    <modified>2023-01-19</modified>
    <summary>Love, friendship, and other close personal relationships have been ill-served in the philosophical literature. Aside from Aristotle's foundational discussion and the occasional essay by the likes of Montaigne, Bacon, and Emerson, few philosophers have contributed deep insights to human relationships. This is disappointing, because as Aristotle observed 2400 years ago we are social creatures for whom close personal relationships are fundamental to our way of life....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Best Self vs. True Self</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1759.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1759</id>
    <issued>2023-01-12</issued>
    <modified>2023-01-12</modified>
    <summary>As previously mentioned, I am skeptical about the notion of the true self. Recently I've done some reading that has reinforced this skepticism. In particular, research by the likes of Roy Baumeister shows that human beings tend to identify with the activities and desires that they think are best (either individually or socially) and to disown the activities and desires that they think aren't so admirable....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Metaphysics in Verse</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1758.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1758</id>
    <issued>2023-01-12</issued>
    <modified>2023-01-12</modified>
    <summary>One of the things I do to avoid exposure to the news is immerse myself in poetry. Most recently I've been reading English and American poets from the 1500s and 1600s, such as Anne Bradstreet, Samuel Daniel, and Thomas Traherne. At the same time, I've started an intensive re-reading of Aristotelian texts and commentary in preparation for writing an epitome of Aristotle's views on human flourishing. Putting the two together can yield some intriguing combinations!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Growing into One's Nature</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1757.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1757</id>
    <issued>2023-01-05</issued>
    <modified>2023-01-05</modified>
    <summary>Existentialist philosophers insist on the ability - indeed, the responsibility - for human beings to create themselves. This is the import of Sartre's famous formulation "existence precedes essence": there is no human essence, and if you believe so then you are engaging in "bad faith" and living inauthentically....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Goodness Trumps Uniqueness</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1756.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1756</id>
    <issued>2022-12-29</issued>
    <modified>2022-12-29</modified>
    <summary>Advocates of modern eudaimonism and the "true self" place great value on individual uniqueness. Consider David L. Norton in his 1976 book Personal Destinies (p. 16):...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2022 Readings</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1755.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1755</id>
    <issued>2022-12-27</issued>
    <modified>2022-12-27</modified>
    <summary>Here are the eighty-odd books I chanced to read in 2022, with links to ones in the public domain that I've posted in full or in part at my Monadnock site. Right now I'm also a third of the way through War and Peace, but there's no way I'll finish it by the end of the year......</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
