<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2025-11-21</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Twenty-Five Years of Blogging</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2002.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2002</id>
    <issued>2025-11-21</issued>
    <modified>2025-11-21</modified>
    <summary>On this day in the year 2000, I posted the first entry in my online journal. Two thousand posts and 650,000+ words later, I'm still at it. Granted, my journal is not quite of Thoreauvian proportions: our friend Henry produced over 2 million words in 24 years of journaling (all of which I read while encountering Thoreau in preparation for composing my book The Upland Farm). Even so, I've done a lot of scribbling over the last quarter century!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Giving and Receiving</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2001.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2001</id>
    <issued>2025-11-16</issued>
    <modified>2025-11-16</modified>
    <summary>Recent life circumstances have spurred me to reflect further on love as an activity, but also on love as a "passivity", as it were....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Letter</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2000.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2000</id>
    <issued>2025-10-17</issued>
    <modified>2025-10-17</modified>
    <summary>Yesterday I penned a letter to my best friend. And I do mean penned: after rummaging around in a box stashed in a closet, I tracked down some fine stationery I'd bought years ago and, pen in hand, sat down to write. Having been away from letter-writing for decades, I was reminded of a few long-forgotten essentials:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Socrates and Thoreau on True Wealth</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1999.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1999</id>
    <issued>2025-10-14</issued>
    <modified>2025-10-14</modified>
    <summary>On this day in 1857, Thoreau wrote as follows in his journal:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Private, Personal, Practical, Passionate, Particular</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1998.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1998</id>
    <issued>2025-10-10</issued>
    <modified>2025-10-10</modified>
    <summary>Following a gap of nearly forty years (!), I'm re-reading Alasdair MacIntyre's influential book After Virtue. As I do so, I'll post occasionally on the reflections it inspires....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Soulcraft</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1997.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1997</id>
    <issued>2025-10-05</issued>
    <modified>2025-10-05</modified>
    <summary>Aristotle wrote three books with "ethics" (ἠθική) in the title, where the word ἠθική is derived from the Greek word for character (ἦθος). Yet to modern ears, "ethics" brings to mind commandments, guardrails, and other restrictions on behavior. Thus arises the question: how best to render the word ἠθική into English?...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
