<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2024-06-16</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Unalienable Rights</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1873.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1873</id>
    <issued>2024-06-16</issued>
    <modified>2024-06-16</modified>
    <summary>Thinking recently about brotherhood and pluralism in an American context spurred me to reflect on the American creed expressed so succinctly in the Declaration of Independence:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Persuasion vs. Power</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1872.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1872</id>
    <issued>2024-06-14</issued>
    <modified>2024-06-14</modified>
    <summary>In my post about pluralism the other day, I mentioned in passing a crucial proviso: those who wish to force their positions on the rest of us have thereby placed themselves outside what Michael Oakeshott called the human conversation....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics III.1-5</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1871.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1871</id>
    <issued>2024-06-11</issued>
    <modified>2024-06-11</modified>
    <summary>As mentioned last time, toward the end of Book II of the Nicomachean Ethics Aristotle states that character traits are things that we choose. In the first half of Book III, he provides a deeper analysis of related issues: the extent to which actions are willing or unwilling, the nature of deliberation and choice, etc. Although the discussion is somewhat technical in spots and has given scholars much to chew on, in the end it has a number of practical implications....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>E Pluribus Unum</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1870.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1870</id>
    <issued>2024-06-10</issued>
    <modified>2024-06-10</modified>
    <summary>Following up on my post about brotherhood, I've continued to think about ways to cultivate a more magnanimous attitude toward other people and groups. One idea I'm trying on for size is seeing different viewpoints as contributing to the overall evolution of society. This is especially challenging in the political realm, which is mired in binary thinking, polarization, and demonization of The Other; yet, for that very reason, perhaps here such a mindshift could be especially valuable....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Brotherhood</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1869.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1869</id>
    <issued>2024-05-28</issued>
    <modified>2024-05-28</modified>
    <summary>A few months ago, Eric Hoel published a fascinating post about the nature of 21st-century society (read the whole thing, linked below, as background to what I write here). Hoel used Hegel (by way of Francis Fukuyama) and Nietzsche (by way of James Dale Davidson and William Rees-Mogg) as the jumping-off points for an analysis of what ails us. His dialectical thesis is the centrality of mob psychology in our current moment, and his antithesis is the sovereign individual who can rise above the mob....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Virtue and Happiness</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1868.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1868</id>
    <issued>2024-05-18</issued>
    <modified>2024-05-18</modified>
    <summary>One of Aristotle's signature claims in ethics is that virtue and happiness go hand in hand. To our ears this sounds questionable at best, because we think of virtue as a matter of following rules and doing your duty, whereas we think of happiness as a matter of having fun and experiencing pleasure. "Do your duty and you'll have lots of fun?" Um, no!...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
