<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2020-11-12</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle's Dialectical Pedagogy: A Review of Revaluing Ethics by Thomas W. Smith</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1654.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1654</id>
    <issued>2020-11-12</issued>
    <modified>2020-11-12</modified>
    <summary>In my research toward writing Complete Yourself: Aristotle on Human Fulfillment, I have read dozens and dozens of books about Aristotle's ethics and his philosophy in general. A small number of those books stand out in the crowded field of Aristotelian studies, but only one of them has been a revelation to me: Revaluing Ethics: Aristotle's Dialectical Pedagogy by Thomas W. Smith....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Election Survival Guide</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1653.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1653</id>
    <issued>2020-11-01</issued>
    <modified>2020-11-01</modified>
    <summary>Every four years I dread the prospect of yet another election for president of the United States. What a depressing, anxiety-ridden spectacle! It's almost enough to make me a monarchist (if only we could find the right sort of monarch, of course)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Wider Palette</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1652.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1652</id>
    <issued>2020-10-30</issued>
    <modified>2020-10-30</modified>
    <summary>In my most recent post ("Beyond Binary"), I talked about the need to transcend dichotomies and false alternatives. One aspect of doing so is recognizing what I called a wider palette of viewpoints, which is easy to do in philosophy and psychology but not in politics (at least not in American politics with its two-party system)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Beyond Binary</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1651.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1651</id>
    <issued>2020-09-20</issued>
    <modified>2020-09-20</modified>
    <summary>As political polarization proliferates, it's beneficial to explore realms of thought that are not limited to left vs. right and us vs. them. Personally, I'm partial to philosophy: it's impossible to reduce all of philosophical thinking to, say, Epicureans vs. Stoics without ignoring the deep and unique contributions of Platonists, Aristotelians, Taoists, Buddhists, Confucians, Hindus, Christians, humanists, skeptics, existentialists, and many more....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #14: The Faults of Aristotle</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1650.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1650</id>
    <issued>2020-09-05</issued>
    <modified>2020-09-05</modified>
    <summary>Although I think Aristotle was the greatest mind who ever lived, he did have his faults. In modern times, he is especially criticized for supposedly being anti-science, anti-democracy, pro-slavery, and anti-women. Let us briefly consider these charges....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Compounding Wisdom</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1649.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1649</id>
    <issued>2020-08-28</issued>
    <modified>2020-08-28</modified>
    <summary>This weekend, in honor of Warren Buffett's 90th birthday, I'd like to consider the phenomenon of compounding. It's a little-known fact that Buffett earned almost 90% of his $82 billion fortune after the age of 65. Yet supposedly he has been fascinated by compounding since the age of 10, when he had an epiphany about how wealth could grow over time through the steady effects of return on investment....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
