<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2021-08-01</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #15: Taking up Aristotle's Causes</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1673.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1673</id>
    <issued>2021-08-01</issued>
    <modified>2021-08-01</modified>
    <summary>In recent times, Aristotle is often criticized for holding back the progress of science for two thousand years. (As Armand Leroi argues in his book The Lagoon based on the research of scholars like David Balme, Allan Gotthelf, and James Lennox, this is rather wrongheaded, given that Aristotle founded the science of biology!) One of the ways Aristotle is alleged to have gone astray is in his "doctrine of the four causes" (especially, we're told, the so-called "final cause" which involves impossibilities like backward causation); although I'm always suspicious when someone attributes a "doctrine" to Aristotle, it's worth looking carefully at what Aristotle actually said instead of relying on shallow or antagonistic summaries....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Meditations on Bach #5: Transcription</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1672.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1672</id>
    <issued>2021-08-01</issued>
    <modified>2021-08-01</modified>
    <summary>As I delve further into Bach's Cello Suites, I also stray further from anything like the received wisdom about how to play them (whether traditionally "classical" or "historically informed"). Take, for instance, the famous prelude from suite #1 in G major. Where I've settled for now is playing the first half at an extremely slow speed, with many sustained single and double notes (thus taking advantage of a capability of the electric bass). As I was practicing this piece at the instrument and then in my head the other day, I realized that I'm playing it at a speed that is appropriate for the breathing characteristic of meditation - half a bar inhaling, half a bar exhaling. That's slow, and perhaps the exact opposite of what Glenn Gould (one of my favorite pianists) did with Bach's keyboard works. However, after the half cadence in measure 22, I start to vary the pace somewhat, speeding up quite a bit in the bariolage of the crescendo before coming back to earth for the ending (which I've modified, too). Reading History, Imagination, and the Performance of Music by Peter Walls over the last few days has helped me to realize that, for better or worse, what I'm doing with the Cello Suites is not performance but transcription - more along the lines of, say, Ferruccio Busoni than Pablo Casals. (Indeed, this is not all that dissimilar from what I've done with my "eudaimonia suite" of books on living well: philosophy as the experience of wisdom, not as discursive argument.) I'll make a rough demo of the G major prelude soon to create a record of my current thinking, no matter how wayward it might be....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Blended Vision</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1671.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1671</id>
    <issued>2021-07-05</issued>
    <modified>2021-07-05</modified>
    <summary>The other day I went to see the eye doctor, who told me I have blended vision: one of my eyes is farsighted and the other is nearsighted, but they function well together. Quite a fitting analogy for what Pierre Hadot called philosophy as the love and practice of wisdom. We tend to think of philosophy as hopelessly abstract, but if it is in part a practice then it focuses not only on what is far but also on what is near. One of the poems in my book Songs of Zarathustra tries to capture this insight:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Opinions vs. Truths</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1670.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1670</id>
    <issued>2021-06-18</issued>
    <modified>2021-06-18</modified>
    <summary>In recent posts we've looked into holding opinions about fewer topics, holding multiple opinions about the same topic, and changing our opinions about the opinions that other people hold. But what exactly is an opinion? Let's take a closer look....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Number Six</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1669.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1669</id>
    <issued>2021-06-06</issued>
    <modified>2021-06-06</modified>
    <summary>Everyone has their idiosyncrasies. One of mine is a particular fascination with the number six....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Holding Multiple Opinions</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1668.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1668</id>
    <issued>2021-05-31</issued>
    <modified>2021-05-31</modified>
    <summary>Sometimes it's difficult to hold fewer opinions in your own mind or to engage in cognitive empathy toward others; that's when it can help to hold multiple opinions at the same time. This might sound like the mental equivalent of juggling plates, but it's a skill worth cultivating (and one with an ancient pedigree, as evidenced for example by the Letter to Pythocles by the ancient Greek philosopher Epicurus)....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
