<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2024-04-26</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics I.9-12</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1862.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1862</id>
    <issued>2024-04-26</issued>
    <modified>2024-04-26</modified>
    <summary>Having mentioned in Nicomachean Ethics I.8 the desirability of external goods such as wealth and reputation, Aristotle naturally moves on to consider the causes of human flourishing. Is fulfillment something that can be learned through training and habituation, or is it a matter of fate or even chance? Well, he says, if flourishing and fulfillment consist in a certain kind of activity (ἐνέργεια), specifically working at the task (ἔργον) of living a complete human life in accordance with inherent thrivings of mind and character, then there must be effort involved. Although this kind of beautifully right (καλὀς) activity is consistent with human nature, still it needs to be acquired and practiced. This is why we don't say that a child has attained fulfillment: it's necessary to achieve reasonably complete excellence (ἀρετή) of mind and character in a reasonably complete life in order to be truly fulfilled....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Poetry Reading</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1861.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1861</id>
    <issued>2024-04-25</issued>
    <modified>2024-04-25</modified>
    <summary>Yesterday evening I was honored to have a conversation with folks from the poetry circle of the Boulder Writers Alliance, at the invitation of poet Laura Border. Although I don't consider myself a poet or even primarily a writer, it was quite a pleasure to talk with such a welcoming group about the relationship between philosophy and poetry as well as the challenges of poetry translation and the differences between ancient and modern poetry. I also read aloud some poems from my books Ancient Fire and Songs of Zarathustra. Because this is a conclave of writers, we also took time toward the end of the session for each participant to write and then read aloud a short poem. Having discoursed a bit during the discussion on the attitudes of Socrates and Plato toward poetry, here's what I composed on the spot with reference to Plato's dialogues Republic and Phaedo:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics I.8</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1860.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1860</id>
    <issued>2024-04-20</issued>
    <modified>2024-04-20</modified>
    <summary>Amidst all the excitement (for philosophy scholars!) about the "function argument" in Nicomachean Ethics I.7, Chapter 8 is often overlooked. Yet there are valuable insights here, too....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics I.7</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1859.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1859</id>
    <issued>2024-04-17</issued>
    <modified>2024-04-17</modified>
    <summary>Book I, Chapter 7 of the Nicomachean Ethics is one of the most consequential and intensively studied passages in all of Aristotle's writings, so it will behoove us to look at it closely. As mentioned last time, it's a rather knotty line of reasoning, but I'll try to describe it as briefly and simply as I can....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tao Te Ching §44: Ageless Life</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1858.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1858</id>
    <issued>2024-04-13</issued>
    <modified>2024-04-13</modified>
    <summary>I continue to ponder various poems from the Tao Te Ching with an eye toward perhaps setting them to music. Here is my provisional rendering of chapter 44:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Modernizing Aristotle's Ethics: A Review</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1857.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1857</id>
    <issued>2024-04-01</issued>
    <modified>2024-04-01</modified>
    <summary>This is just a brief note that folks interested in Aristotle, Ayn Rand, the psychology of happiness, or any combination thereof might enjoy my review of Roger E. Bissell and Vinay Kolhatkar's new book Modernizing Aristotle's Ethics: Toward a New Art and Science of Self-Actualization, just published in Issue 44, No. 1 of the interdisciplinary journal Reason Papers. Check it out!...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
