<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2025-09-05</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Living Wisdom</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1989.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1989</id>
    <issued>2025-09-05</issued>
    <modified>2025-09-05</modified>
    <summary>While reading yet another book by Pierre Hadot recently, I came across a fascinating passage from the ancient Greek writer Plutarch about philosophy as a way of life. Here's the crux of it, in my own translation:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>American Complexities</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1988.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1988</id>
    <issued>2025-09-05</issued>
    <modified>2025-09-05</modified>
    <summary>Reading about American history and culture is forever fascinating. Of late I've been focused on learning about various immigrant groups, from monumental ones like the English and the Africans (explained so well by David Hackett Fischer in his books Albion's Seed and African Founders) to relatively unknown ones like the French Huguenots who migrated to Boston, New York, and South Carolina in the 1690s and the Canary Islanders who settled in southern Louisiana under Spanish rule from 1778 to 1783. America has experienced dozens of such migrant streams, each consisting of atypically adventurous people and each adding its distinctive flavor to the gumbo of American culture. Indeed, as Walt Whitman observed in his 1855 poem Great Are the Myths, America is "the nation of clusters of equal nations"; Frederick Douglass echoed Whitman in his 1869 speech Our Composite Nation; and Albert Murray renewed these insights in his 1970 book The Omni-Americans, wherein he argued that American culture is inherently composite, pluralistic, mulatto....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Vibe Thinking</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1987.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1987</id>
    <issued>2025-09-03</issued>
    <modified>2025-09-03</modified>
    <summary>Over lunch last week, a friend and I had an interesting discussion about the future of computer programming. At his startup, he makes extensive use of machine learning and large language models but still writes plenty of code. He called this "AI-assisted coding", in contradistinction to "vibe coding”, whereby people who don't know how to code ask the LLM chatbot to generate all the code for them. He also noted that when an LLM generates code, you have to get really good at reading code - a skill that even old-style programmers haven't traditionally cultivated or enjoyed....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Greek Tragedy and American Jazz</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1986.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1986</id>
    <issued>2025-08-25</issued>
    <modified>2025-08-25</modified>
    <summary>Cross-pollination is a wondrous thing. Over the last few months I've been reading about two topics that might seem quite far apart: ancient Greek tragedy and American jazz. In the first category, I'm working my way through all the extant tragedies of Aeschylus, Sophocles, and Euripides, and also reading literary and philosophical analysis of tragic drama, such as Walter Kaufmann's Tragedy and Philosophy. In the second category, I've been reading biographies of great jazz musicians and composers (Armstrong, Ellington, Monk, Mingus, Coltrane, etc.) as well as historical and philosophical analysis of the meaning of jazz and blues in American culture, especially some amazing books by Albert Murray and some essays by Ralph Ellison....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Historical Aspirations</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1985.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1985</id>
    <issued>2025-08-25</issued>
    <modified>2025-08-25</modified>
    <summary>Following up on my post about thinking historically, here are some further reflections on the methodological insights (and, to my mind, shortcomings) of my favorite historian, David Hackett Fischer....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Sunlight and Shadow</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1984.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1984</id>
    <issued>2025-08-24</issued>
    <modified>2025-08-24</modified>
    <summary>Overnight I realized that my post yesterday about Walter Kaufmann's account of love as a virtue could give the impression that my view of life is rather dark. Whereas it seems that Kaufmann had something of a tragic sense of life, my outlook is decidedly sunnier. Since I was quite young, I've wondered at the cosmic improbability of being alive. Several months ago I put it this way to a friend:...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
