<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2018-02-04</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle: A First Encounter</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1603.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1603</id>
    <issued>2018-02-04</issued>
    <modified>2018-02-04</modified>
    <summary>Aristotle's views on living well and doing well - what the ancient Greeks called εὐδαιμονία or eudaimonia - are some of the most enduring insights into ethics ever put into words. Yet the deepest meaning of those words is usually obscured by efforts to translate and interpret Aristotle's thoughts. In part the problem is linguistic, in part it is cultural, but ultimately it is philosophical: ancient Greek world views, Aristotle's among them, are very far from our modern ways of thinking and feeling....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Songs of Zarathustra Now Published</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1602.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1602</id>
    <issued>2018-02-03</issued>
    <modified>2018-02-03</modified>
    <summary>My short book on Friedrich Nietzsche, Songs of Zarathustra, is now published in paperback and ebook formats, and of course also on my website. Once again both the form and the content are unorthodox: I construe Nietzsche in a more humanistic way than most interpreters, and I do so in a cycle of 73 brief poems (including translations of some of Nietzsche's own verse). Neither aspect is likely to endear me to academics, but then I don't write for a scholarly audience - even though my books are based on a deep reading of the original texts....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Privacy FTW</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1601.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1601</id>
    <issued>2018-01-27</issued>
    <modified>2018-01-27</modified>
    <summary>Tomorrow (January 28th) is Data Privacy Day. Why not join in the celebration? Here are some suggestions to prevent absolutely everything you do online from being tracked:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Scales and Modes and Tetrachords, Oh My!</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1600.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1600</id>
    <issued>2018-01-03</issued>
    <modified>2018-01-03</modified>
    <summary>In preparation for recording my arrangements of music by Yes for solo electric bass, I've started taking music lessons with Mark Stefaniw, a fine bassist in the Denver area. Under Mark's tutelage I've been digging into music theory, which is both fascinating and enlightening (especially given my many years of musical learning at the surface)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ceding Our Humanity</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1599.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1599</id>
    <issued>2017-12-20</issued>
    <modified>2017-12-20</modified>
    <summary>Geoff Huston's keynote talk at RIPE 75, "The Death of Transit and Beyond", provides a sobering perspective on the recent evolution of the Internet - and, because so many of our personal, economic, intellectual, and political interactions happen over the Internet these days, on the evolution of society at large. Although Geoff tried to steer clear of alarmism, the picture is not pretty. Extreme concentration of wealth and power has led to a few leviathans controlling an overwhelming percentage of our online life (as of today, Apple, Google, Microsoft, Amazon, Alibaba, Tencent, and Facebook are seven of the eight largest public corporations in the world by market capitalization). Furthermore, as I explained in my talk "The Internet is Dead, Long Live the Internet" three years ago, in large measure these companies make money by tracking everything we do online and then selling those profiles to advertisers and marketers. And it gets worse: unlike the so-called robber barons of the late 19th century Gilded Age, which merely controlled markets for transportation, steel, oil, coal, and other physical goods, in subtle and not-so-subtle ways today's robber barons monitor and increasingly direct our mental and emotional life through the news we learn about, the books we read, the videos we watch, the people we talk with and connect to, and much more....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Novel Idea</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1598.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1598</id>
    <issued>2017-12-17</issued>
    <modified>2017-12-17</modified>
    <summary>I've long imagined that the sixth movement in my "eudaimonia suite" of books on the art of living would be about Taoism. However, recently an intriguing ambition came to me: writing a novel about Pyrrho's journey to Central Asia and Northwestern India with Alexander the Great's army and his conversion to skepticism there by early Buddhists (likely in the Gandharan city of Taxila above the Peshawar Valley - a great center of learning at the time). I like the goal of exploring the commonalities among early Taoism, early Buddhism, and Pyrrhonism, as well as Heraclitus and other pre-Socractic philosophers. In essence, this would be a novelization of Christopher Beckwith's thesis from his fascinating book Greek Buddha. Aside from the usual challenges of working through the ideas of a thinker like Nietzsche or Thoreau, there would be new obstacles to overcome here: I don't know Sanskrit or classical Chinese, and I've never written any fiction, not even a short story. Truth be told, I'm not deeply drawn to stories and I rarely read novels. However, a few years ago I read both The Glass Bead Game and Siddhartha by Hermann Hesse, and recently I read When Nietzsche Wept by Irvin Yalom. In so doing, I realized that I enjoy novels of ideas, which have no plot to speak of but make up for it with interesting dialogue and internal discovery. In any case, after I publish Songs of Zarathustra a few weeks from now I'll first finish my translation of the ethical writings of Epicurus and then write an epitome of Aristotle's moral philosophy, so writing a book on ancient Buddhism and skepticism is years away....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
