<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - philosopher, technologist, musician.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2026-01-21</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophy and Psychology Redux</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2026.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2026</id>
    <issued>2026-01-21</issued>
    <modified>2026-01-21</modified>
    <summary>Yesterday my friend Adrian Lory and I had an enjoyable and thought-provoking dialogue on Substack Live about philosophy and psychology as complementary paths to wisdom and fulfillment - so much so that we plan to have a follow-up chat in the coming weeks. Inspired by our conversation, here are some further questions I'm pondering about the interface between philosophy and psychology:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Writing Blank Verse</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2025.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2025</id>
    <issued>2026-01-13</issued>
    <modified>2026-01-13</modified>
    <summary>For my slowly-progressing epic poem about Pyrrho and Alexander the Great, I'm writing in blank verse, i.e., unrhymed iambic pentameter. Many of the great English-language poets have written in blank verse, including Shakespeare, Milton, Wordsworth, and Frost. Blank verse is especially appropriate, if you ask me, for epic poetry, since it's something like the equivalent in English of ancient Greek dactylic hexameter (another option is to employ fourteeners, as Matthew Arnold preferred for translations of Homer and as A.E. Stallings did in her amazing translation of Lucretius). Aside from its epic and dramatic pedigree, one of the attractions of blank verse is that it steers clear of the chimey sound and forced rhymes of heroic couplets, yet still maintains a regular pulse....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Discipline of Reading</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2024.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2024</id>
    <issued>2026-01-12</issued>
    <modified>2026-01-12</modified>
    <summary>A friend asked me yesterday how it is that I am so disciplined about reading. I perceive a few reasons....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Music of the Future</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2023.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2023</id>
    <issued>2026-01-09</issued>
    <modified>2026-01-09</modified>
    <summary>Over at The American Scholar, Joseph Horowitz has asked the big question about art music in America: can it find an orientation, a future direction, a way forward? In truth, the question has loomed over our musical culture, unanswered, ever since the serialist revolution over a hundred years ago. Horowitz's telling highlights composers who resisted serialism, such as Busoni, Elgar, Sibelius, and Ives (we might widen the lens even further to include the likes of Debussy, Ravel, Delius, Hindemith, Scriabin, and Shostakovich). He also connects a few dots from Dvořák and his stay in America to composers who answered Dvořák's call to honor and integrate music from Native American cultures; a somewhat prominent example is Busoni's Indian Fantasy for piano and orchestra, whereas a more obscure but quite inspiring example is Arthur Farwell's "Hoka" String Quartet (which Horowitz names "the closest thing I know to an American idiom in parallel with Béla Bartók’s raw absorption of Transylvanian song and dance")....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Making the Political Personal</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2022.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2022</id>
    <issued>2026-01-08</issued>
    <modified>2026-01-08</modified>
    <summary>Last week I had a brief conversation with two of my neighbors about politics and, specifically, my avoidance thereof. We touched on only the first of the topics I cover in this post, but I thought it might be helpful to me, and perhaps others, if I use this space to clarify my thoughts....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Force and Assurance of the Soul</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2021.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2021</id>
    <issued>2026-01-04</issued>
    <modified>2026-01-04</modified>
    <summary>In his essay "Of the Rewards of Honour", Montaigne discourses on the "vain and in themselves valueless distinctions to honour and recompense virtue" that governments have instituted over the centuries: crowns of laurel, special uniforms, privileged seating, names, titles, coats of arms, and the like. Most commonly, these rewards of honor are used to encourage military valor among the citizenry. Montaigne then goes on to say:...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
