<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - philosopher, technologist, musician.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2025-12-27</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Workout #3</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2017.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2017</id>
    <issued>2025-12-27</issued>
    <modified>2025-12-27</modified>
    <summary>In this third and last installment of my Soul Workout, I address the two remaining questions derived from my reading of Eric Hoffer's book The Passionate State of Mind:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Workout #2</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2016.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2016</id>
    <issued>2025-12-26</issued>
    <modified>2025-12-26</modified>
    <summary>Continuing my Soul Workout, I've been reflecting on this question: "Am I less tolerant than I could be of other people's behavior and opinions?"...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Workout #1</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2015.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2015</id>
    <issued>2025-12-23</issued>
    <modified>2025-12-23</modified>
    <summary>Following up on my post about a Soul Workout, I've hit the spiritual gym and done some reflective reps on my personal practices. So far I've focused on three of the six questions I gleaned from Eric Hoffer's book The Passionate State of Mind:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Soul Workout</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2014.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2014</id>
    <issued>2025-12-21</issued>
    <modified>2025-12-21</modified>
    <summary>While reading Eric Hoffer's book The Passionate State of Mind, I came across some thought-provoking aphorisms about self-knowledge, self-deception, and personal identity. Here are the key sentences, which I've extracted and strung together for my own purposes:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophy and Psychology</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2013.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2013</id>
    <issued>2025-12-15</issued>
    <modified>2025-12-15</modified>
    <summary>Sometime in the next few weeks my friend Adrian Lory and I will hold a Substack Live video conversation about philosophy and psychology as complementary paths to wisdom and fulfillment. In preparation, I've been thinking up some questions about the relationship between philosophy and psychology, as well as their respective contributions to the good life. Here's what I have so far:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Change and Revolution</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2012.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2012</id>
    <issued>2025-12-14</issued>
    <modified>2025-12-14</modified>
    <summary>In his book First Things, Last Things, Eric Hoffer makes some observations about change and revolution:...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
