<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2022-01-17</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>MLK and Personalism</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1693.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1693</id>
    <issued>2022-01-17</issued>
    <modified>2022-01-17</modified>
    <summary>In my recent post on idealism and identity, I mentioned my attraction to the philosophy of personalism, with its emphasis on human dignity. It is perhaps a little-known fact that Martin Luther King, Jr., was greatly influenced by that very philosophy. Early in life he ventured north to study at Boston University, then the center of personalist thought in America, where he completed his doctorate under theologian Edgar Sheffield Brightman. We can see the deep influence of personalism on King's views in two quotes from his famous "I Have a Dream" speech:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Idealism and Identity</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1692.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1692</id>
    <issued>2022-01-15</issued>
    <modified>2022-01-15</modified>
    <summary>Personal identity is a deep, and deeply meaningful, subject: at some level, what's more important than what makes you you? Paradoxically, throughout history and across cultures, often personal identity has been a social construct, tied closely to tribe, clan, family, ethnic group, race, caste, class, societal role, and so on - usually in opposition to some Other ("I'm a Capulet, not a Montague", "I'm a proletarian, not a bourgeois", etc.)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Cultivating Curiosity</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1691.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1691</id>
    <issued>2022-01-08</issued>
    <modified>2022-01-08</modified>
    <summary>In my drive to hold fewer opinions (or at least hold them less strongly), for a while I tried to cultivate a healthy skepticism about things I believe - for instance, by attempting to question one opinion every week. This didn't work, at least for me, because it felt too negative. Instead, now I'm working to cultivate curiosity. Here are a few thoughts on the process....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Cultivating Empathy</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1690.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1690</id>
    <issued>2022-01-01</issued>
    <modified>2022-01-01</modified>
    <summary>If you ask those I work with or mentor what my distinctive personal qualities are, I suspect that on the short list you might find empathy. For instance, I often reach out to work colleagues if I know that they face significant challenges, if their skills aren't being fully utilized, if they're not appreciated as much as they should be, if someone on their team has resigned, or on the positive side if they've been doing great work....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Monadnock Valley Press Annual Report 2021</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1689.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1689</id>
    <issued>2022-01-01</issued>
    <modified>2022-01-01</modified>
    <summary>Happy Public Domain Day!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Questions and Answers</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1688.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1688</id>
    <issued>2021-12-29</issued>
    <modified>2021-12-29</modified>
    <summary>Consider the following statements... "There are no answers, only questions." "Life is all about the journey, not the destination." "A teacher or a counselor should encourage dialogue, not provide direction." All true as far as they go. And yet....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
