<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2023-04-20</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Writing as Thinking</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1777.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1777</id>
    <issued>2023-04-20</issued>
    <modified>2023-04-20</modified>
    <summary>Why write? I suppose there are many reasons: sharing your opinions, persuading others of your positions on issues, journaling through personal challenges, getting things off your chest, creating something beautiful, making a name for yourself, getting published, perhaps even generating income (good luck with that!)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Pursuit of Happiness</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1776.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1776</id>
    <issued>2023-04-13</issued>
    <modified>2023-04-13</modified>
    <summary>It's been said that America's three greatest contributions to world civilization are jazz, baseball, and the Declaration of Independence. Much as I like the first two, today is a fine day to ponder the third not only because it is Thomas Jefferson's birthday but also because this blog post is entry number 1776 in the online journal I've been keeping since November of 2000....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophy and Grief</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1775.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1775</id>
    <issued>2023-04-06</issued>
    <modified>2023-04-06</modified>
    <summary>Grieving is one of the characteristic activities of human beings. Although it seems that some other species (e.g., members of the corvid family) experience sorrow, grief is a more complex phenomenon. Recently I had occasion to read a fine book on the topic by Michael Cholbi, entitled Grief: A Philosophical Guide. Here are the essentials of what I gleaned....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Battle of the Bricks</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1774.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1774</id>
    <issued>2023-03-30</issued>
    <modified>2023-03-30</modified>
    <summary>Last year I decided to read War and Peace for the first time. Although Tolstoy's powers of psychological observation are amazing, I got stuck about halfway through (during a lengthy description of a fox hunt), and since then I haven't really been able to get back into it. It didn't help that none of the characters appealed to me strongly, perhaps because so many of them exhibit high levels of pretentiousness or self-deception - or both! Yes, 635 pages is a large investment of time, but getting from there to page 1386 feels like a tough slog and I'm not sure I have the energy....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Intellectual Jousting</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1773.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1773</id>
    <issued>2023-03-17</issued>
    <modified>2023-03-17</modified>
    <summary>In my recent post on intelligence vs. wisdom, I used the phrase "intellectual jousting" to describe the modern practice of doing philosophy. Here's a bit of psychological speculation about how that activity comes to be valued....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Intelligence vs. Wisdom</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1772.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1772</id>
    <issued>2023-03-17</issued>
    <modified>2023-03-17</modified>
    <summary>Ever since I left behind the high arrogance of my teenage years, I have valued wisdom over intelligence. This is likely why I'm much more drawn to the ancient conception of philosophy as a way of life than to the modern conception of philosophy as an exercise in argumentation....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
