<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2024-08-08</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics VI.5</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1890.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1890</id>
    <issued>2024-08-08</issued>
    <modified>2024-08-08</modified>
    <summary>In VI.5, Aristotle finally turns to a deeper analysis of phronēsis. I render this term as "wisdom", whereas others render it as "practical wisdom" (the standard these days), "practical judgment" (Joe Sachs), or "prudence" (prevalent in older translations). The wise person - the phronimos - is "able to deliberate beautifully about things that are good and advantageous, not in part, such as the sort of things that are conducive to health or strength, but the sort of things that are conducive to living well as a whole" (1140a25-28, Sachs translation). By the way, here "conducive" renders πρὸς, the same preposition we find in πρὸς τὸ τέλος, which is Aristotle's phrase for "that which takes us closer to completion" or "that which is toward the goal" - where the goal is living well as a whole, i.e., success [eupraxia] or fulfillment [eudaimonia]....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics VI.3-4</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1889.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1889</id>
    <issued>2024-08-04</issued>
    <modified>2024-08-04</modified>
    <summary>On the last section of our walk, we started to pick our way through a boulder-field of concepts that Aristotle introduced to kick off Book VI. Here we'll glance at two of those concepts: understanding [epistēmē] and craft [technē]. Aristotle's purpose here is not to examine these phenomena in detail, but to set up a contrast with wisdom [phronēsis] and sagacity [sophia], which will become the primary focus later in Book VI....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Homeric Similes</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1888.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1888</id>
    <issued>2024-08-04</issued>
    <modified>2024-08-04</modified>
    <summary>Having recently re-read both the Iliad and the Odyssey, I already find myself reading them yet again to more closely study various aspects of Homeric style. One of the things I've always enjoyed about the Homeric epics is the extended similes that liken events in the story to everyday experiences (indeed, I recall writing a paper about such similes for my Homer class with Laura Slatkin back in college). Here is an example from Book II of the Iliad as translated by Alexander Pope about 300 years ago:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Nicholas Dykes, RIP</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1887.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1887</id>
    <issued>2024-08-01</issued>
    <modified>2024-08-01</modified>
    <summary>Today I was saddened to learn, belatedly, that my friend Nicholas Dykes passed away earlier this year. Nick and I corresponded on and off for 25 years, ever since I published his poems "First Call of a Redwing" and "On Mynydd Troed" in The Monadnock Review, a webzine I maintained from 1997 to 2002. I was lucky to spend a few hours with him in person back in 2006 after the memorial service for British libertarian writer and activist Chris Tame, since I just happened to be London at that time and took the train down to Chichester for the event. Although Nick had strong opinions and took exception to my book The Tao of Roark (if I recall correctly, he thought it was repetitious and unenlightening), we always enjoyed sharing thoughts about philosophy and literature. I really liked his novel Old Nick's Guide to Happiness (a kind of philosophical adventure story) and was looking forward to the novel he was working on at the time of his death, about a lost island of Epicureans in the Indian Ocean. He will be missed. Rest in peace, my friend....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Reincarnation</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1886.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1886</id>
    <issued>2024-07-31</issued>
    <modified>2024-07-31</modified>
    <summary>No, not that kind of reincarnation. I refer instead to the mind tricks involved in fiction-writing. As I've been exploring the possibility of composing an epic poem about Pyrrho and Alexander (to date I've produced less than 200 lines, so don't get too excited!), I've treated it as if it were a translation of a lost work by Timon of Phlius, the best-known disciple of Pyrrho and a thinker who often wrote in a Homeric style. However, by no means am I expert in such matters, which is why I defer to the great Russian writer Yevgeny Zamyatin in his essay "On Language" (translated by Mirra Ginsburg):...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Shakespeare on Self-Knowledge and Self-Mastery</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1885.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1885</id>
    <issued>2024-07-30</issued>
    <modified>2024-07-30</modified>
    <summary>Having read all of Shakespeare over the last eight months, I find myself even more inspired to explore the philosophical insights embedded throughout the plays. As previously mentioned, in Romeo and Juliet Shakespeare calls philosophy "the sweet milk of adversity", since it provides us with consolation in hard times. Yet it also fortifies and prepares us for successful action and much else besides....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
