<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2022-04-28</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Wisdom and Freedom</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1712.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1712</id>
    <issued>2022-04-28</issued>
    <modified>2022-04-28</modified>
    <summary>Why do we continue to find such value in the life wisdom of ancient philosophers like Socrates, Aristotle, Confucius, Lao Tzu, Siddhartha Gautama, Epicurus, and Epictetus? It's not as if we're still reading Ptolemy on astronomy or even Euclid on geometry, so why have these philosophical insights endured?...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Exploring Social Space</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1711.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1711</id>
    <issued>2022-04-24</issued>
    <modified>2022-04-24</modified>
    <summary>One of the insights I find so intriguing from ecological psychology as developed by James and Eleanor Gibson is the concept of exploring visual space. Animals (including we humans) aren't simplistic sensory processing machines that are fixed to a point in space; instead, we are free to move around in order to see things from multiple perspectives....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Likeability</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1710.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1710</id>
    <issued>2022-04-21</issued>
    <modified>2022-04-21</modified>
    <summary>I seem to be getting into a rhythm of posting new thoughts on Thursdays - given my usual subject matter, we could think of this as "Thriving Thursday"......</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Social Affordances and Self-Conceptions</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1709.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1709</id>
    <issued>2022-04-14</issued>
    <modified>2022-04-14</modified>
    <summary>As I mentioned a few months ago in my post "Idealism and Identity", personal identity is, paradoxically, often a social construct. Here I'd like to dig more deeply into why that's the case, but without straying too far into theoretical matters because I like to provide practical insights in my blog posts....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Egoism, Altruism, and Oxygen Masks</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1708.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1708</id>
    <issued>2022-04-06</issued>
    <modified>2022-04-06</modified>
    <summary>A friend asked me recently if I think that self-improvement is selfish. My short answer was that building up your character is a matter of cultivating your higher self rather than gratifying your lower self, so this activity might exist beyond the dichotomy of egoism vs. altruism....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Meanings of Meaning</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1707.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1707</id>
    <issued>2022-03-28</issued>
    <modified>2022-03-28</modified>
    <summary>If you tell people that you're interested in philosophy, inevitably someone will ask you about the meaning of life. Although the question might predate The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy, ancient philosophers in the Greek, Indian, and Chinese traditions didn't raise it. Personally I adhere to the aphorism that it's best not to puzzle over the meaning of life, but instead work to create a life of meaning....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
