<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2022-12-26</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Monadnock Valley Press Annual Report 2022</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1754.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1754</id>
    <issued>2022-12-26</issued>
    <modified>2022-12-26</modified>
    <summary>This was a big year for uploading public-domain works to the Monadnock Valley Press - likely the biggest year since I founded the site in 2008. Indeed, I republished works by 50 authors: Dante Alighieri, Aristotle, Matthew Arnold, Jane Austen, John Burroughs, Thomas Campion, Willa Cather, Joseph Conrad, William Cowper, Frederick Douglass, John Dryden, George Eliot, E.M. Forster, Robert Herrick, Hesiod, Robert Hillyer, Langston Hughes, David Hume, Henrik Ibsen, William James, Robinson Jeffers, Ben Jonson, Emma Lazarus, Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, Lucretius, Christopher Marlowe, Herman Melville, John Stuart Mill, John Milton, Michel de Montaigne, Kakuzo Okakura, Richard Overton, Walter Pater, Plutarch, Sir Walter Raleigh, Laura Riding, Edwin Arlington Robinson, Bertrand Russell, William Shakespeare, Sophocles, Baruch Spinoza, Wallace Stevens, Sara Teasdale, Henry David Thoreau, Leo Tolstoy, Virgil, Voltaire, George Washington, John Greenleaf Whittier, and Xenophon. Whew!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Approaching Excellence</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1753.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1753</id>
    <issued>2022-12-21</issued>
    <modified>2022-12-21</modified>
    <summary>Aristotle is famous for his so-called doctrine of the mean: a particular excellence of character is not the opposite of a single fault (e.g., courage vs. cowardice) but is intermediate between excess and defect (e.g., courage is opposed to both rashness and cowardice). Although some scholars never go deeper than this surface understanding, as I see it "that which is intermediate" (τὸ μέσον) is merely a first approximation to excellence, because there's an awful lot of space in the middle between going far beyond the mean and falling far short of it....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Inner Revolution</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1752.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1752</id>
    <issued>2022-12-15</issued>
    <modified>2022-12-15</modified>
    <summary>One of the key themes of Tolstoy's War and Peace (which I'm currently reading for the first time) is self-deception. The reader quickly perceives that Nikolai Rostov, Andrei Bolkonsky, and many other characters are fooling themselves about their own worth, thoughts, and actions. There is a connection here to a famous quote from Tolstoy:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Effective Altruism and Ineffective Egoism</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1751.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1751</id>
    <issued>2022-12-08</issued>
    <modified>2022-12-08</modified>
    <summary>The collapse of Sam Bankman-Fried's crypto empire at FTX and Alameda Research has cast a shadow over the "effective altruism" movement, of which he was a major financer. Ironically, I would argue that in the end he failed at altruism because he was an ineffective egoist!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Mathematics of Freedom</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1750.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1750</id>
    <issued>2022-12-02</issued>
    <modified>2022-12-02</modified>
    <summary>While reading about the recent protests in China against the government's Zero Covid policy (and, more generally, the totalitarian surveillance state established by the Chinese Communist Party), I was reminded of a fascinating quote from logician Kurt Gödel extending the results of his Incompleteness Theorem to matters of society and governance:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Can a Nietzschean Be a Feminist?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1749.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1749</id>
    <issued>2022-12-01</issued>
    <modified>2022-12-01</modified>
    <summary>In one of my earliest blog posts (written in 1996!), I explained why I'm a female chauvinist. This attitude can be hard to square with my mostly positive perspective on Friedrich Nietzsche, which I explored in my book Songs of Zarathustra. After all, Nietzsche is notorious for spewing vitriol and venom regarding the role of women in modern society. Unfortunately, this is something that his admirers often prefer to sweep under the rug....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
