<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2025-04-13</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>The Nation of Many Nations</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1953.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1953</id>
    <issued>2025-04-13</issued>
    <modified>2025-04-13</modified>
    <summary>In Song of Myself, Walt Whitman declared himself to be "one of the great nation, the nation of many nations" - claiming identity as a northerner and a southerner, a Yankee, a Kentuckian, a Hoosier, a Badger, a Buckeye, and a habitan of numerous other places in North America. (Whitman contained multitudes, after all!)...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Four Causes of Fulfillment</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1952.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1952</id>
    <issued>2025-04-11</issued>
    <modified>2025-04-11</modified>
    <summary>Aristotle is famous, or infamous, for what is known as his doctrine of the four causes. As I’ve explained before, there are many misconceptions about these matters, but I’ll go with the traditional description for the purpose of this somewhat fanciful post about what causes an examined life of wisdom and fulfillment....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>He Who Pays the Piper Calls the Tune</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1951.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1951</id>
    <issued>2025-04-09</issued>
    <modified>2025-04-09</modified>
    <summary>Recently my alma mater, Columbia University, was back in the news because the Trump administration threatened to withhold $400 million in federal grants until the university changed some of its internal polocies. The political responses were predictable: populists were pleased about sticking it to leftist academics, faculty fulminated about threats to their intellectual freedom, the interim president lost her job over decisions she made, and a few folks quietly wondered about the wisdom of federal funding for so much educational activity and scientific research....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Where I Stand</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1950.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1950</id>
    <issued>2025-04-08</issued>
    <modified>2025-04-08</modified>
    <summary>Spurred by Garry Kasparov's call for a positive vision of the free society, Arnold Kling posted a list of the causes he is for. It seems like a good idea to reflect on these matters from time to time - perhaps especially at this time. Therefore - while recognizing both that I'm politically powerless and that my views have significance only for me - here I'll very briefly set out ten principles that I hold to be important in the political realm....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Talking vs. Thinking</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1949.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1949</id>
    <issued>2025-04-07</issued>
    <modified>2025-04-07</modified>
    <summary>A friend and I have begun a pair reading of The Faith of a Heretic by Walter Kaufmann. It's the second time through for both of us and we have mutual admiration for Kaufmann, so we're excited about digging into this most personal of Kaufmann's books on philosophy and religion....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle on Freedom</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1948.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1948</id>
    <issued>2025-03-31</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-31</modified>
    <summary>As mentioned two weeks ago in my note "Translation as Thinking", the concepts used across time and space (and, even, across writers) can vary quite significantly in the meanings they capture. This is especially true regarding concepts that are rather vague in the first place, such as virtue, happiness, democracy, and - the subject of today's post - freedom....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
