<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2024-07-13</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics IV.5-9</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1882.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1882</id>
    <issued>2024-07-13</issued>
    <modified>2024-07-13</modified>
    <summary>Following the intellectual drama of Aristotle's chapter on greatness of soul, the rest of Book IV covers gentleness (of which the contraries are an angry or docile disposition) and a few social excellences like benevolence, modesty, and wit. It might not be coincidental that all of these act as counterweights to the haughty arrogance we just witnessed in the great-souled man....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics IV.3-4</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1881.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1881</id>
    <issued>2024-07-11</issued>
    <modified>2024-07-11</modified>
    <summary>As hinted last time, Book IV, Chapter 3 of the Nicomachean Ethics has its oddities. Aristotle's discussion of greatness of soul (traditionally translated as "pride") has, I suspect, turned many people away from the valuable insights to be found throughout his writings because his "great-souled man" comes across as a haughty, arrogant prig that few of us would want as a friend....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Iambic Observations</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1880.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1880</id>
    <issued>2024-07-09</issued>
    <modified>2024-07-09</modified>
    <summary>If I do decide to write an epic poem about Pyrrho and Alexander the Great, I would do so in blank verse, i.e., in unrhymed iambic pentameter. Toward that end, recently I found myself re-reading All the Fun's in How You Say a Thing: An Explanation of Meter and Versification by Timothy Steele, one of my favorite living poets. This is an extremely helpful book for anyone who wants to write - or gain a greater appreciation for - metrical poetry in English, from Chaucer to the present day. Here are some of the lessons I learned this time around......</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Pyrrhiad</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1879.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1879</id>
    <issued>2024-07-09</issued>
    <modified>2024-07-09</modified>
    <summary>For some time now I've toyed with the idea of writing a novel (provisionally entitled Gods Among Men) about Alexander the Great and the founder of philosophical skepticism, Pyrrho. Having recently re-read both the Iliad and the Odyssey, I'm wondering if I could structure the story as an epic poem, almost as if it were translated from the work of an ancient Greek poet deeply influenced by Homer. Here's a draft of the standard invocation of the muse to start things off:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics IV.1-2</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1878.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1878</id>
    <issued>2024-07-08</issued>
    <modified>2024-07-08</modified>
    <summary>Next Aristotle turns to generosity. A more literal rendering of the Greek word ἐλευθεριότης might be "free-giving", since it is derived from ἐλευθερία, the Greek word for freedom. We'll talk more about freedom farther along in our walk with Aristotle, but for now it's worth noting that Aristotle's conception of freedom is not purely political but also includes personal aspects of character, behavior, and thinking....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics III.10-12</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1877.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1877</id>
    <issued>2024-07-02</issued>
    <modified>2024-07-02</modified>
    <summary>After his discussion of courage, Aristotle moves immediately to another of the traditional four virtues in ancient Greece: moderation. Although Aristotle never said that we should pursue moderation in everything, he did think that moderation is crucial to human fulfillment. Among other considerations, courage is paradigmatically displayed in war, but we engage in war only for the sake of peace; thus we need to understand and practice the character traits that maintain peace, among which moderation plays a central role....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
