<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2022-06-29</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>RFC 9280: RFC Editor Model</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1722.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1722</id>
    <issued>2022-06-29</issued>
    <modified>2022-06-29</modified>
    <summary>Every year the RFC Editor publishes hundreds of technical specifications in the Request for Comments (RFC) Series. But who or what is the RFC Editor? Originally it was one person: Jon Postel. Over the years the editing and publishing role has expanded to include a team of people at the RFC Publishing Center (RPC). In addition, the policy aspects, along with day-to-day troubleshooting of contentious issues that arise during publication, have been handled by a person with the title of RFC Series Editor (RSE). These various roles and responsibilities have been looked after (at a high level, anyway) by the RFC Series Oversight Committee (RSOC), which reports to the Internet Architecture Board (IAB), which has had ultimate authority over the evolution of this model. If it sounds confusing and perhaps a little opaque, that's because it is. Therefore, over the last few years the decided to revisit the underlying structure to improve transparency, clarify roles and responsibilities, and provide for greater community involvement. This work was completed through an open discussion process under the auspices of the IAB in the form of the RFC Editor Future Development Program. Because I'm a nice guy and because I'm good at helping to forge consensus, I volunteered to edit the Internet-Draft produced by this Program. The resulting document (of course it's an RFC, too!) has just been published as RFC 9280: RFC Editor Model (Version 3) - see my post at the IETF blog for more details....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Substitutions</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1721.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1721</id>
    <issued>2022-06-30</issued>
    <modified>2022-06-30</modified>
    <summary>Almost ten years ago I wrote a blog post about my "to-don't list": the things that I deliberately don't do, such as watch TV, follow the news, go shopping for fun, or spend time on social media. In my experience sometimes it's relatively easy to cease such activities, but other times I need to substitute one activity for another....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Socrates and Thoreau</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1720.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1720</id>
    <issued>2022-06-23</issued>
    <modified>2022-06-23</modified>
    <summary>My favorite quote from Henry David Thoreau runs as follows:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>That Flourishing Feeling</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1719.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1719</id>
    <issued>2022-06-16</issued>
    <modified>2022-06-16</modified>
    <summary>Positive psychology is sometimes perceived as putting a premium on pleasant experiences - what critics call "happiology". Yet just because pleasure is a positive experience doesn't mean it's the only positive experience!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Soul of Stoicism</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1718.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1718</id>
    <issued>2022-06-09</issued>
    <modified>2022-06-09</modified>
    <summary>People sometimes ask me what I think about Stoicism (not the phenomenon of physical and emotional fortitude, which I would call stoicism with a small "s", but the Greco-Roman philosophical school that has undergone a recent revival). At the risk of alienating those of my readers who lean in the direction of Stoicism, I've decided to write a few blog posts on the topic, starting with this one....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Being an Integrity</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1717.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1717</id>
    <issued>2022-05-27</issued>
    <modified>2022-05-27</modified>
    <summary>Yesterday while reading an old book on East Asian folk crafts (The Unknown Crafstman by Sōetsu Yanagi, p. 153), I came across the following passage:...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
