<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2020-07-13</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>The Power of Reflection</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1643.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1643</id>
    <issued>2020-07-13</issued>
    <modified>2020-07-13</modified>
    <summary>In a journal entry composed a few years ago on philosophy as a way of life, I observed:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Justifying Anger</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1642.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1642</id>
    <issued>2020-07-08</issued>
    <modified>2020-07-08</modified>
    <summary>In my last post, I extrapolated from the philosophy of Epicurus to indicate how to avoid unjustified anger and its less virulent siblings (annoyance, frustration, disappointment, etc.). Indeed, Epicurus seems to have been the first person to identify what centuries later became the seven deadly sins - one of which was anger....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophy and Anger</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1641.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1641</id>
    <issued>2020-06-19</issued>
    <modified>2020-06-19</modified>
    <summary>The world is full of anger, both well-founded and ill-founded. In a future post I'll talk about well-founded anger, but this time I'll provide some reflections on ill-founded anger....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Dialogue and Deliberation</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1640.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1640</id>
    <issued>2020-06-19</issued>
    <modified>2020-06-19</modified>
    <summary>One of Aristotle’s characteristic methods for solving philosophical problems is dialectic: upon (i) reaching an impasse (aporia), he (ii) surveys existing explanations (logoi) and reputable opinions (endoxa), (iii) engages in analysis to remove paradoxes and draw distinctions, then (iv) formulates a synthesis that harmonizes the explanations and saves the appearances (phainomena)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Crisis Investing</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1639.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1639</id>
    <issued>2020-05-28</issued>
    <modified>2020-05-28</modified>
    <summary>Exactly four years ago I wrote a post entitled "Investing for the Rest of Us", in which I discussed the permanent portfolio investing method, invented by Harry Browne. The permanent portfolio has two additional benefits that I've come to fully appreciate only this year: uncorrelated assets and forced rebalancing....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Serenity</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1638.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1638</id>
    <issued>2020-02-09</issued>
    <modified>2020-02-09</modified>
    <summary>Just as people used to ask me how I accomplish so much, recently a few people have asked me how I stay so serene. Although this question is harder to answer, I'll give it a try....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
