<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2021-04-10</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Bach on Bass #4: Instrumental Solution</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1665.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1665</id>
    <issued>2021-04-10</issued>
    <modified>2021-04-10</modified>
    <summary>After much research and some helpful input from double bassist Mark Stefaniw, the unofficial artistic advisor for my "Bach on Bass" project, I've chosen to buy a Stradi bass made by Marek Dąbek of Juliszew, Poland. Not only does Marek make absolutely gorgeous instruments, but he was excited to work with me on a design that met all my criteri: a four-string fretless bass with tapewound strings tuned in fifths, a very long fingerboard with a deep cutaway so that I can play intricate passages high up on the neck, a combination of piezo and magnetic pickups (the latter is important to enable experimentation with an eBow on certain pieces), and a chocolately tone that balances the best of electric and upright bass sounds. A long email thread with Marek led to a bass that is all oak, a wood we both love: roasted European oak for the body (chambered to enhance its acoustic properties), a hybrid through-body neck also in roasted oak, and both the fingerboard and top in 2000-year-old bog oak. Since Marek likes to name his basses, we're calling this one the "Mocha 4". The only bad part is that Marek is a true artisan who makes only 20 instruments a year and has a large backlog of orders, so I won't get my hands on the Mocha until early next year. But it's going to be worth the wait!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Holding Fewer Opinions</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1664.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1664</id>
    <issued>2021-04-06</issued>
    <modified>2021-04-06</modified>
    <summary>A few months ago I read the transcript of a discussion between Brian Beck and Robin Hanson, in which Hanson advised the listener to hold fewer opinions:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Politically Independent</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1663.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1663</id>
    <issued>2021-03-27</issued>
    <modified>2021-03-27</modified>
    <summary>Longtime readers of this weblog know that politically speaking I've always been more or less libertarian. (Little-known fact: many years ago I started a run for the House of Representatives on the Libertarian Party ticket, but my wife and I moved that year so I never got on the ballot.) Back in 2012 I thought that participating in the Republican Liberty Caucus might be effective because the county I live is solidly Republican, but once Trump was nominated for president in 2016 I switched my voter registration to Libertarian. After the recent election I decided to switch again, this time to Independent. Here's why....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>RFC 8838: Trickle ICE</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1662.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1662</id>
    <issued>2021-01-21</issued>
    <modified>2021-01-21</modified>
    <summary>Way back in 2005 some folks at Google and other parts of the Jabber community started to define a technology for setting up voice and video calls over XMPP, which we called Jingle. Unlike similar methods used in relation to SIP, Jingle enabled endpoints to dynamically gather and exchange potential connection paths for NAT traversal within context of the Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE). The original name for this was "dribbling" to differentiate it from the offer/answer method defined in RFC 3264 (wherein an endpoint needs to gather all of its candidate IP addresses up front before sending the offer). Over time the IETF defined a similar method for SIP, too, which we generalized under the name Trickle ICE. This week the IETF published a document cluster containing dozens of RFCs related to WebRTC, including RFC 8838 for Trickle ICE (which I co-authored with Emil Ivov of Jitsi and Justin Uberti of Google). Enjoy!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Bach on Bass #3: Instrumental Challenges</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1661.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1661</id>
    <issued>2021-01-12</issued>
    <modified>2021-01-12</modified>
    <summary>As mentioned last time, there are instrumental challenges involved with tuning an electric bass in fifths, as I plan to do in order to learn the Bach Cello Suites. Classical double bassists often solve the problem of the low C by installing a special extension. On electric bass, you can tune the E string down to C but that results in a low-tension string on the bottom and therefore a flabby tone. You could also play a 5-string bass (for which the lowest string sounds a B), I suppose, but to me that defeats the purpose and I have a strong preference for 4-string basses. You could swap out the low E string for the same low B string that that 5-string bassists use, but then the action (distance between string and fingerboard) isn't quite right. A further challenge for me is that the Minotaur bass I currently play (made by luthier Joe Veillette of Woodstock, NY) is a short-scale bass, and I haven't found anyone who makes that low B string in a short-scale version (I prefer D'Addario tapewound strings on the Minotaur)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Bach on Bass #2: Keys and Tunings</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1660.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1660</id>
    <issued>2021-01-06</issued>
    <modified>2021-01-06</modified>
    <summary>Many questions arise when considering how to climb the mountain of playing Bach's Cello Suites on electric bass. One of the key questions is the question of keys. The original keys for the six suites are G major, D minor, C major, E♭ major, C minor, and D major respectively. Other than the fourth suite, these keys lie naturally on the cello, which is tuned in fifths and whose open strings (from lowest to highest) are C-G-D-A. Thus five of the six suites can benefit from the harmonic resonance of open strings, which is especially important when playing the suites on a Baroque cello. (Those who play in a more Romantic style don't like the notes of the open strings because you can't generate the requisite vibrato.)...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
