<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2022-06-15</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Software is Eating Our Humanity</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1788.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1788</id>
    <issued>2022-06-15</issued>
    <modified>2022-06-15</modified>
    <summary>While reading Stefan Zweig's book The World of Yesterday recently, I came across the following quote:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Keeping It Brief</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1787.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1787</id>
    <issued>2022-06-09</issued>
    <modified>2022-06-09</modified>
    <summary>Epicurus once said: "Understand that a long discourse and a short one both achieve the same result." Although that's standard advice for writers (Yevgeny Zamyatin counselled "writing with 90-proof ink"), few follow it. Many books could have been long articles, many long articles could have been blog posts, and many blog posts could have been aphorisms. My journal entries average around 400 words these days, and I limit my books to around 100 pages. This is simple respect for you, the reader. Besides, I'd rather provoke difficult questions than provide definitive answers, because only you can answer those questions for yourself, anyway. Perhaps loving wisdom involves respecting your wisdom as much as my own......</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Socrates and Thoreau Revisited</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1786.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1786</id>
    <issued>2022-06-09</issued>
    <modified>2022-06-09</modified>
    <summary>Last year around this time I posted a few thoughts on Socrates and Thoreau, specifically regarding the likely influence of a passage in Book VI of Plato's Republic on Thoreau's attitude toward mere professors of philosophy, who unlike true philosophers do not live according to the dictates of wisdom. The other day, while re-reading key passages in Plato's dialogues as part of my research on Aristotle, I suddenly realized that on the very next page in the 1804 edition of Plato's works that Thoreau borrowed from Emerson can be found the inspiration for Thoreau's attitude toward the news, best encapsulated in an aphorism from his essay Life Without Principle: "Read not the Times. Read the Eternities."...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>George Winston, RIP</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1785.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1785</id>
    <issued>2023-06-07</issued>
    <modified>2023-06-07</modified>
    <summary>I was saddened yesterday to learn (via my friend Wayne Bethanis) that pianist-composer George Winston has died. Every solo performer of original music - not just pianists but guitarists and everyone else - owes him a debt of gratitude, for he was one of the few who blazed the trail of modern instrumental music, starting with his album Autumn in 1980. Although his music was often called "new age", he preferred the evocative term "rural folk piano". Many streams came together in his music: folk, blues, jazz, classical, rock, gospel, rhythm and blues, Hawaiian, and more. Yet he fused them into a seamless whole that was uniquely his own....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle on Fulfillment</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1784.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1784</id>
    <issued>2023-06-01</issued>
    <modified>2023-06-01</modified>
    <summary>The more deeply I ponder Aristotle's conception of eudaimonia (usually translated as "happiness" or more recently sometimes as "flourishing"), the more radical it seems....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ways of Life and Lines of Work</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1783.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1783</id>
    <issued>2023-06-01</issued>
    <modified>2023-06-01</modified>
    <summary>Because labor is so central to human existence, throughout history various thinkers have speculated about what the Buddhist eightfold path calls "right livelihood" for those who would seek and practice wisdom. For instance, both the Stoic Musonius Rufus and the Confucian Wu Yubi advocated subsistence farming as a noble line of work. The Taoist sage Chuang Tzu tells a beautiful story about the artistry of a lowly butcher. Although officially Aristotle downplayed the value of mechanical pursuits like housebuilding and even music-making, nevertheless he frequently used craftsmen as models of practical thinking and he applied the lessons of craftsmanship to ethical reflection. In recent times, Matthew Crawford titled one of his books "shop class as soul craft" and has argued that working in the trades enables you to bring your whole self to your productive activities. And so on....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
