<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - philosopher, technologist, musician.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2025-12-29</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Monadnock Valley Press Annual Report 2025</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2019.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2019</id>
    <issued>2025-12-29</issued>
    <modified>2025-12-29</modified>
    <summary>Following my tradition of posting on or about Public Domain Day, here is a brief report about this year's publishing activity at the Monadnock Valley Press, my website for writings in the public domain....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2025 Readings</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2018.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2018</id>
    <issued>2025-12-28</issued>
    <modified>2025-12-28</modified>
    <summary>In 2024 I read 95 books; although I didn't think I'd ever top that, in 2025 I somehow managed to read 116 books (more than two a week and almost ten a month). The downside is that for various reasons I didn't write my book on Aristotle, which I thought would absorb most of my energies. Instead I read a bunch of jazz biographies, historical tomes on American culture, some classic American literature, all the ancient Greek tragedies, philosophical treatments of various topics in ethics and aesthetics, and the usual smattering of poetry. Highlights were three original works of philosophy by Walter Kaufmann, three early novels by Willa Cather (my new favorite writer of fiction!), and wide-ranging explorations in music and aesthetics (especially Roger Scruton's Beauty, the collected nonfiction of Albert Murray, and Ellen Dissanayake's ethological analyses of art as a behavior in What Is Art For? and Homo Aestheticus)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Workout #3</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2017.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2017</id>
    <issued>2025-12-27</issued>
    <modified>2025-12-27</modified>
    <summary>In this third and last installment of my Soul Workout, I address the two remaining questions derived from my reading of Eric Hoffer's book The Passionate State of Mind:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Workout #2</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2016.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2016</id>
    <issued>2025-12-26</issued>
    <modified>2025-12-26</modified>
    <summary>Continuing my Soul Workout, I've been reflecting on this question: "Am I less tolerant than I could be of other people's behavior and opinions?"...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Workout #1</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2015.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2015</id>
    <issued>2025-12-23</issued>
    <modified>2025-12-23</modified>
    <summary>Following up on my post about a Soul Workout, I've hit the spiritual gym and done some reflective reps on my personal practices. So far I've focused on three of the six questions I gleaned from Eric Hoffer's book The Passionate State of Mind:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Soul Workout</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2014.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2014</id>
    <issued>2025-12-21</issued>
    <modified>2025-12-21</modified>
    <summary>While reading Eric Hoffer's book The Passionate State of Mind, I came across some thought-provoking aphorisms about self-knowledge, self-deception, and personal identity. Here are the key sentences, which I've extracted and strung together for my own purposes:...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
