<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2021-12-26</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Meditations on Bach #9: Musical Monadology</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1685.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1685</id>
    <issued>2021-12-26</issued>
    <modified>2021-12-26</modified>
    <summary>In meditation #7 of this series, I took note of some similarities between the aesthetics of Aristotle and the music of Bach. Another intriguing influence might be the monadology of Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz (1646-1716), who directly influenced philosophers and musical theorists in the Bach's orbit: for instance, Bach's student Lorenz Mizler (1711-1778) was a follower of the Leibniz scholar Christian Wolff (1679-1754). In chapter 5 of his book Music in the Culture of the Renassiance and Other Essays, Edward Lowinsky makes the following observations:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Friend by Any Other Name</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1684.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1684</id>
    <issued>2021-12-19</issued>
    <modified>2021-12-19</modified>
    <summary>It is said that when the ancient Greek philosopher Epicurus died, he left behind thousands of friends. This was 2300 years before Facebook, so how could he have befriended so many people?...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #17: Let the Re-Reading Begin</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1683.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1683</id>
    <issued>2021-11-28</issued>
    <modified>2021-11-28</modified>
    <summary>Just under two years ago, I thought I was done with phase one of my research into Aristotle's views o human flourishing, having at that point read around 120 distinct works by or related to Aristotle (including all of Plato's dialogues). Well, I was wrong: since then I've read an additional 150 works, almost exclusively in the scholarly literature on Aristotle. Now I have three whole shelves of books about Aristotle in my office....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophy vs. Ideology</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1682.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1682</id>
    <issued>2021-11-04</issued>
    <modified>2021-11-04</modified>
    <summary>Today I'd like to explore some implications of my recent series of posts about the nature of opinion; specifically, the dangers of ideology. (As a reminder, so far I've discussed holding fewer opinions, opinions about opinions, holding multiple opinions, opinions vs. truths, and opinions weak and strong.)...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Meditations on Bach #8: Two Quotes from Pablo Casals</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1681.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1681</id>
    <issued>2021-10-26</issued>
    <modified>2021-10-26</modified>
    <summary>Here are two quotes from the great cellist Pablo Casals, who re-introduced the Bach Cello Suites to the world in the early twentieth century......</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>There's No Such Thing as a Kudo</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1680.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1680</id>
    <issued>2021-10-17</issued>
    <modified>2021-10-17</modified>
    <summary>It always warms my heart when we import a word directly from ancient Greek into English. Often they are philosophical locutions, such as eudaimonia and ataraxia. Yet at times more mundane terms make the leap; these days perhaps the most common one is kudos (e.g., "kudos to you on aceing that algebra test!"). Consistent with modern English usage, people tend to pronounce it "koo-doze" and think of it as a plural ("that algebra test was really hard so you deserve many kudos for aceing it"). However, in ancient Greek κῦδος was pronounced "koo-doss" and was a singular noun (meaning fame, honor, renown). Just as we give praise (not "a praise") to a friend or colleague, so an ancient Greek might have given κῦδος. I'm sorry to disappoint you, but as a result there is no such thing as a kudo....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
