<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2023-09-08</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Consuming vs. Producing</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1821.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1821</id>
    <issued>2023-09-08</issued>
    <modified>2023-09-08</modified>
    <summary>During my Open Reading interview with Sal Inglima a few months ago, I mentioned my opinion that producing poetry is more fulfilling than reading poetry. Although this is an opinion that it might be best for me to let go of, before doing so I'd like to generalize and expand on the idea....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Frames of Mind</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1820.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1820</id>
    <issued>2023-08-31</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-31</modified>
    <summary>In my recent post about snares and attachments (and in my older post about idealism and identity), I observed that it's all too easy to become attached to one's opinions and ideas. In his book On the Wisdom of America (pp. 229-230), Lin Yutang makes a similar point with regard to what he calls frames of mind:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #18: Summaries</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1819.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1819</id>
    <issued>2023-08-31</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-31</modified>
    <summary>It's been almost two years since I last reported on progress with my forthcoming book about Aristotle's conception of human fulfillment, so here's a brief update. As mentioned last time, I'm working my way back through the key books and scholarly papers I've read so far. This involves reviewing thousands of dog-eared pages and marked-up passages to identify the most important points. Here's a photo that gives a sense of what that looks like (this shows pages 124 and 125 of Matthew D. Walker's excellent book Aristotle on the Uses of Contemplation)......</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tao Te Ching ยง56: One with the Way</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1818.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1818</id>
    <issued>2023-08-26</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-26</modified>
    <summary>Following up on my previous renderings of chapter 1 and chapter 11 of the Tao Te Ching, here is my initial attempt at chapter 56:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Attuning to Beauty</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1817.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1817</id>
    <issued>2023-08-22</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-22</modified>
    <summary>When describing recently my practice of daily forethought, I mentioned that every day I try to attune myself to the beauty of the world around me. This might sound pompous and grandiose because often we associate beauty only with the fine arts, but for me it's much more practical and prosaic. Here are some of the activities I engage in toward this end:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Snares and Attachments</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1816.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1816</id>
    <issued>2023-08-23</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-23</modified>
    <summary>Having posted enough semi-political entries of late to last me quite a while, it's time to return to reflections on living....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
