<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2019-02-07</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Virtues Ancient and Modern</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1621.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1621</id>
    <issued>2019-02-07</issued>
    <modified>2019-02-07</modified>
    <summary>In his book Confronting Aristotle's Ethics, Eugene Garver explores how, for Aristotle, personal excellence is also interpersonal excellence: because of the intensely social nature of ancient communities, virtues like courage and moderation had value because they protected and preserved the balance of the community as a whole. Thus courage was really valor in battle against another community that would have enslaved your own people, not the courage of principled resistance (e.g., Rosa Parks) or intellectual integrity (e.g., Galileo). Thus moderation was about controlling your urges (adultery upsets social harmony) and keeping in good physical condition (it's hard to be valorous if you're grossly overweight). And so on....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #7: φρόνησις</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1620.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1620</id>
    <issued>2019-02-05</issued>
    <modified>2019-02-05</modified>
    <summary>For Aristotle, the various excellences of character (courage, moderation, justice, and the like) are all instances of tending to find a balance between overdoing and underdoing a particular kind of action or feeling, either generally or in a particular respect (e.g., becoming angry in the wrong situations, toward the wrong kinds of people, too quickly, too strongly, etc.). Borrowing terminology from archery, he speaks of balance as a matter of hitting the target (σκοπός) and of imbalance as a matter of missing the mark (ἁμαρτία)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Personalism</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1619.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1619</id>
    <issued>2019-01-19</issued>
    <modified>2019-01-19</modified>
    <summary>In my philosophy department talk last October, I said something that might turn out to be more true than I had realized: it's a worthy ambition to become an accomplished person. Recalling that there used to be a philosophical journal called The Personalist, I've started to wonder if "personalism" might be an appropriate name for my approach to philosophy. A quick Internet search revealed that there has been a loose tradition of personalism over the last 200 years, encompassing thinkers as diverse as William James, Karol Wotyla (Pope John Paul II), and, appropriately enough for this weekend, Martin Luther King, Jr. (who studied with personalist theologian Edgar Sheffield Brightman at Boston University)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2018 Readings</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1618.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1618</id>
    <issued>2018-12-31</issued>
    <modified>2018-12-31</modified>
    <summary>Here's a list of the books I read in 2018 (including the complete works of Aristotle and a number of related scholarly books, along with a smattering of fiction):...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #6: A Second Look at the Eudemian Ethics</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1617.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1617</id>
    <issued>2018-12-11</issued>
    <modified>2018-12-11</modified>
    <summary>Aristotle wrote two treatises on ethics, which have come down to us as the Nicomachean Ethics or NE (in ten books) and the Eudemian Ethics or EE (in eight books). Confusingly, for reasons lost in the mists of time three of the books appear in both treatises (NE 5-7 = EE 4-6). Although until the commentary of Aspasius in the second century AD the EE was apparently considered to be the definitive statement of Aristotle's views, since then the NE has taken priority (so much so that many scholarly treatments of Aristotelian ethics completely ignore the EE). Yet detailed stylometric and textual analyses conducted by Anthony Kenny from the 1960s to the 1990s indicate that the three "common books" go with the EE, not the NE. It also seems likely (though so far not yet proven) that the EE was written after the NE, during the last eight years of Aristotle's life....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Investing in Life</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1616.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1616</id>
    <issued>2018-11-17</issued>
    <modified>2018-11-17</modified>
    <summary>Recently I got to talking with my friend Dave Jilk about happiness, flourishing, and my future book The Art of Living. While relating my ideas about the goals of life (as captured in a recent blog post), I described the importance of taking a balanced approach and including all or most of these goals in one's life pursuits. He likened this to portfolio management in investing, which is a great analogy. This spurred me to thinking further about the value that each area of life brings to one's overall success in life. Consider a few somewhat fanciful extensions of this analogy:...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
