<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2018-10-30</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Goals</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1614.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1614</id>
    <issued>2018-10-30</issued>
    <modified>2018-10-30</modified>
    <summary>There are many ways to categorize and divide up the various areas and activities of life. Here is a six-fold scheme I'm exploring:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Understanding Others</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1613.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1613</id>
    <issued>2018-10-26</issued>
    <modified>2018-10-26</modified>
    <summary>In my recent philosophy talk, I mentioned that thinking philosophically has helped me better understand people. This might seem counterintuitive - after all, don't big thinkers believe they have all the answers? Yes, I used to have that kind of arrogance, too. Yet over time I started to wonder: why do people have so many different opinions about things? Why have these various philosophies of life persisted for so long (Stoicism, Platonism, Buddhism, Taoism, etc.)? Why do I think what I think? Is it really in my control? At some level can you really "blame" people for the contents of their minds?...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophy Video</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1612.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1612</id>
    <issued>2018-10-19</issued>
    <modified>2018-10-19</modified>
    <summary>Video of my talk on philosophy as a foundation for success is now available, in two parts: the talk itself and the question-and-answer session. Thanks to Prof. Mitzi Lee for making the recording and posting it to YouTube!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #5: Three Forms of the Good</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1611.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1611</id>
    <issued>2018-10-12</issued>
    <modified>2018-10-12</modified>
    <summary>In Book Two, Chapter Three of the Nicomachean Ethics, Aristotle distinguishes three forms of the good: what is pleasurable or enjoyable (τό ἡδύ), what is useful or advantageous (τό συμφέρων), and what is right or beautiful (τό καλόν). In other places in his writings on both ethics and biology, he distinguishes three forms of reaching or desire (ὄρεξις): craving or appetite (ἐπιθυμία), feeling or passion (θυμός), and decision or will (βούλησις). Various interpreters (such as John Cooper in his book Reason and Emotion) have attempted to align these two sets of three, whereas other interpreters (such as Giles Pearson in his book Aristotle on Desire) have criticized such attempts as forced, misguided, and not supported by the textual evidence. Although I tend to agree with the integrators because I believe Aristotle was a fairly systematic thinker, I think Cooper's connection of θυμός with τό καλόν isn't right. Instead, it seems to me that craving or appetite is for the pleasant or enjoyable, feeling or passion is for the useful or advantageous, and decision or will is for what's right or beautiful....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>You're Majoring in What?!?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1610.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1610</id>
    <issued>2018-09-26</issued>
    <modified>2018-09-26</modified>
    <summary>On October 10th I'll give a talk entitled "You're Majoring in What?!? Why Philosophy is a Foundation for Success" at the University of Colorado Boulder (Hellems Arts and Sciences building, room 199, 6 PM). Although I don't believe it will be recorded, at the least I'll post the slides afterward. And if you live in the vicinity, feel free to stop by - I'll use my typical "performance art" presentation style, so it might even be mildly entertaining. :-)...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Foundations for Philosophical Practice</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1609.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1609</id>
    <issued>2018-09-24</issued>
    <modified>2018-09-24</modified>
    <summary>Recently I've revisited a field that's intrigued me for some time: philosophical counselling, or more broadly philosophical practice. Most of those active in this field are almost anti-method, and what methods they do employ are derived from hermeneutics, phenomenology, existentialism, Stoicism, and Socratic questioning - some of which I find interesting but none of which I find deeply congenial. Philosophical practice emerged in Europe around 1980 among thinkers influenced by hermeneutics and existentialism, and even the American philosophers in this area are mostly existentialists (associated with the American Philosophical Practitioners Association) or Stoics (associated with the National Philosophical Counseling Association) - for instance, Elliot Cohen, the progenitor of logic-based therapy, was a disciple of Albert Ellis (inventor of Rational Emotive Behavior Therapy). By contrast, my philosophical orientation is toward eudaimonia (the ancient Greek term for happiness, flourishing, living well) and the focus of my writing and living is on solving problems that hinder the pursuit of happiness. Upon reflection, I'm starting to see the possibility of developing a more joyous approach to philosophical practice that takes its inspiration from positive thinkers - especially the six I'm writing books about: Rand, Nietzsche, Aristotle, Thoreau, Epicurus, and Lao Tzu....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
