<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2021-10-17</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>There's No Such Thing as a Kudo</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1680.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1680</id>
    <issued>2021-10-17</issued>
    <modified>2021-10-17</modified>
    <summary>It always warms my heart when we import a word directly from ancient Greek into English. Often they are philosophical locutions, such eudaimonia and ataraxia. Yet at times more mundane terms make the leap; perhaps the most common one these days is kudos (e.g., "kudos to you on aceing that algebra test!"). Consistent with modern English usage, people tend to pronounce it "koo-doze" and think of it as a plural ("that algebra test was really hard so you deserve many kudos for aceing it"). However, in ancient Greek κῦδος was pronounced "koo-doss" and was a singular noun (meaning fame, honor, renown, praise). Just as we give praise (not "a praise") to a friend or colleague, so an ancient Greek might have given κῦδος. I'm sorry to disappoint you, but as a result there is no such thing as a kudo....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Opinions Weak and Strong</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1679.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1679</id>
    <issued>2021-09-24</issued>
    <modified>2021-09-24</modified>
    <summary>Continuing a thread that I started to explore earlier this year, I'd like to take a closer look at the intensity of opinions. Here as almost everywhere, there is a continuum: we all have opinions we hold strongly and opinions we hold weakly. Not only do the specific contents of these buckets change over time, but in general the intensity of one's opinions can change over time, too. We're all familiar with the sophomoric young adult who has strong opinions about everything (yes, I resembled that remark). Such an individual can be contrasted with the more mature person, who understands what truly matters in life and doesn't hold strong opinions about matters that are less important or positively unimportant....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What I've Learned from Aristotle</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1678.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1678</id>
    <issued>2020-09-12</issued>
    <modified>2020-09-12</modified>
    <summary>My friend Adrian Lory asked me recently to describe the essence of what I've learned from all of my Aristotle readings over the last few years as I prepare to write a book about his views on human flourishing. Here's a brief summary....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Meditations on Bach #7: Aristotle and Bach</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1677.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1677</id>
    <issued>2021-08-15</issued>
    <modified>2021-08-15</modified>
    <summary>On pp. 169-174 of his book Bach: The Learned Musician, Christoph Wolff describes the genesis of Bach's musical thinking. Of particular interest to me is his recounting of some insights from Johann Nikolaus Forkel, who founded the field of musicology and wrote the first biography of Bach in 1802. Wolff writes as follows....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #16: The Sources of Beauty</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1676.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1676</id>
    <issued>2021-08-15</issued>
    <modified>2021-08-15</modified>
    <summary>Aristotle uses the word καλός in both an aesthetic sense and an ethical sense. This has caused confusion among translators and commenters alike. Should the word be translated as "beautiful" when talking about art but as "right" or "fine" or "noble" when talking about character, intention, and action? Did Aristotle think that works of art were inextricably tied up with morality or that traits of character were aesthetic in some way? Let's look into the matter....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Meditations on Bach #6: Five Strings?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1675.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1675</id>
    <issued>2021-08-14</issued>
    <modified>2021-08-14</modified>
    <summary>Although the first five of Bach's suites for unaccompanied cello lie quite naturally on the bass (when tuned in fifths, that is!), the sixth suite in D major (BWV 1012) is a slightly different story because it was originally written for an instrument with an added string above the usual four. The exact identity of this instrument remains a mystery - some think it was written for a viola pomposa or viola de spalla, others for a violoncello piccolo (not that any of those instruments are well-understood). Whatever the truth of the matter, playing music written for a five-string instrument on a four-string instrument introduces new challenges: in particular, it requires intricate playing high up on the fingerboard. Modern cellists try to overcome this challenge through heavy use of thumb position, an innovation that post-dates Bach's lifetime; however, that doesn't make the task much easier. While working on the prelude to the sixth suite, I've realized that playing it on a five-string electric bass would make a lot of sense. Ideally such a bass would be tuned in fifths with a high E string, C-G-D-A-E. This seems achievable by using strings for a six-string bass and discarding one of the strings; for example, La Bella makes a six-string set normally tuned B-E-A-D-G-C and I would tune B up to C, discard the E string, tune A down a step to G, keep D as-is, tune G up a step to A, and tune C up two steps to E. After conferring with Marek Dąbek of Stradi Basses on whether the high E string will work, I'm happy to report that we're transforming the "Mocha 4" into a "Mocha 5"....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
