<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2025-03-06</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Inequalities</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1943.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1943</id>
    <issued>2025-03-06</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-06</modified>
    <summary>In an essay some weeks ago at Persuasion magazine entitled "Don't Just Let Radicals Dictate Your Opinions", professor of philosophy Matt Lutz listed three intellectual foundations for a more vibrant center-left political presence in America: "liberalism is the first principle"; "inequalities are problems to be solved"; and "absolutes are unwise"....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Beauty Trumps Evil</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1942.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1942</id>
    <issued>2025-03-05</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-05</modified>
    <summary>A friend of mine once said that good and evil live parallel lives. It's hard to deny that there are and always have been extremely bad people in the world - dictators, secret policemen, drug lords, gang leaders, terrorists, assassins, sex traffickers, and the like; yet one could be fortunate enough go through life without directly running up against such twisted specimens of humanity, even if one knows they exist out there somewhere....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Scaling the State</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1941.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1941</id>
    <issued>2025-03-04</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-04</modified>
    <summary>By no means do I have "the solution" for what ails the American body politic - as always, there are many causes (and many competing solutions) for our current predicament. And to be clear, I speak not about the day-to-day ins and outs of what's happening in the District of Columbia - who can keep track of it all? - but about longer-term trends. One of those trends is the ever-increasing centralization of governance at the national level....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Writing as Thinking</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1940.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1940</id>
    <issued>2025-03-03</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-03</modified>
    <summary>Why write? I can't speak for anyone else, but for me writing is a form of thinking. Although I often have vague notions floating around in my head, they don't crystallize until I formulate them in black and white. Before words can inform, they must be formed....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Joy of Creation</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1939.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1939</id>
    <issued>2025-03-02</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-02</modified>
    <summary>Several times now I've been exposed to "poems" generated by LLMs, whether sent to me by friends or posted by bloggers. Leaving aside their questionable quality, I would never use LLMs in this way. To me, the joy of creation lies not in the artifact but in the artistry. Would you prompt an LLM-equipped robot to attend a concert or sporting event on your behalf, take a walk with your child, or meet your best friend for lunch? I shudder to think that people might do such things before long. Similarly, writing poems, composing music, making pottery, and the like are not instances of drudgery but creative acts emblematic of the life of a free person....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>In Medias Res</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1938.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1938</id>
    <issued>2025-03-02</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-02</modified>
    <summary>(This post introduces my new Substack newsletter, Beautiful Wisdom.)...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
