<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2023-12-09</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Reality is Messy</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1835.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1835</id>
    <issued>2023-12-09</issued>
    <modified>2023-12-09</modified>
    <summary>The usually reasonable Arnold Kling, one of my favorite bloggers going back 25 years, has been using ChatGPT to build an essay-grading app and might have taken one too many sips of the Kool-Aid. Consider:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>An Aristotelian Glossary</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1834.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1834</id>
    <issued>2023-12-06</issued>
    <modified>2023-12-06</modified>
    <summary>Of late I've been working on the first serious contribution to my forthcoming book about Aristotle's conception of human fulfillment: a glossary of key terms. Those curious enough to peruse it will quickly discover that some of my renderings are rather non-standard. In my defense, usually these translations are rooted in ancient Greek etymology and usage or modern academic scholarship (e.g., both Aryeh Kosman and Myles Burnyeat recommended "understanding" instead of "knowledge" for epistēmē, as noted in my recent post "Understanding What You Know"); however, in a few instances I go farther out on a limb (e.g., "thriving" instead of "virtue" for aretē and, most centrally of all, "fulfillment" instead of "happiness" for eudaimonia). Although all of these renderings are subject to change, I'm quite satisfied with them so far (having pondered them for years) and in fact they provide a good indication of the interpretive direction I'm taking....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Understanding What You Know</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1833.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1833</id>
    <issued>2023-11-29</issued>
    <modified>2023-11-29</modified>
    <summary>Recently I discovered two ancient philosophy papers from the 1970s (by Aryeh Kosman and Myles Burnyeat) drawing a distinction between knowledge and understanding. As far as I can tell, Kosman was the first to propose that the Greek word epistēmē is best translated as understanding, and that in fact it means understanding how to explain what you know, in other words understanding why the thing you know is the way it is....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Economic Gratitude</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1832.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1832</id>
    <issued>2023-11-27</issued>
    <modified>2023-11-27</modified>
    <summary>Over the last few months I've been tutoring a Ukrainian mom in English as a Second Language through my local library. Several weeks ago she asked me how Americans navigate the world of saving and investment, so I sent her links to one or two of my own blog posts as well as a number of more professional resources. We also had an hourlong discussion about the economic and legal infrastructure for investment that exists in America: stock markets, mutual funds, ETFs, Treasury bills, federal and municipal bonds, REITs, precious metals, commodities, futures markets, 401(k) plans, IRAs, 529 accounts, and all the rest. Folks in the Ukraine and many other countries around the world simply don't have (relatively) trusted investment vehicles like this; in all likelihood, their primary investment method is putting cash under the pillow. We don't realize how fortunate we are to have so many ways to build wealth....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Primacy of the Prompt</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1831.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1831</id>
    <issued>2023-11-16</issued>
    <modified>2023-11-16</modified>
    <summary>While re-reading Robert Sokolowski's excellent book Phenomenology of the Human Person recently, I came across a fascinating quote from Derek Bickerton's book Language and Human Behavior:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tragedy vs. Atrocity</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1830.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1830</id>
    <issued>2023-11-16</issued>
    <modified>2023-11-16</modified>
    <summary>Ever since the 9/11 terrorist attacks, I've been bothered by a point of language. All too often (most recently in relation to the October 7 pogrom in Israel), people say that such events are a tragedy, but this is not correct because it implicitly relieves the participants of moral responsibility. A pogrom, a massacre, a terrorist attack, a genocide - these are not tragedies, they are atrocities. Yes, it's a tragic situation that, say, there was until very recently an Armenian exclave within the borders of Azerbaijan; but the act of forcibly expelling those Armenians was an atrocity. The same applies to pogroms of Russian Jews in the 19th and 20th centuries, Turkey's genocide of Armenians during World War I, the Holocaust against European Jews carried out by Nazi Germany with the collaboration of other fascist regimes, the Rwandan genocide of Tutsi people by Hutu militias in 1994, and so many other acts of collective violence throughout human history. We could even say it's tragic that human beings are so prone to atrocities, but moral responsibility for the atrocities themselves must be assigned to the people who instigate and participate in them. Precision on this point is extremely important, as a matter of both linguistic accuracy and ethical clarity....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
