<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2025-10-17</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>A Letter</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2000.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2000</id>
    <issued>2025-10-17</issued>
    <modified>2025-10-17</modified>
    <summary>Yesterday I penned a letter to my best friend. And I do mean penned: after rummaging around in a box stashed in a closet, I tracked down some fine stationery I'd bought years ago and, pen in hand, sat down to write. Having been away from letter-writing for decades, I was reminded of a few long-forgotten essentials:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Socrates and Thoreau on True Wealth</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1999.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1999</id>
    <issued>2025-10-14</issued>
    <modified>2025-10-14</modified>
    <summary>On this day in 1857, Thoreau wrote as follows in his journal:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Private, Personal, Practical, Passionate, Particular</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1998.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1998</id>
    <issued>2025-10-10</issued>
    <modified>2025-10-10</modified>
    <summary>Following a gap of nearly forty years (!), I'm re-reading Alasdair MacIntyre's influential book After Virtue. As I do so, I'll post occasionally on the reflections it inspires....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Soulcraft</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1997.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1997</id>
    <issued>2025-10-05</issued>
    <modified>2025-10-05</modified>
    <summary>Aristotle wrote three books with "ethics" (ἠθική) in the title, where the word ἠθική is derived from the Greek word for character (ἦθος). Yet to modern ears, "ethics" brings to mind commandments, guardrails, and other restrictions on behavior. Thus arises the question: how best to render the word ἠθική into English?...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Biscuit Wood</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1996.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1996</id>
    <issued>2025-10-02</issued>
    <modified>2025-10-02</modified>
    <summary>With winter preparations already underway here (I don't want to get caught flatfooted as happened last year when we were hit with three feet of snow in the first week of November), I was reminded of a story that Henry David Thoreau related in his journal on December 15th, 1859:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Bushwhacking</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1995.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1995</id>
    <issued>2025-10-01</issued>
    <modified>2025-10-01</modified>
    <summary>One of the differences, I'm finding, between public philosophy and private philosophy is that the former is full of well-established trails, whereas the latter is largely an unexplored territory in which bushwhacking is required if you want to blaze a path to wisdom. For instance, there are probably hundreds of books on a typical public philosophy topic like free will vs. determinism, whereas there are few if any about, say, understanding and navigating the varieties of grieving....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
