<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2024-02-05</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Called to Account</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1849.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1849</id>
    <issued>2024-02-05</issued>
    <modified>2024-02-05</modified>
    <summary>In Plato's dialogue Laches, Lysimachus and Melesias are searching for someone to teach their sons about courage, so they engage the Athenian generals Laches and Nikias in conversation, with Socrates participating alongside. Socrates encourages Lysimachus to seek an account (logos) of virtue from Laches and Nikias, since they are older and presumably wiser than Socrates himself. When Lysimachus agrees that this is a good idea, Nikias makes a fascinating observation:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Crafty</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1848.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1848</id>
    <issued>2024-01-27</issued>
    <modified>2024-01-27</modified>
    <summary>Aristotle is well-known for having pioneered our vocabulary of potentiality and actualization. An especially meaningful form of human potentiality or capacity is what he calls a hexis: a stable, voluntarily acquired trait that, when applied, results in reliable activity of a certain kind. Aristotle identifies three such primary traits in human life: virtue or excellence of character (aretē), knowledge or understanding (epistēmē), and craft or skill (technē)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Does Everyone Have a Philosophy of Life?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1847.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1847</id>
    <issued>2024-01-18</issued>
    <modified>2024-01-18</modified>
    <summary>In the spirit of questioning my beliefs and reducing the number of opinions I hold, lately I've been wondering about something I've always assumed: that everyone has a philosophy of life....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Truth, Goodness, Beauty</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1846.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1846</id>
    <issued>2024-01-13</issued>
    <modified>2024-01-13</modified>
    <summary>As I've noted before, the unity of truth, good, and beauty is close to the heart of the Socratic-Platonic-Aristotelian tradition. That's because the highest thing we can know or understand is not the world or even ourselves, but the good. Socrates realized this when he turned away from natural philosophy to the consideration of human affairs. For Aristotle, an understanding of the human good is the key to avoiding the extremes of foolishness and cunning, and thus achieving wisdom or φρόνησις; and an understanding of the divine (the good in its purest form) is the key to avoiding the extremes of ignorance and sophistry or deception, and thus achieving sagacity or σοφία....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Freed from Need</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1845.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1845</id>
    <issued>2024-01-02</issued>
    <modified>2024-01-02</modified>
    <summary>A few months ago, two different people reached out to me about editing their respective books. The first person was someone I had worked with for several years, whom I liked and respected, who had a complete manuscript that although in need of editing was in decent shape, and who was respectful of my time and fairly flexible about schedule. The second person was someone who contacted me out of the blue, who hadn't put in the effort to make his manuscript as good as he was able to on his own, who wanted a quick turnaround, and who was kind of passive-aggressive about working together; he seemed to think that offering to pay me would make up for these failings, and indeed he was almost offended when I told him that I don't charge to edit people's books....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Monadnock Valley Press Annual Report 2023</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1844.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1844</id>
    <issued>2023-12-28</issued>
    <modified>2023-12-28</modified>
    <summary>In contrast to 2022, when I republished works by fifty authors, 2023 was a slow year at the Monadnock Valley Press. In retrospect, the focus seems to have been English-language poets old and new (or as new as copyright expiration laws will allow). In chronological order of authors' birthdates, that would be:...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
