<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2022-09-08</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Means and Ends</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1734.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1734</id>
    <issued>2022-09-08</issued>
    <modified>2022-09-08</modified>
    <summary>Last week we looked at the distinction between internal goods, external goods, and shared goods. At that time I touched on a further distinction between means and ends in life. Here again Aristotle can be of assistance, because he discusses these matters in his two major books about character and action, which have come down to us as the Nicomachean Ethics and the Eudemian Ethics....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Good Things Come in Threes</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1733.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1733</id>
    <issued>2022-09-01</issued>
    <modified>2022-09-01</modified>
    <summary>In my recent post "There's No Such Thing as the Mind", I expressed astonishment at a statement by Italian philosopher Maurizio Ferraris to the effect that one's body is part of the external world. This raises the question of what exactly is internal vs. external, and how to categorize the various good things we value in life....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Thoughts, Actions, Values</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1732.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1732</id>
    <issued>2022-08-25</issued>
    <modified>2022-08-25</modified>
    <summary>Aristotle's Nicomachean Ethics famously begins with the following sentence (as translated by W.D. Ross):...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Meditations on Bach #11: Mocha 5 Bass</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1731.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1731</id>
    <issued>2022-08-23</issued>
    <modified>2022-08-23</modified>
    <summary>I'm delighted to report that today I took delivery of a custom-made Symphony electric bass from Stradi Basses in Poland. It is absolutely gorgeous, sounds wonderful, and plays beautifully! Luthier Marek Dąbek was a dream to work with and he met all of my requirements with true craftsmanship and creativity, building with the expert assistance of his wife Agnieska an instrument we're calling the "Mocha 5". I now have a magnificent five-string bass, natively tuned in fifths using custom strings by Italian string maker Galli, that will provide a strong foundation for my transcriptions of the Bach Cello Suites (as well as some original solo bass pieces I'm composing). Wow! Thank you, Marek and Agnieska!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It's Values All the Way Down</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1730.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1730</id>
    <issued>2022-08-18</issued>
    <modified>2022-08-18</modified>
    <summary>One often hears the claim that science must be value-neutral, especially in social sciences like economics, psychology, and sociology. This claim is one instance of fact-value dualism: the doctrine that facts are facts, values are values, and never the twain shall meet. Another instance of this dualism is the assertion (traceable to British empiricist David Hume) that you can't derive an "ought" from an "is"....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>There's No Such Thing as the Mind</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1729.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1729</id>
    <issued>2022-08-11</issued>
    <modified>2022-08-11</modified>
    <summary>Not long ago, a friend recommended that I check out the work of Italian philosopher Maurizio Ferraris, so I promptly ordered his book Manifesto of New Realism via interlibrary loan. Overall it is a valiant attempt to dig out of the hole of postmodernism - valuable, at the very least, for those who have fallen into that particular hole in the first place. Ferraris identifies one aspect of the constraints I talked about recently, in the form of what he calls "unamendability" (i.e., the fact that some aspects of reality cannot be changed by human wishes and ideas). On page 35 of the English translation, he writes:...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
