<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2025-05-26</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Self-Deception</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1965.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1965</id>
    <issued>2025-05-26</issued>
    <modified>2025-05-26</modified>
    <summary>One of my personal aphorisms is: "The easiest thing in the world is self-deception."...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Step by Step</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1964.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1964</id>
    <issued>2025-05-24</issued>
    <modified>2025-05-24</modified>
    <summary>Combining threads from recent posts on Spinoza and on Walter Kaufmann, here are a few further thoughts on intellectual honesty and philosophical methodology....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Whence Wonder?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1963.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1963</id>
    <issued>2025-05-23</issued>
    <modified>2025-05-23</modified>
    <summary>Socrates, Plato, and Aristotle held that philosophy - the love and practice of wisdom - begins in wonder. But whence wonder?...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Reading Spinoza</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1962.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1962</id>
    <issued>2025-05-22</issued>
    <modified>2025-05-22</modified>
    <summary>Over the last few weeks I've been re-reading Spinoza's Ethics yet again, this time inspired by a review of Kieran Fox's newly-published spiritual biography of Einstein, which noted that when pressed about his religious beliefs the great scientist claimed to believe in Spinoza's God....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Freedom of Screech</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1961.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1961</id>
    <issued>2025-05-13</issued>
    <modified>2025-05-13</modified>
    <summary>My alma mater, Columbia University, was back in the news yet again last week because some screeching students took over parts of Butler Library while serious students were preparing for final exams. The details are unimportant in this context; instead I'm puzzled by what passes for speech these days....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Intellectual Honesty</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1960.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1960</id>
    <issued>2025-05-08</issued>
    <modified>2025-05-08</modified>
    <summary>In his book The Faith of a Heretic, Walter Kaufmann spells out an ethic of intellectual honesty. (The book covers many other topics, but that's the core of it.) He sets admirably high standards for himself and anyone else who would, in the words of his fellow philosopher Jan Patočka, live in truth. As Kaufmann presents it, intellectual honesty is a challenging virtue because we're all liable to limit ourselves to the comfortable confines of what we already know - or think we know....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
