<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2025-03-15</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>The Divinity of Being</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1945.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1945</id>
    <issued>2025-03-15</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-15</modified>
    <summary>While continuing my travels in the land of Aristotle (specifically, entering passages from his Metaphysics into my digital commonplace book), I chanced recently upon the shoreline of the vast ocean of theology. Knowing that I would quickly drown if I ventured too far from shore, I merely picked up a few seashells, waded in up to my knees, and enjoyed the view of the endless depths. Even though these are mostly uncharted waters for me (despite a few related posts almost twenty years ago), I'll give a short report on my excursion....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Romanticism or Renaissance?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1944.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1944</id>
    <issued>2025-03-08</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-08</modified>
    <summary>Both Ted Gioia and Ross Barkan (among others) have observed cultural stirrings that indicate we might be moving away from rationalism, in ways similar to the sea change from Enlightenment to Romanticism around 1800. Count me intrigued....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Inequalities</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1943.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1943</id>
    <issued>2025-03-06</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-06</modified>
    <summary>In an essay some weeks ago at Persuasion magazine entitled "Don't Just Let Radicals Dictate Your Opinions", professor of philosophy Matt Lutz listed three intellectual foundations for a more vibrant center-left political presence in America: "liberalism is the first principle"; "inequalities are problems to be solved"; and "absolutes are unwise"....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Beauty Trumps Evil</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1942.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1942</id>
    <issued>2025-03-05</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-05</modified>
    <summary>A friend of mine once said that good and evil live parallel lives. It's hard to deny that there are and always have been extremely bad people in the world - dictators, secret policemen, drug lords, gang leaders, terrorists, assassins, sex traffickers, and the like; yet one could be fortunate enough go through life without directly running up against such twisted specimens of humanity, even if one knows they exist out there somewhere....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Scaling the State</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1941.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1941</id>
    <issued>2025-03-04</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-04</modified>
    <summary>By no means do I have "the solution" for what ails the American body politic - as always, there are many causes (and many competing solutions) for our current predicament. And to be clear, I speak not about the day-to-day ins and outs of what's happening in the District of Columbia - who can keep track of it all? - but about longer-term trends. One of those trends is the ever-increasing centralization of governance at the national level....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Writing as Thinking</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1940.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1940</id>
    <issued>2025-03-03</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-03</modified>
    <summary>Why write? I can't speak for anyone else, but for me writing is a form of thinking. Although I often have vague notions floating around in my head, they don't crystallize until I formulate them in black and white. Before words can inform, they must be formed....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
