<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2024-09-24</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics VII.11-14</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1903.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1903</id>
    <issued>2024-09-24</issued>
    <modified>2024-09-24</modified>
    <summary>Early on in the Nicomachean Ethics, Aristotle observed that thrivings and corruptions of character are centrally concerned with managing life's pleasures and pains, joys and distresses; as two examples, the cowardly person fails to act courageously out of a desire to avoid even necessary pains, whereas the decadent person fails to act moderately out of a desire to pursue even unnecessary pleasures. Here in Book VII, Aristotle expands on those observations and provides a stronger foundation for his claims....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics VII.1-10</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1902.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1902</id>
    <issued>2024-09-21</issued>
    <modified>2024-09-21</modified>
    <summary>At the end of Nicomachean Ethics Book VI, Aristotle sketched out an ideal of human flourishing, in the form of the seriously good person who seamlessly combines excellence of mind and character, practical wisdom [phronēsis] and ethical thriving [aretē]. Yet human experience is not always so seamless. There are many ways to go astray in life, which in Book VII Aristotle boils down to three: corruption [mochthēria] of character, lack of self-restraint [akrasia], and, rarely, a deficient state that borders on an animal-like existence [theriotēs]....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tao Te Ching §33: Know Yourself</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1901.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1901</id>
    <issued>2024-09-17</issued>
    <modified>2024-09-17</modified>
    <summary>Here's another of my renderings from the Tao Te Ching:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics VI.12-13</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1900.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1900</id>
    <issued>2024-09-15</issued>
    <modified>2024-09-15</modified>
    <summary>In the final two chapters of Nicomachean Ethics Book VI, Aristotle asks some probing questions about thrivings of mind and character....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Information vs. Wisdom</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1899.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1899</id>
    <issued>2024-09-10</issued>
    <modified>2024-09-10</modified>
    <summary>The world is awash with information. Some information is misinformation (falsehoods), and some misinformation is disinformation (deliberate falsehoods), but all of it is stuff that needs to processed in order to be useful, otherwise it's not much better than gossip or rumor....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Homeric Ambiguity</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1898.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1898</id>
    <issued>2024-09-08</issued>
    <modified>2024-09-08</modified>
    <summary>One of the many fascinating aspects of both the Iliad and the Odyssey is the fundamental ambiguity of Homer's stories. Is the Iliad a great war poem - or a great anti-war poem? Is Achilles really the hero of the Iliad, or is it perhaps Hector (whose death and funeral mark the end of the poem)? Are the gods the sources and enforcers of justice, or are they just as often capriciously unjust (e.g., in causing the ten-year wanderings of Odysseus after the Trojan War)? And so on....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
