<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2021-01-21</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>RFC 8838: Trickle ICE</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1662.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1662</id>
    <issued>2021-01-21</issued>
    <modified>2021-01-21</modified>
    <summary>Way back in 2005 some folks at Google and other parts of the Jabber community started to define a technology for setting up voice and video calls over XMPP, which we called Jingle. Unlike similar methods used in relation to SIP, Jingle enabled endpoints to dynamically gather and exchange potential connection paths for NAT traversal within context of the Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE). The original name for this was "dribbling" to differentiate it from the offer/answer method defined in RFC 3264 (wherein an endpoint needs to gather all of its candidate IP addresses up front before sending the offer). Over time the IETF defined a similar method for SIP, too, which we generalized under the name Trickle ICE. This week the IETF published a document cluster containing dozens of RFCs related to WebRTC, including RFC 8838 for Trickle ICE (which I co-authored with Emil Ivov of Jitsi and Justin Uberti of Google). Enjoy!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Bach on Bass #3: Instrumental Challenges</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1661.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1661</id>
    <issued>2021-01-12</issued>
    <modified>2021-01-12</modified>
    <summary>As mentioned last time, there are instrumental challenges involved with tuning an electric bass in fifths, as I plan to do in order to learn the Bach Cello Suites. Classical double bassists often solve the problem of the low C by installing a special extension. On electric bass, you can tune the E string down to C but that results in a low-tension string on the bottom and therefore a flabby tone. You could also play a 5-string bass (for which the lowest string sounds a B), I suppose, but to me that defeats the purpose and I have a strong preference for 4-string basses. You could swap out the low E string for the same low B string that that 5-string bassists use, but then the action (distance between string and fingerboard) isn't quite right. A further challenge for me is that the Minotaur bass I currently play (made by luthier Joe Veillette of Woodstock, NY) is a short-scale bass, and I haven't found anyone who makes that low B string in a short-scale version (I prefer D'Addario tapewound strings on the Minotaur)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Bach on Bass #2: Keys and Tunings</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1660.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1660</id>
    <issued>2021-01-06</issued>
    <modified>2021-01-06</modified>
    <summary>Many questions arise when considering how to climb the mountain of playing Bach's Cello Suites on electric bass. One of the key questions is the question of keys. The original keys for the six suites are G major, D minor, C major, E♭ major, C minor, and D major respectively. Other than the fourth suite, these keys lie naturally on the cello, which is tuned in fifths and whose open strings (from lowest to highest) are C-G-D-A. Thus five of the six suites can benefit from the harmonic resonance of open strings, which is especially important when playing the suites on a Baroque cello. (Those who play in a more Romantic style don't like the notes of the open strings because you can't generate the requisite vibrato.)...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Bach on Bass #1: Wonder</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1659.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1659</id>
    <issued>2021-01-05</issued>
    <modified>2021-01-05</modified>
    <summary>Wonder is what I've long felt about Bach's Suites for Unaccompanied Cello. I'm not sure when I first heard them, but over time they have become ever more meaningful to me. I regularly listen to various recorded renditions; some of my favorites are by Stephen Isserlis (cello), Patricia McCarty (viola), Edgar Meyer (double bass), Michael Nicolella (guitar), Jean-Guihen Queyras (cello), Hopkinson Smith (lute), Janos Starker (cello), and Pieter Wispelwey (cello). So far, that is - I'm actively adding more recordings to my collection as I explore these works ever more deeply....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Monadnock Valley Press Annual Report 2020</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1658.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1658</id>
    <issued>2021-01-01</issued>
    <modified>2021-01-01</modified>
    <summary>Apparently I got out of the habit of writing a brief "annual report" for the Monadnock Valley Press, under whose auspices I both post public-domain texts (at monadnock.net) and publish the philosophy books I write on the side. So it's about time to remedy the oversight, since the last report was for 2016....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2020 Readings</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1657.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1657</id>
    <issued>2020-12-31</issued>
    <modified>2020-12-31</modified>
    <summary>Despite pandemic lockdowns and such, I read only ~75 books this year (granted, a third of them were dense works of philosophical scholarship on Aristotle). In 2021 I hope to finish the remaining dozen or so books I need to read in preparation for writing an epitome of Aristotle's ethics; I also hope to include a more generous helping of literature, modern science, and history. Several of the following books are available online at monadnock.net (the site where I post books that are in the public domain); see the end of this post for links....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
