<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2023-12-18</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Do We Need the Concept of a Concept?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1840.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1840</id>
    <issued>2023-12-18</issued>
    <modified>2023-12-18</modified>
    <summary>As mentioned last month, I'm slowly re-reading Robert Sokolowski's book Phenomenology of the Human Person with a friend of mine. When I first wrote about this book four years ago, I noted that Sokolowski "explains the epistemology of reason in the context of human conversation: by embracing the back and forth of speech ... he sidesteps the ever present dangers of solipsism and mental representationalism." As a point of comparison, in her book Introduction to Objectivist Epistemology, Ayn Rand says that a child independently formulates the concept of, say, a tree in his or her own mind by observing trees in reality. However, on this account we need to add communication as a separate capacity on top of concept-formation so that we can explain how the child associates the word 'tree' with the concept....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophy vs. Philosophies</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1839.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1839</id>
    <issued>2023-12-14</issued>
    <modified>2023-12-14</modified>
    <summary>On the very first page of his book What Is Ancient Philosophy?, Pierre Hadot — the late French scholar who almost singlehandedly resurrected the humanistic conception of philosophy as a way of life — drew a distinction between individual philosophies on the one hand and philosophy itself on the other:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>More on Ancient Friends</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1838.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1838</id>
    <issued>2023-12-13</issued>
    <modified>2023-12-13</modified>
    <summary>A mere two nights after quoting Niccolò Machiavelli's reflections on his ancient friends, I came upon a similar passage in Essays in Idleness, written by the Japanese poet-monk Yoshida Kenkō around the year 1330. Here's what Kenkō had to say, in the translation by Donald Keene:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Planning to Be Old</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1837.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1837</id>
    <issued>2023-12-12</issued>
    <modified>2023-12-12</modified>
    <summary>Earlier this year at a family gathering, I overheard an uncle of mine (who is in his late 80s) say something in passing to one of his siblings about the importance of planning to be old. This set me to thinking: what might such planning involve? Here are some possible considerations:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ancient Friends</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1836.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1836</id>
    <issued>2023-12-10</issued>
    <modified>2023-12-10</modified>
    <summary>On this day 510 years ago (December 10th, 1513), Niccolò Machiavelli wrote a now-famous letter to his friend Francesco Vettori about his life in exile from Florence - and about a little book he was writing, which has come down to us as The Prince. After relating what had happened that day on his farm and in the village, he described his evening routine, when he would "visit" with Plutarch, Polybius, Livy, Aristotle, and other great minds of antiquity:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Reality is Messy</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1835.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1835</id>
    <issued>2023-12-09</issued>
    <modified>2023-12-09</modified>
    <summary>The usually reasonable Arnold Kling, one of my favorite bloggers going back 25 years, has been using ChatGPT to build an essay-grading app and might have taken one too many sips of the Kool-Aid. Consider:...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
