<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2024-10-13</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Beowulf</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1910.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1910</id>
    <issued>2024-10-13</issued>
    <modified>2024-10-13</modified>
    <summary>As part of my background research for composing an epic poem about Pyrrho, I'm reading epics from around the world. So far this year I've read both the Iliad and the Odyssey twice (in Richmond Lattimore's masterful translations), Milton's Paradise Lost, the Argonautica by Apollonius of Rhodes, and most recently Beowulf. I'm also about halfway through Virgil's Aeneid (in John Dryden's translation), after which I intend to start on Ferdowsi's great Persian epic, the Shahnameh. I'm also halfway through my friend Dave Jilk's newly published science-fiction novel in the form of an epic poem, entitled Epoch: A Poetic Psy-Phi Saga (more on that soon). And there are plenty more where these came from!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Middlemarch</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1909.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1909</id>
    <issued>2024-10-12</issued>
    <modified>2024-10-12</modified>
    <summary>The other day I finished reading George Eliot's novel Middlemarch. This was my second attempt, since a few years ago I had made it about halfway through but then got distracted with other projects. Middlemarch is widely considered one of the greatest novels in the English language, and I can't disagree. The aspect that most impresses me is Eliot's deep understanding of human character, emotion, and deliberation, for good and for ill. As befits Eliot's intellectual interests (she was the first to translate Spinoza's Ethics from Latin into English), that understanding is simultaneously both psychological and philosophical. I love how she provides ethical insights at just the right moments in the narrative: "character too is a process and an unfolding"; "character is not cut in marble - it is not something solid and unalterable. It is something living and changing, and may become diseased as our bodies do"; "every limit is a beginning as well as an ending"; "there is no creature whose inward being is so strong that it is not greatly determined by what lies outside it"; "is there not a genius for feeling nobly which also reigns over human spirits?" (etc.). British novelist Robert McCrum once called Middlemarch "a cathedral of words" and it certainly is long (my copy, printed in the 1920s, clocks in around 1350 pages, although more modern editions are around 800). Yet Eliot needed that vast structure to house the many fascinating characters she created, to portray their interrelationships, and to resolve their conflicts. Brava!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics VIII.1-5</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1908.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1908</id>
    <issued>2024-10-11</issued>
    <modified>2024-10-11</modified>
    <summary>Books VIII and IX of the Nicomachean Ethics are devoted to philia. The translators all say this word means friendship - but I think they're wrong. According to Aristotle, the paradigm case of philia is a mother's love for her children (1161b27). Going out on a limb (as I am wont to do), I therefore render philia as love....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Void for Vagueness</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1907.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1907</id>
    <issued>2024-10-08</issued>
    <modified>2024-10-08</modified>
    <summary>In yesterday's post about philosophical hubris, I mentioned Alexandre Lefebvre's proposal to regard liberalism as a way of life. Astute readers might have noticed that words like liberalism, neoliberalism, and fascism don't appear prominently in my writings. Beyond the fact that I tend to avoid political topics, there's another reason: I find these words to be extremely slippery. Indeed, they are often so ill-defined as to be void for vagueness, which might be why it's so easy to hurl them as epithets. Yet isms are not the only such words in our increasingly partisan culture. Similar in their effects are terms like feminazi, Islamophobic, woke, denier, and a host of others. If you think about them carefully, can you be sure that they provide a solid basis for clear thinking, mutual understanding, and respectful communication? I have my doubts......</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophical Hubris</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1906.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1906</id>
    <issued>2024-10-07</issued>
    <modified>2024-10-07</modified>
    <summary>In further reflecting on my recent post about criticism vs. cultivation, I've been pondering the all-too-common phenomenon of philosophical hubris: the attitude among some philosophers that they can pronounce intelligently on any topic or situation presented to them. To such thinkers (parodied as long ago as Plato's Gorgias), humility might be an intellectual virtue for others, but it isn't one for them....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Whole Wheat Pancake Recipe</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1905.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1905</id>
    <issued>2024-10-05</issued>
    <modified>2024-10-05</modified>
    <summary>Every once in a while I post a recipe here, almost as much for my own reference as for sharing. Because several people have asked me about my whole wheat pancakes recently, I figured I'd write up how I make them....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
