<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2018-02-12</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotelian Questions</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1604.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1604</id>
    <issued>2018-02-12</issued>
    <modified>2018-02-12</modified>
    <summary>My intent in writing a book on Aristotelian ethics is not to present exactly what Aristotle said (I'll leave that to scholars such as J.O. Urmson in his excellent epitome Aristotle's Ethics), but hopefully what he meant and even more pointedly what he means for us 2300+ years later. The goal is to present my own direct encounter with Aristotle, unmediated by millennia of often misguided scholarship and mistranslation. (Ironically, we need some scholarship to do that, so separating the wheat from the chaff is necessary.) Here are some of the questions I'll be trying answer:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle: A First Encounter</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1603.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1603</id>
    <issued>2018-02-04</issued>
    <modified>2018-02-04</modified>
    <summary>Aristotle's views on living well and doing well - what the ancient Greeks called εὐδαιμονία or eudaimonia - are some of the most enduring insights into ethics ever put into words. Yet the deepest meaning of those words is usually obscured by efforts to translate and interpret Aristotle's thoughts. In part the problem is linguistic, in part it is cultural, but ultimately it is philosophical: ancient Greek world views, Aristotle's among them, are very far from our modern ways of thinking and feeling....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Songs of Zarathustra Now Published</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1602.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1602</id>
    <issued>2018-02-03</issued>
    <modified>2018-02-03</modified>
    <summary>My short book on Friedrich Nietzsche, Songs of Zarathustra, is now published in paperback and ebook formats, and of course also on my website. Once again both the form and the content are unorthodox: I construe Nietzsche in a more humanistic way than most interpreters, and I do so in a cycle of 73 brief poems (including translations of some of Nietzsche's own verse). Neither aspect is likely to endear me to academics, but then I don't write for a scholarly audience - even though my books are based on a deep reading of the original texts....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Privacy FTW</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1601.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1601</id>
    <issued>2018-01-27</issued>
    <modified>2018-01-27</modified>
    <summary>Tomorrow (January 28th) is Data Privacy Day. Why not join in the celebration? Here are some suggestions to prevent absolutely everything you do online from being tracked:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Scales and Modes and Tetrachords, Oh My!</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1600.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1600</id>
    <issued>2018-01-03</issued>
    <modified>2018-01-03</modified>
    <summary>In preparation for recording my arrangements of music by Yes for solo electric bass, I've started taking music lessons with Mark Stefaniw, a fine bassist in the Denver area. Under Mark's tutelage I've been digging into music theory, which is both fascinating and enlightening (especially given my many years of musical learning at the surface)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ceding Our Humanity</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1599.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1599</id>
    <issued>2017-12-20</issued>
    <modified>2017-12-20</modified>
    <summary>Geoff Huston's keynote talk at RIPE 75, "The Death of Transit and Beyond", provides a sobering perspective on the recent evolution of the Internet - and, because so many of our personal, economic, intellectual, and political interactions happen over the Internet these days, on the evolution of society at large. Although Geoff tried to steer clear of alarmism, the picture is not pretty. Extreme concentration of wealth and power has led to a few leviathans controlling an overwhelming percentage of our online life (as of today, Apple, Google, Microsoft, Amazon, Alibaba, Tencent, and Facebook are seven of the eight largest public corporations in the world by market capitalization). Furthermore, as I explained in my talk "The Internet is Dead, Long Live the Internet" three years ago, in large measure these companies make money by tracking everything we do online and then selling those profiles to advertisers and marketers. And it gets worse: unlike the so-called robber barons of the late 19th century Gilded Age, which merely controlled markets for transportation, steel, oil, coal, and other physical goods, in subtle and not-so-subtle ways today's robber barons monitor and increasingly direct our mental and emotional life through the news we learn about, the books we read, the videos we watch, the people we talk with and connect to, and much more....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
