<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2025-11-26</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Beauty, Pleasure, Mozart, and Bob Dylan</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2004.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2004</id>
    <issued>2025-11-26</issued>
    <modified>2025-11-26</modified>
    <summary>Since choosing the name Beautiful Wisdom for my Substack earlier this year, I have focused more on wisdom and less on beauty. That might be changing, for several reasons: I've been getting deeper into musical composition, theory, and performance; I've been souring on speculative logorrhea; and in some of my recent readings on aesthetics I've been disappointed with philosophical accounts of beauty....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Personal Side of Public Behavior</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2003.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2003</id>
    <issued>2025-11-22</issued>
    <modified>2025-11-22</modified>
    <summary>While conversing with a friend the other day about the seemingly endless decline in societal standards of public behavior, I had a realization: there is nothing I can do about how other people conduct themselves; all I can do is conduct myself up to my own standards. This is not a newfound awareness - I can't count the number of times I have observed that the only thing I have control over in life is myself, and even this can be rather tenuous - yet each time I make such an observation my consciousness experiences a little jolt of surprised recognition....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Twenty-Five Years of Blogging</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2002.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2002</id>
    <issued>2025-11-21</issued>
    <modified>2025-11-21</modified>
    <summary>On this day in the year 2000, I posted the first entry in my online journal. Two thousand posts and 650,000+ words later, I'm still at it. Granted, my journal is not quite of Thoreauvian proportions: our friend Henry produced over 2 million words in 24 years of journaling (all of which I read while encountering Thoreau in preparation for composing my book The Upland Farm). Even so, I've done a lot of scribbling over the last quarter century!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Giving and Receiving</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2001.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2001</id>
    <issued>2025-11-16</issued>
    <modified>2025-11-16</modified>
    <summary>Recent life circumstances have spurred me to reflect further on love as an activity, but also on love as a "passivity", as it were....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Letter</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2000.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2000</id>
    <issued>2025-10-17</issued>
    <modified>2025-10-17</modified>
    <summary>Yesterday I penned a letter to my best friend. And I do mean penned: after rummaging around in a box stashed in a closet, I tracked down some fine stationery I'd bought years ago and, pen in hand, sat down to write. Having been away from letter-writing for decades, I was reminded of a few long-forgotten essentials:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Socrates and Thoreau on True Wealth</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1999.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1999</id>
    <issued>2025-10-14</issued>
    <modified>2025-10-14</modified>
    <summary>On this day in 1857, Thoreau wrote as follows in his journal:...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
