<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2017-02-04</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Thoreau on Genius</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1579.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1579</id>
    <issued>2017-02-04</issued>
    <modified>2017-02-04</modified>
    <summary>Someone who knows that I'm writing a book on Thoreau sent me a link from BrainPickings.org about Thoreau's views on the topic of genius. Drawing on the "Thursday" and "Friday" chapters of A Week on the Concord and Merrimack Rivers, the author focuses her brief essay on the difference between an artisan, an artist, and a genius....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>HTTPS No More</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1578.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1578</id>
    <issued>2017-02-02</issued>
    <modified>2017-02-02</modified>
    <summary>One unfortunate byproduct of shutting down my VPS and moving my websites to GitHub Pages is that I'm no longer hosting the stpeter.im domain via HTTPS. Although I'm not overjoyed about this, I'm also not deeply disturbed by it given that my personal website isn't exactly the kind of information that needs to be encrypted in transit (and someone could retrieve it over HTTPS from GitHub.com if they really wanted to). Mike Linksvayer helpfully pointed out to me that there are some solutions, and I'll look into those soon. In the meantime I've modified all the cross-links within my websites so that they use http instead of https URLs....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>VPS No More</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1577.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1577</id>
    <issued>2017-02-01</issued>
    <modified>2017-02-01</modified>
    <summary>A few weeks ago I spent most of a Sunday trying, and failing, to upgrade the Debian Linux distribution on my virtual private server (VPS). After the Linux experts at my hosting company also failed after 90 minutes of fighting with the thing, I realized that the time had come to shut down my VPS and find simpler solutions. For me, that turned out to be FastMail for my email addresses and GitHub Pages for my websites (I was also hosting a few WordPress sites for friends, which I've moved to WordPress.com). The only things I miss at this point are HTTPS for one of my websites, and the personal XMPP server I was running. Yet the HTTPS wasn't really all that critical (I know, HTTPS Everywhere and all that, but in practice I'm not running transactional websites and in fact all of my sites are even free of JavaScript - I guess I'm a Web 1.0 kind of person). And although the XMPP server was a fine thing, I do run jabber.org and I've had a few addresses there forever, so I might as well use them. Simplify, simplify!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Poets' Paradox</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1576.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1576</id>
    <issued>2017-01-31</issued>
    <modified>2017-01-31</modified>
    <summary>Here's another draft poem for my far-future book Songs of Zarathustra:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ism Book Updates</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1575.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1575</id>
    <issued>2017-01-29</issued>
    <modified>2017-01-29</modified>
    <summary>One of the great things about publishing to the Internet, and nowadays print on demand as well, is that you can continually improve what you have written. Among my writings, there is no better example than The Ism Book: A Field Guide to Philosophy. I first wrote this highly interlinked book using HyperCard on my first Macintosh computer, then ported it to the Internet in 1996. Since then it has undergone numerous revisions as I've broadened and deepened my understanding of philosophical history and concepts. Last week while in flight to and from California I marked up a copy of the book with copious amounts of red ink, and today I keyed in a large number of edits (in fact I've been making numerous fixes for the last two months). Now I just need to port all these changes over to the physical book and republish it....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Irrelevance of Government</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1574.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1574</id>
    <issued>2017-01-21</issued>
    <modified>2017-01-21</modified>
    <summary>Imagine life a thousand years ago in, say, France or Italy. The society and culture in which you are immersed is deeply focused on religion. The words of your local priest have great significance, a bishop or archbishop is a personage of divine importance, and the Pope is like a spiritual emperor. Those wishing to effect social change, or tell other people what to do, or pursue their own personal advantage, necessarily use the tool that is ready to hand, and that is the apparatus of the church....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
