<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2024-09-03</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics VI.6-8</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1896.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1896</id>
    <issued>2024-09-03</issued>
    <modified>2024-09-03</modified>
    <summary>In the most recent installment of our walk with Aristotle, we puzzled through the beginnings of his analysis of wisdom [phronēsis]. In Book VI.6-8 he climbs further up this steep section of the trail to discuss not only wisdom but also sagacity [sophia]....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Republic If You Can Keep It</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1895.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1895</id>
    <issued>2024-08-30</issued>
    <modified>2024-08-30</modified>
    <summary>Every year around Independence Day, I carve out time to read and reflect on the Declaration of Independence and the Constitution; and every year I notice something new. This year it was the first clause in Article IV, Section 4: "The United States shall guarantee to every State in this Union a Republican Form of Government." As with everything else in the Constitution, this "guarantee clause" has been analyzed historically, legally, and philosophically over the last 200+ years. Although I'm not a scholar of the Constitution and don't plan to become one, my curiosity was piqued, so I decided to gain a slightly better understanding of republicanism (with a small "r")....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Pyrrho in the Light of Homer</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1894.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1894</id>
    <issued>2024-08-28</issued>
    <modified>2024-08-28</modified>
    <summary>Only the merest wisps of evidence remain for the thoughts of Pyrrho, the founder of ancient Greek skepticism and, perhaps, the bringer of Buddhism to Greece. Like Socrates, Pyrrho wrote nothing. His disciple Timon of Phlius did some writing, but almost all of it is lost. The primary text that has survived from antiquity is a brief passage in the Preparation for the Gospel by the Christian polemicist Eusebius of Caesarea (4th century AD), who quotes from Book VIII of On Philosophy by the Peripatetic philosopher Aristocles of Messene (1st century AD), who in turn cites but doesn't seem to precisely quote Timon. That's not much to go on!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tao Te Ching §2: What-Is and What-Is-Not</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1893.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1893</id>
    <issued>2024-08-26</issued>
    <modified>2024-08-26</modified>
    <summary>In my continuing experimentation with the Tao Te Ching, here's a draft rendering of the second chapter:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Homeric Style</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1892.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1892</id>
    <issued>2024-08-18</issued>
    <modified>2024-08-18</modified>
    <summary>As previously noted, my stylistic intent in writing an epic poem about Pyrrho and Alexander the Great is to have it sound as if translated into modern English iambic pentameter from the ancient Greek dactylic hexameter of a Hellenistic author deeply influenced by Homer. To do this convincingly, I need to have a firm grasp on Homeric style. Here Matthew Arnold's 1861 lectures "On Translating Homer" are invaluable. He identifies four key features of the Homeric poems:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tao Te Ching §81: True Words</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1891.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1891</id>
    <issued>2024-08-14</issued>
    <modified>2024-08-14</modified>
    <summary>Following up on my previous postings about the Tao Te Ching, here is one possible rendering of the very last poem, number 81:...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
