<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2024-08-28</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Pyrrho in the Light of Homer</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1894.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1894</id>
    <issued>2024-08-28</issued>
    <modified>2024-08-28</modified>
    <summary>Only the merest wisps of evidence remain for the thoughts of Pyrrho, the founder of ancient Greek skepticism and, perhaps, the bringer of Buddhism to Greece. Like Socrates, Pyrrho wrote nothing. His disciple Timon of Phlius did some writing, but almost all of it is lost. The primary text that has survived from antiquity is a brief passage in the Preparation for the Gospel by the Christian polemicist Eusebius of Caesarea (4th century AD), who quotes from Book VIII of On Philosophy by the Peripatetic philosopher Aristocles of Messene (1st century AD), who in turn cites but doesn't seem to precisely quote Timon. That's not much to go on!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tao Te Ching §2: What-Is and What-Is-Not</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1893.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1893</id>
    <issued>2024-08-26</issued>
    <modified>2024-08-26</modified>
    <summary>In my continuing experimentation with the Tao Te Ching, here's a draft rendering of the second chapter:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Homeric Style</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1892.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1892</id>
    <issued>2024-08-18</issued>
    <modified>2024-08-18</modified>
    <summary>As previously noted, my stylistic intent in writing an epic poem about Pyrrho and Alexander the Great is to have it sound as if translated into modern English iambic pentameter from the ancient Greek dactylic hexameter of a Hellenistic author deeply influenced by Homer. To do this convincingly, I need to have a firm grasp on Homeric style. Here Matthew Arnold's 1861 lectures "On Translating Homer" are invaluable. He identifies four key features of the Homeric poems:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tao Te Ching §81: True Words</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1891.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1891</id>
    <issued>2024-08-14</issued>
    <modified>2024-08-14</modified>
    <summary>Following up on my previous postings about the Tao Te Ching, here is one possible rendering of the very last poem, number 81:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics VI.5</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1890.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1890</id>
    <issued>2024-08-08</issued>
    <modified>2024-08-08</modified>
    <summary>In VI.5, Aristotle finally turns to a deeper analysis of phronēsis. I render this term as "wisdom", whereas others render it as "practical wisdom" (the standard these days), "practical judgment" (Joe Sachs), or "prudence" (prevalent in older translations). The wise person - the phronimos - is "able to deliberate beautifully about things that are good and advantageous, not in part, such as the sort of things that are conducive to health or strength, but the sort of things that are conducive to living well as a whole" (1140a25-28, Sachs translation). By the way, here "conducive" renders πρὸς, the same preposition we find in πρὸς τὸ τέλος, which is Aristotle's phrase for "that which takes us closer to completion" or "that which is toward the goal" - where the goal is living well as a whole, i.e., success [eupraxia] or fulfillment [eudaimonia]....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics VI.3-4</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1889.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1889</id>
    <issued>2024-08-04</issued>
    <modified>2024-08-04</modified>
    <summary>On the last section of our walk, we started to pick our way through a boulder-field of concepts that Aristotle introduced to kick off Book VI. Here we'll glance at two of those concepts: understanding [epistēmē] and craft [technē]. Aristotle's purpose here is not to examine these phenomena in detail, but to set up a contrast with wisdom [phronēsis] and sagacity [sophia], which will become the primary focus later in Book VI....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
