<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2022-02-10</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Meditations on Bach #10: Philosophy in Music</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1700.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1700</id>
    <issued>2022-02-10</issued>
    <modified>2022-02-10</modified>
    <summary>In the second edition of his extremely intriguing book Bach: The Fencing Master, cellist Anner Bylsma writes as follows:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Jealousy and Envy</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1699.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1699</id>
    <issued>2022-02-10</issued>
    <modified>2022-02-10</modified>
    <summary>A friend recently asked me how I would characterize the difference between jealousy and envy. Here's how I see it: jealousy is when I want to gain something you have, and envy is when I want you to lose something you have. If I'm jealous of your new Tesla, I want a Tesla too. If I'm envious of the superyacht that Jeff Bezos is building, I don't want him to have that yacht even if I'll never be able to have such a thing....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Delphic Wisdom and Modern Science</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1698.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1698</id>
    <issued>2022-02-04</issued>
    <modified>2022-02-04</modified>
    <summary>Carved into the walls of the ancient Greek temple at Delphi were two proverbs: γνῶθι σεαυτόν ("know thyself") and μηδὲν ἄγαν ("nothing too much"). Plato mentions them in his dialogue Protagoras, set around 434 BCE, but most likely they were common among the Greeks as far back as 600 BCE or even earlier. Although they are so very old, recently I've been pondering their connection to the latest research in the modern science of psychology....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophical Professionalism</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1697.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1697</id>
    <issued>2022-02-01</issued>
    <modified>2022-02-01</modified>
    <summary>Robin Hanson recently suggested that we need more generalist thinkers, and that they can be found among the ranks of polymaths, public intellectuals, and professional philosophers. Although I might post again on the topic of generalists vs. specialists, today I'd like to focus instead on the concept of philosophical professionalism....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Underlying Theme</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1696.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1696</id>
    <issued>2022-01-27</issued>
    <modified>2022-01-27</modified>
    <summary>In a comment on my recent post about Aristotle on ways of life, my friend Kurt wondered if, according to Aristotle, the best life must have a single purpose (in Greek, a telos). I would say so: at the very beginning of the Eudemian Ethics, he says that it is a sign of great folly to not organize your life around some telos. Yet I think this can be interpreted in several different ways....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle on Ways of Life</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1695.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1695</id>
    <issued>2022-01-24</issued>
    <modified>2022-01-24</modified>
    <summary>While I'm reflecting on philosophies and ways of life, I thought it would be interesting to look at what Aristotle says about ways of life in his writings on ethics....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
