<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2023-12-23</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>The Old Way</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1842.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1842</id>
    <issued>2023-12-23</issued>
    <modified>2023-12-23</modified>
    <summary>In her book The Old Way, Elizabeth Marshall Thomas provides a poignant portrait of the hunter-gatherer way of life, based on her "first contact" experience with the Bushmen of the Kalahari Desert in the early 1950s. Her account contains many fascinating aspects, such as her description of how the Bushmen groups of ~25 people had no leader but instead made decisions by consensus. She calls their knowledge, customs, and skills "The Old Way" because she contends that we humans evolved into that way of life over hundreds of thousands (perhaps even millions) of years after we split from chimpanzees and the climate of much of Africa changed from rain forest to savannah. When you consider that humans lived as hunter-gatherers for over ten thousand generations, that we have lived as agriculturalists for only a few hundred generations, and that we have lived in industrial society for only ten to twenty generations, you start to realize the vast scale of human evolution and the deep foundations for how we think and behave - as well as the extraordinary novelty of our modern way of life. It's no surprise, then, that it's all too easy for us, whether individually or collectively, to retrogress into tribalism. Yet it seems to me that modern tribalism has all the worst features of The Old Way and none of the many features that redeemed it and indeed made it absolutely necessary for human survival until ten thousand years ago or so. In fact, what we think of as tribalism seems to have more in common with the hierarchical societies based on status, power, and wealth that emerged after the hunter-gatherer way of life broke down, and less on the egalitarian societies of The Old Way....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Short Shrift</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1841.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1841</id>
    <issued>2023-12-19</issued>
    <modified>2023-12-19</modified>
    <summary>Riffing on a post by Arnold Kling, who in turn was riffing on Marc Andreessen, I've been pondering the topics that various schools of thought tend to ignore. Kling was talking about politics: conservatives don't like to discuss beneficial social changes they once opposed, progressives don't like to consider anything but oppression as a cause of disparate outcomes, etc. However, we can apply the same line of thinking to philosophies. Here are a few possibilities:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Do We Need the Concept of a Concept?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1840.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1840</id>
    <issued>2023-12-18</issued>
    <modified>2023-12-18</modified>
    <summary>As mentioned last month, I'm slowly re-reading Robert Sokolowski's book Phenomenology of the Human Person with a friend of mine. When I first wrote about this book four years ago, I noted that Sokolowski "explains the epistemology of reason in the context of human conversation: by embracing the back and forth of speech ... he sidesteps the ever present dangers of solipsism and mental representationalism." As a point of comparison, in her book Introduction to Objectivist Epistemology, Ayn Rand says that a child independently formulates the concept of, say, a tree in his or her own mind by observing trees in reality. However, on this account we need to add communication as a separate capacity on top of concept-formation so that we can explain how the child associates the word 'tree' with the concept....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophy vs. Philosophies</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1839.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1839</id>
    <issued>2023-12-14</issued>
    <modified>2023-12-14</modified>
    <summary>On the very first page of his book What Is Ancient Philosophy?, Pierre Hadot — the late French scholar who almost singlehandedly resurrected the humanistic conception of philosophy as a way of life — drew a distinction between individual philosophies on the one hand and philosophy itself on the other:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>More on Ancient Friends</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1838.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1838</id>
    <issued>2023-12-13</issued>
    <modified>2023-12-13</modified>
    <summary>A mere two nights after quoting Niccolò Machiavelli's reflections on his ancient friends, I came upon a similar passage in Essays in Idleness, written by the Japanese poet-monk Yoshida Kenkō around the year 1330. Here's what Kenkō had to say, in the translation by Donald Keene:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Planning to Be Old</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1837.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1837</id>
    <issued>2023-12-12</issued>
    <modified>2023-12-12</modified>
    <summary>Earlier this year at a family gathering, I overheard an uncle of mine (who is in his late 80s) say something in passing to one of his siblings about the importance of planning to be old. This set me to thinking: what might such planning involve? Here are some possible considerations:...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
