<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2021-05-31</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Holding Multiple Opinions</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1668.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1668</id>
    <issued>2021-05-31</issued>
    <modified>2021-05-31</modified>
    <summary>Sometimes it's difficult to hold fewer opinions in your own mind or to engage in cognitive empathy toward others; that's when it can help to hold multiple opinions at the same time. This might sound like the mental equivalent of juggling plates, but it's a skill worth cultivating (and one with an ancient pedigree, as evidenced for example by the Letter to Pythocles by the ancient Greek philosopher Epicurus)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What Is a Concept Album?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1667.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1667</id>
    <issued>2021-05-06</issued>
    <modified>2021-05-06</modified>
    <summary>And now for something completely different: a rollicking discussion on the Big Yellow Praxis podcast about some underappreciated musical recordings, in which Jacob and I explore the age-old question: what exactly makes a concept album? Check it out on YouTube!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Opinions about Opinions</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1666.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1666</id>
    <issued>2021-05-04</issued>
    <modified>2021-05-04</modified>
    <summary>My friend Paul sent me a few thoughts about my recent post on holding fewer opinions. He's formulated an approach that involves holding fewer opinions about other people's opinions. This seems valuable, and related to a post I wrote four years ago entitled "Why Do You Think What You Think?" My introspective conclusion then was that I can't always assign praise or blame for the contents of my thoughts; extending this to other people is a good example of what Arnold Kling calls cognitive empathy: instead of demonizing people who disagree with you, suspend judgment or at least try to understand where they might be coming from. (It's probably best to build up such a practice first in matters that aren't very consequential - and we all have our limits regarding the opinions we find acceptable!) The flip side is not deifying your own thoughts, which we could express in the following aphorism: "if you think well of your own opinions just because they're yours, then you're not thinking well."...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Bach on Bass #4: Instrumental Solution</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1665.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1665</id>
    <issued>2021-04-10</issued>
    <modified>2021-04-10</modified>
    <summary>After much research and some helpful input from double bassist Mark Stefaniw, the unofficial artistic advisor for my "Bach on Bass" project, I've chosen to buy a Stradi bass made by Marek Dąbek of Juliszew, Poland. Not only does Marek make absolutely gorgeous instruments, but he was excited to work with me on a design that met all my criteria: a four-string fretless bass with tapewound strings tuned in fifths, a very long fingerboard with a deep cutaway so that I can play intricate passages high up on the neck, a combination of piezo and magnetic pickups (the latter is important to enable experimentation with an eBow on certain pieces), and a chocolately tone that balances the best of electric and upright bass sounds. A long email thread with Marek led to a bass that is all oak, a wood we both love: roasted European oak for the body (chambered to enhance its acoustic properties), a hybrid through-body neck also in roasted oak, and both the fingerboard and top in 2000-year-old bog oak. Since Marek likes to name his basses, we're calling this one the "Mocha 4". The only bad part is that Marek is a true artisan who makes only 20 instruments a year and has a large backlog of orders, so I won't get my hands on the Mocha until early next year. But it's going to be worth the wait!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Holding Fewer Opinions</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1664.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1664</id>
    <issued>2021-04-06</issued>
    <modified>2021-04-06</modified>
    <summary>A few months ago I read the transcript of a discussion between Brian Beck and Robin Hanson, in which Hanson advised the listener to hold fewer opinions:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Politically Independent</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1663.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1663</id>
    <issued>2021-03-27</issued>
    <modified>2021-03-27</modified>
    <summary>Longtime readers of this weblog know that politically speaking I've always been more or less libertarian. (Little-known fact: many years ago I started a run for the House of Representatives on the Libertarian Party ticket, but my wife and I moved that year so I never got on the ballot.) Back in 2012 I thought that participating in the Republican Liberty Caucus might be effective because the county I live is solidly Republican, but once Trump was nominated for president in 2016 I switched my voter registration to Libertarian. After the recent election I decided to switch again, this time to Independent. Here's why....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
