<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2025-10-02</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Biscuit Wood</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1996.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1996</id>
    <issued>2025-10-02</issued>
    <modified>2025-10-02</modified>
    <summary>With winter preparations already underway here (I don't want to get caught flatfooted as happened last year when we were hit with three feet of snow in the first week of November), I was reminded of a story that Henry David Thoreau related in his journal on December 15th, 1859:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Bushwhacking</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1995.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1995</id>
    <issued>2025-10-01</issued>
    <modified>2025-10-01</modified>
    <summary>One of the differences, I'm finding, between public philosophy and private philosophy is that the former is full of well-established trails, whereas the latter is largely an unexplored territory in which bushwhacking is required if you want to blaze a path to wisdom. For instance, there are probably hundreds of books on a typical public philosophy topic like free will vs. determinism, whereas there are few if any about, say, understanding and navigating the varieties of grieving....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Varieties of Grieving</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1994.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1994</id>
    <issued>2025-09-29</issued>
    <modified>2025-09-29</modified>
    <summary>A few years ago I read an excellent book entitled Grief: A Philosophical Guide by Michael Cholbi. Since then, events in my life have led me to reflect further on the several varieties of grieving experience, as William James might have phrased it. Foremost in my mind are anticipatory grief (mental, emotional, and spiritual adjustment to a future loss, such as loss of parents) and ambiguous grief (adjustment to a loss that is difficult to understand or resolve, such as a loved one's incapacitation because of dementia)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Sagehood</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1993.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1993</id>
    <issued>2025-09-23</issued>
    <modified>2025-09-23</modified>
    <summary>In most of the ancient philosophical communities, the figure of the sage was held up as the ideal to which a budding lover of wisdom should rightly aspire. This was true of Confucianism, Pythagoreanism, Stoicism, Buddhism, Taoism, Pyrrhonism, Epicureanism, and the various "schools" inspired by the example of Socrates, including the "think tanks" and voluminous works of Plato and Aristotle....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophers: Public and Private</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1992.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1992</id>
    <issued>2025-09-17</issued>
    <modified>2025-09-17</modified>
    <summary>We're all familiar with public intellectuals: prominent thinkers who cross over from merely academic research to have an impact on the broader culture through popular books, public debates, influence on government policy, and so on....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>American Identity</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1991.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1991</id>
    <issued>2025-09-17</issued>
    <modified>2025-09-17</modified>
    <summary>Because today is Constitution Day, I figured it would appropriate to share a few reflections on what it is to be an American. Apparently that's a thing these days! But in fact it's been a thing since at least 1781, when J. Hector St. Jean de Crevecoeur published his essay What Is an American....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
