<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2022-10-27</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Become What You Are</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1742.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1742</id>
    <issued>2022-10-27</issued>
    <modified>2022-10-27</modified>
    <summary>Following on our investigation last week of the ancient Greek maxim "Know Thyself", I thought it might be interesting to explain another Greek phrase that has gained currency in recent times: "Become What You Are"....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Know Thyself</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1741.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1741</id>
    <issued>2022-10-20</issued>
    <modified>2022-10-20</modified>
    <summary>The saying γνῶθι σαυτόν ("know thyself") was prominently displayed at the temple of Delphi, where ancient Greeks, Romans, Persians, and others sought answers to their most pressing questions. Yet what is it exactly to know thyself? Essential clues can be found in an obscure little book published in 1916: "Know Thyself" in Greek and Latin Literature, in which Eliza Gregory Wilkins collected almost all mentions of the maxim up until the fall of Rome....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Agreement Is Overrated</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1740.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1740</id>
    <issued>2022-10-13</issued>
    <modified>2022-10-13</modified>
    <summary>How many times has a friend sent you a link to an essay with the proviso "I don't agree with everything this person says, but it's worth reading"? I used to do that, too, but then I reflected on whether intellectual agreement is truly important, and I concluded that it's not....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Thinking Forward</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1739.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1739</id>
    <issued>2022-10-06</issued>
    <modified>2022-10-06</modified>
    <summary>Much of what makes human beings distinctive is what Jacob Bronowski called "a sense of the future" (in addition to his old book by that name, see also more recently Homo Prospectus by Seligman, Railton, Baumeister, and Sripada). Certainly most animals can think at least a few minutes or maybe hours in advance, but they're not actively planning months or years ahead of time as humans can. Yet, perhaps under the influence of modern science, our conception of our intellectual capacities is often retrospective: reason is thought to be a faculty that formulates accurate conclusions and stable laws from the evidence we have painfully gathered in the past through induction, experiment, and the like....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Virtues: One or Many?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1738.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1738</id>
    <issued>2022-09-29</issued>
    <modified>2022-09-29</modified>
    <summary>In a post last week about the value of studying multiple philosophies, I observed that I have not read much Christian theology. As if on queue, I decided to read Augustine's Of the Morals of the Catholic Church, written in 388 CE. The impetus was a footnote on page 179 of Daniel C. Russell's book Practical Intelligence and the Virtues, where he said that he would not consider non-secular arguments for the unity of the virtues, such as Augustine's argument that there really is only one virtue, which is the love of God....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What Is Philosophy For?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1737.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1737</id>
    <issued>2022-09-25</issued>
    <modified>2022-09-25</modified>
    <summary>Occasionally one reads something so singularly misguided that it puts into stark relief a vital concern of human existence. In the case at hand, the vital concern is the place of philosophy in the best life for human beings and the piece of writing is a scholarly paper published just last week by philosopher Hanno Sauer, entitled "The End of History."...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
