<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2025-03-03</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Writing as Thinking</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1940.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1940</id>
    <issued>2025-03-03</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-03</modified>
    <summary>Why write? I can't speak for anyone else, but for me writing is a form of thinking. Although I often have vague notions floating around in my head, they don't crystallize until I formulate them in black and white. Before words can inform, they must be formed....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Joy of Creation</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1939.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1939</id>
    <issued>2025-03-02</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-02</modified>
    <summary>Several times now I've been exposed to "poems" generated by LLMs, whether sent to me by friends or posted by bloggers. Leaving aside their questionable quality, I would never use LLMs in this way. To me, the joy of creation lies not in the artifact but in the artistry. Would you prompt an LLM-equipped robot to attend a concert or sporting event on your behalf, take a walk with your child, or meet your best friend for lunch? I shudder to think that people might do such things before long. Similarly, writing poems, composing music, making pottery, and the like are not instances of drudgery but creative acts emblematic of the life of a free person....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>In Medias Res</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1938.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1938</id>
    <issued>2025-03-02</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-02</modified>
    <summary>(This post introduces my new Substack newsletter, Beautiful Wisdom.)...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Poem a Day Keeps the Doldrums Away</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1937.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1937</id>
    <issued>2025-02-25</issued>
    <modified>2025-02-25</modified>
    <summary>To keep my sanity and experience more beauty in life, I endeavor to read a few poems every day. To facilitate this practice among other people, I've decided to start a Substack newsletter with a simple mission: publish one classic poem a day from the vast store of English-language verse in the public domain that I've already uploaded to the Monadnock Valley Press website. Check it out at the link below....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Inwardly Free</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1936.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1936</id>
    <issued>2025-02-09</issued>
    <modified>2025-02-09</modified>
    <summary>A while back I learned of a poet and historian named Peter Viereck (1916-2006), who not only won the Pulitzer Prize for poetry in 1949 but also wrote insightful books of social and literary criticism in the American individualist tradition of Emerson, Thoreau, and Randolph Bourne. In his now-forgotten book The Unadjusted Man, published in 1956, Viereck celebrated the kind of person who dodges the pressures of conformity (what he called "overadjustment") to maintain a measure of intellectual independence. Here is a fine passage about one path to becoming an "unadjusted man":...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Moving Slow</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1935.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1935</id>
    <issued>2025-02-08</issued>
    <modified>2025-02-08</modified>
    <summary>Several factors have conspired recently to slow down my pace of posting. Not only have I been working through a difficult and distracting family matter, but I've been questioning some of my existing commitments. Among other things, I've decided to conclude my philosophical coaching and startup advising activities. Although these were intriguing experiments and I enjoyed working with several people, I have my doubts about how truly helpful I was; more generally, I doubt that I am cut out for the helping professions. As a result, I'll be shutting down my philosopher.coach website and in the future posting only at stpeter.im (however, I won't rule out a move to Substack, at least for some of my mid-length writings)....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
