<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2023-02-12</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Best Friend Books</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1766.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1766</id>
    <issued>2023-02-12</issued>
    <modified>2023-02-12</modified>
    <summary>It occurs to me that, just as we have circles of friendship, so also we sometimes have circles of influence and affection in the books we read. Certain books and authors are like best friends that we revisit again and again: think of those who cherish the novels of Jane Austen, the Meditations of Marcus Aurelius, the Confessions of Augustine, or the plays of Shakespeare....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Career Reflections</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1765.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1765</id>
    <issued>2023-02-09</issued>
    <modified>2023-02-09</modified>
    <summary>Twelve months ago this week I quit my job at Mozilla. Herewith a few reflections on my 25 years in tech....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle on AI</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1764.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1764</id>
    <issued>2023-02-02</issued>
    <modified>2023-02-02</modified>
    <summary>Apparently the world is all agog over a computer program called ChatGPT. It's a harbinger of yet another emergency disaster crisis! The singularity is near! We're facing an imminent reality collapse! We won't be able to tell fake from real, machine from human, false from true! How will we know what information to trust?!?...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Emergency Disaster Crisis</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1763.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1763</id>
    <issued>2023-01-27</issued>
    <modified>2023-01-27</modified>
    <summary>One reason I don't pay much attention to the news is that just about everything being reported on is an emergency, a disaster, a crisis! I like to run them all together and say that we're in the midst of an Emergency Disaster Crisis....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Circles of Friendship</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1762.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1762</id>
    <issued>2023-01-25</issued>
    <modified>2023-01-25</modified>
    <summary>As noted last week, Robin Dunbar, who has done amazing research into close personal relationships, is best known for "Dunbar's Number" - his finding that the typical friends network contains about 150 people (as discussed in a recent post by Arnold Kling). Yet as I also noted long ago in my blog post "Joining the Band", there are actually multiple Dunbar numbers, each roughly 3x more or less than the next one in the series....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Metaphysics in Verse II</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1761.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1761</id>
    <issued>2023-01-23</issued>
    <modified>2023-01-23</modified>
    <summary>Among the strangest conceptions of metaphysics is Aristotle's fanciful (or perhaps deadly serious) hypothesis of the Unmoved Mover. It's difficult to understand quite what he was getting at, and I'm not about to formulate a scholarly exegesis of the idea. But I did compose a little poem about it:...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
