<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2017-01-14</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Monadnock Valley Press Annual Report 2016</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1572.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1572</id>
    <issued>2017-01-14</issued>
    <modified>2017-01-14</modified>
    <summary>In 2016 I again spent very little time on posting public-domain texts at the Monadnock Valley Press - only a few works by Henry David Thoreau, Virginia Woolf, and Blaise Pascal. Once I finish my forthcoming book on Thoreau, I plan to clear out a backlog of books, essays, and plays by Ibsen, Confucius, Emerson, Montaigne, Spinoza, Petrarch, Lucretius, Epictetus, Seneca, and Cicero. With revenue of $248.62 and expenses of $181.58, we earned only $67.04 in 2016, too. It's a good thing I don't write philosophy books for the money!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Thoreau on Magnanimity</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1571.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1571</id>
    <issued>2017-01-08</issued>
    <modified>2017-01-08</modified>
    <summary>Reading is one thing; understanding is another. Part of what I do while "working through" the writings of a thinker like Thoreau is to delve deeply into key themes, concepts, and even words. Consider, for example, this sentence from Economy, the first chapter of Walden: "To be a philosopher is not merely to have subtle thoughts, nor even to found a school, but so to love wisdom as to live according to its dictates, a life of simplicity, independence, magnanimity, and trust." When reading on the surface, it's easy to gloss over a sentence like this and merely have a pleasant feeling that it's a good thing to live philosophically. Yet what exactly is Thoreau talking about here? What does he mean by the somewhat vague and uncommon word magnanimity? To figure that out can require quite a bit of digging....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Corporatization</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1570.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1570</id>
    <issued>2017-01-06</issued>
    <modified>2017-01-06</modified>
    <summary>While taking my dog to two different doctors the other day (long story), I discovered that veterinary practices are increasing being bought up by large corporate entities like PetVet and VCA. Your seemingly small, local caregiver just might have sold his or her practice to one of these companies, supposedly while still retaining control over medical decision-making (that little voice in the back of my head is saying "he who pays the piper, calls the tune")....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophy and Ideology</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1569.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1569</id>
    <issued>2017-01-01</issued>
    <modified>2017-01-01</modified>
    <summary>I know someone who only listens to the music of Bob Dylan. Now, I respect Dylan's songwriting immensely and I play a number of his songs, but I don't think you can call someone who only listens to Bob Dylan a lover of music. That requires what jazz musicians call big ears: an appreciation for a wide variety of musical styles, composers, and performers....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Irrelevance of God</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1568.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1568</id>
    <issued>2016-12-31</issued>
    <modified>2016-12-31</modified>
    <summary>While doing research for my forthcoming book on Henry David Thoreau, I've been exploring the philosophies of ancient India (Thoreau was a great admirer of the Bhagavat-Gita, the Rig-Veda, and the Laws of Manu). In so doing, I recently came across the Samkhya school of thought, which is an atheistic strand of Hinduism closely related to Yoga philosophy (apparently the Yoga Sutras of Patañjali grew out of the Samkhya tradition). Interestingly, Samkhya is more nontheistic than anti-theistic: in essence it treats god or gods as irrelevant to life and ethics. This approach is in line with my attitude; although I have been a non-believer since the age of nine (as described in my very first journal post from 1989), I am not militantly anti-theist and the underlying theme of my lifelong philosophy project is how to be good without god....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Irrelevance of God</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1567.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1567</id>
    <issued>2016-12-30</issued>
    <modified>2016-12-30</modified>
    <summary>For students of American culture, one of the most fascinating books of the year was Hillbilly Elegy by J.D. Vance. The author's descriptions of his troubled upbringing in the rural hills of Kentucky and a fading industrial town in Ohio have spurred casual observers to note that these are just the kinds of places that switched political allegiances in 2016. Yet cries of "Trump!" uncover only a minuscule percentage of the story. To truly understand what's going on here requires a long-term historical perspective....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
