<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2023-07-04</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>The Best We Can Do</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1794.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1794</id>
    <issued>2023-07-04</issued>
    <modified>2023-07-04</modified>
    <summary>Here's a further thought about the examined life, which the other day I summarized as "The best way to live is to never stop asking yourself: What is the best way to live?" Implicit in that formulation is a focus on personal improvement, for it involves continually asking yourself "Is this the best I can do?" For someone with high ethical ideals, the answer is always "not quite" because there is always a gap between the ideal and the real. Having those ideals gives us something to strive for. As I like say, "You don't have to achieve an ideal to realize the benefits of idealism."...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Certainty</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1793.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1793</id>
    <issued>2023-07-02</issued>
    <modified>2023-07-02</modified>
    <summary>In my post the other day about the examined life, I observed that some people are certain about their answers to the great questions of life. By contrast, those of a Socratic bent typically doubt that certainty is likely or even possible. The standard rejoinder is this: "It sounds like you're certain that certainty is impossible." Quite the conundrum....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Examined Life</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1792.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1792</id>
    <issued>2023-06-29</issued>
    <modified>2023-06-29</modified>
    <summary>All the great questions of life boil down to this: What is the best way to live?...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Threading a Middle Path</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1791.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1791</id>
    <issued>2023-06-22</issued>
    <modified>2023-06-22</modified>
    <summary>In the past I've written about both the ancient philosophical method of dialectic and the importance of intellectual and political moderation. Here I'd like to bring these two strands together....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Chosen Wisdom</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1790.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1790</id>
    <issued>2023-06-20</issued>
    <modified>2023-06-20</modified>
    <summary>The longer I study and practice philosophy, the more value I find in a wide variety of wisdom traditions. When I first became interested in philosophy at the age of 12, it was exclusively in the form of Ayn Rand's philosophy of Objectivism. About this philosophy I was, at least throughout my teenage years, thoroughly dogmatic: all the other philosophies were riddled with error - not even worth considering - and Rand's philosophy simply was philosophy as far as I was concerned. (To be clear, the fault was not Rand's but my own - I could have been just as dogmatic about Stoicism or existentialism.)...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>More Humanity</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1789.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1789</id>
    <issued>2023-06-17</issued>
    <modified>2023-06-17</modified>
    <summary>The other day I observed that, in the balance between mindlessly using technology and deliberately honoring people's humanity (including my own), I tilt toward more humanity. But how does that cash out in everyday life?...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
