<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2017-08-10</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>None of My Business</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1590.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1590</id>
    <issued>2017-08-10</issued>
    <modified>2017-08-10</modified>
    <summary>Apropos of my latest journal entry "Politics is a Disease", here is a quote from Beyond Good and Evil (Section 251) by Friedrich Nietzsche:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Politics is a Disease</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1589.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1589</id>
    <issued>2017-07-18</issued>
    <modified>2017-07-18</modified>
    <summary>I have become progressively disenchanted with, indeed actively opposed to, politics. More and more, I see it as a disease that has grown to take over not only the "body politic" but also the individual mind and soul. My enemy is the assertion that "the personal is the political", and that there is no domain of life outside of politics - not art or music, not love or friendship, not philosophy or religion - nothing. This idea emerged in the radical Marxist-feminist movement of the late 1960s, and was given canonical expression in an essay by Carol Hanisch....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Happy 200th, Henry Thoreau</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1588.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1588</id>
    <issued>2017-07-12</issued>
    <modified>2017-07-12</modified>
    <summary>Today is the 200th anniversary of Henry David Thoreau's birth. To celebrate, I've published two books on his philosophy of life: The Upland Farm (a 50-page original exploration in the form of a journal) and Seasons of Thoreau (a 300-page compilation of quotes from his writings). Both books are available for free on my website, and can also be purchased in paperback and ebook formats from Amazon....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Poetry as Code</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1587.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1587</id>
    <issued>2017-06-21</issued>
    <modified>2017-06-21</modified>
    <summary>A few months ago, in preparation for composing a cycle of poems on Nietzsche's ethical philosophy (now half done and provisionally entitled Songs of Zarathustra), I made the time to re-read my favorite book on the writing of metrical poetry: All the Fun's in How You Say a Thing by Timothy Steele. This also inspired me to revisit and revise some of the poems and translations I published years ago in my book Ancient Fire. Sadly, I discovered that those early poems were rather buggy; the translations of Horace were especially malformed and a few of them required major refactoring so that they would compile from a metrical perspective....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>RFC 8141: Uniform Resource Names</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1586.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1586</id>
    <issued>2017-04-27</issued>
    <modified>2017-04-27</modified>
    <summary>Long, long ago on an Internet far, far away, some forward-thinking technologists defined several different types of identifiers called Uniform Resource Locators or URLs (for locating things - say, an article published online) and Uniform Resource Names or URNs (for permanently naming things without necessarily locating them - say, identifying a book by its ISBN no matter where a physical or electronic copy might be located). Some years later, a grand unified theory of identifiers was formulated, leading to the creation of Uniform Resource Identifiers (URIs) including both URLs and URNs (and URCs, but who's ever heard of those?). Even though most URIs that we use today are URLs, URNs as specified in RFC 2141 have continued to be widely deployed, especially for bibliographic purposes and as XML namespace names. Because the communities that use URNs have felt the need to make some slight adjustments to the syntax and to align URNs with the formal definition of URIs, back in 2010 folks at the IETF decided to start work on a new document to obsolete RFC 2141. It took us 7 years (!), but here we are today with RFC 8141 to bring URNs into the modern age (almost exactly 20 years after the publication of RFC 2141 in 1997). Special thanks to John Klensin for co-editing this specification with me!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Conceptism</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1585.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1585</id>
    <issued>2017-04-02</issued>
    <modified>2017-04-02</modified>
    <summary>While dipping back into Baltasar Gracián's Art of Worldly Wisdom recently, I got curious about the author, who it turns out was both a practitioner and a theoretician of a 17th-century Iberian literary style called conceptism. My interest was further piqued when I learned that conceptist writers attempted to express intricate conceptual meanings in a very concise form, and that both Schopenhauer and Nietzsche were great admirers of Gracián (in Nietzsche's case perhaps reflected in his aphoristic style). I'm reminded also of Yevgeny Zamyatin's essay Theme and Plot, in which he espoused a concentrated brevity that he called "the art of writing with ninety-proof ink" (Zamyatin, in turn, was a great admirer of Nietzsche). These stylistic currents strike a deep chord with me, given my project of writing six extremely compressed books on eudaimonia. Speaking of which, now that I'm almost done with the book about Thoreau I'm making fast progress on a cycle of philosophical poems about Nietzsche....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
