<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2023-11-08</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>RFC 9525: Service Identity in TLS</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1829.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1829</id>
    <issued>2023-11-08</issued>
    <modified>2023-11-08</modified>
    <summary>In November of 2002, I attended my first meeting of the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF), the premier standards-setting organization for the Internet. Since that initial exposure at IETF 55 in Atlanta, I have chaired working groups, run Birds of a Feather (BoF) sessions, acted as an expert reviewer, and served on the Internet Engineering Steering Group and the RFC Series Oversight Committee. As of today, I've also authored 49 documents in the IETF's Request for Comments (RFC) series, which puts me in roughly the top 1% of RFC authors. The RFC published today is an updated specification for verifying the identity of servers in the context of Transport Layer Security, which is the primary protocol for protecting communication over the Internet (think the 's' in 'https'). I co-authored the previous version of this document (RFC 6125) with Jeff Hodges and this new version with Rich Salz, both of whom were a pleasure to work with. Although I still have a few residual IETF commitments, this RFC will in all likelihood be the last one I author, since my writing energy is now devoted to philosophy books, not technical specifications. At least I'm going out with a bang, because this document (along with RFC 9325, which I also co-authored) is cited by well over a hundred other RFCs and thus plays a significant role in helping to keep the Internet secure....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Be Careful What You Measure</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1828.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1828</id>
    <issued>2023-10-27</issued>
    <modified>2023-10-27</modified>
    <summary>In business, it's often said that "if you can't measure it, you can't manage it." This aphorism is frequently attributed to Peter Drucker, although wrongly; instead it's pulled from a saying by quality expert W. Edwards Deming, despite the fact that his point was the exact opposite: "It is wrong to suppose that if you can't measure it, you can't manage it – a costly myth."...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Overcoming Savagery</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1827.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1827</id>
    <issued>2023-10-14</issued>
    <modified>2023-10-14</modified>
    <summary>The genocidal atrocities committed last weekend against Israeli citizens by thousands of Hamas terrorists are literally unspeakable. No words, and certainly no words I can say, have the power to heal such monstrous wounds. Yet one must not remain silent....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #19: The Nature of Life</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1826.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1826</id>
    <issued>2023-10-13</issued>
    <modified>2023-10-13</modified>
    <summary>Aristotle was the first biologist. Sadly, even though around one-third of his extant writings are devoted to living things, few of his interpreters take the biological basis of Aristotle's philosophy very seriously. This despite the fact that Charles Darwin said in a late letter that his "two gods" Linnaeus and Cuvier were "mere school-boys to old Aristotle"! It's a shame that Darwin didn't live long enough to study and comment on Aristotle's biological writings....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Sentience and Salience</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1825.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1825</id>
    <issued>2023-09-30</issued>
    <modified>2023-09-30</modified>
    <summary>As you might have guessed from yesterday's post about opinion machines, I'm skeptical that so-called artificial intelligence systems will exhibit sentience anytime soon. Thus, although my primary concern is how humans will act in relation to these systems (even more personally, how I will act), I figure it can't hurt to sketch out my thinking on the broader topic....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Opinion Machines</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1824.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1824</id>
    <issued>2023-09-29</issued>
    <modified>2023-09-29</modified>
    <summary>As I've striven over the last few years to hold fewer opinions, those who hold opinions about seemingly everything have become more noticeable to me. Whether it's the prospects for runaway inflation, the underlying causes for increasing loneliness in society, or the likely outcome of the upcoming elections in Ecuador, some bloggers and pundits are like opinion machines, able to crank out a position on anything at a moment's notice....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
