<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2024-10-25</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>A Visit to the Dentist</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1914.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1914</id>
    <issued>2024-10-25</issued>
    <modified>2024-10-25</modified>
    <summary>During a visit to the dentist the other day, I experimented with what I recently called radical gratitude. Throughout the visit, I asked myself: how much of what I experienced could I perceive as a gift to be enjoyed and appreciated? (To be clear, I actually like going to the dentist, so this wasn't as much of a stretch for me as it might be for others.)...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics VIII.9-IX.3</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1913.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1913</id>
    <issued>2024-10-20</issued>
    <modified>2024-10-20</modified>
    <summary>Moving on from his discussions of ideal relationships and then unequal relationships, Aristotle first takes a detour into different forms of political community (monarchy, aristocracy, democracy, etc.). This likely strikes us as strange, until Aristotle explains that philia holds societies together even more than justice does; in this context, I would translate the term as brotherhood (a somewhat attenuated kind of loving in especially short supply these days, it seems!). The idea is that philia exists to the extent that two or more people share common goals and activities, such as workmates (Aristotle's example is actually shipmates on a commercial venture), fellow soldiers, neighbors, participants in a religious order, or members of a social club. And all of these specific varieties of association exist under the broad framework of the overall society in which you live....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics VIII.6-8</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1912.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1912</id>
    <issued>2024-10-18</issued>
    <modified>2024-10-18</modified>
    <summary>Following up on his presentation of an ideal of human relationships, in Nicomachean Ethics VIII.6-8 Aristotle starts to investigate some of the variables that lead to less than ideal outcomes. Because ideally love and friendship in all their many forms entails a kind of equality, one of these variables is inequality between the two people involved, with respect to common attributes such as wealth, power, social class, fame, beauty, etc. As a modern example, consider the employees of a large corporation: it's highly unlikely, perhaps even unheard of, that the CEO will have a close relationship with the guy in the mailroom; the power gap is simply too wide. Or, to take the example that Aristotle uses, a ruler who is blessed with great wealth, absolute power, noble birth, and good looks usually surrounds himself with those who are useful (henchmen and servants and the like) and those who are pleasant (flatterers and entertainers and the like), but not with people of excellent character who take life seriously. Indeed, although the seriously good person is inherently both useful and enjoyable, such a person is not inclined to befriend a ruler unless the ruler is also superior in virtue, and that doesn't happen often....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Radical Gratitude</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1911.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1911</id>
    <issued>2024-10-15</issued>
    <modified>2024-10-15</modified>
    <summary>While attempting recently to render the first few lines of Tao Te Ching ยง14 about the nature of the Tao, I came up with the following:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Beowulf</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1910.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1910</id>
    <issued>2024-10-13</issued>
    <modified>2024-10-13</modified>
    <summary>As part of my background research for composing an epic poem about Pyrrho, I'm reading epics from around the world. So far this year I've read both the Iliad and the Odyssey twice (in Richmond Lattimore's masterful translations), Milton's Paradise Lost, the Argonautica by Apollonius of Rhodes, and most recently Beowulf. I'm also about halfway through Virgil's Aeneid (in John Dryden's translation), after which I intend to start on Ferdowsi's great Persian epic, the Shahnameh. I'm also halfway through my friend Dave Jilk's newly published science-fiction novel in the form of an epic poem, entitled Epoch: A Poetic Psy-Phi Saga (more on that soon). And there are plenty more where these came from!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Middlemarch</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1909.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1909</id>
    <issued>2024-10-12</issued>
    <modified>2024-10-12</modified>
    <summary>The other day I finished reading George Eliot's novel Middlemarch. This was my second attempt, since a few years ago I had made it about halfway through but then got distracted with other projects. Middlemarch is widely considered one of the greatest novels in the English language, and I can't disagree. The aspect that most impresses me is Eliot's deep understanding of human character, emotion, and deliberation, for good and for ill. As befits Eliot's intellectual interests (she was the first to translate Spinoza's Ethics from Latin into English), that understanding is simultaneously both psychological and philosophical. I love how she provides ethical insights at just the right moments in the narrative: "character too is a process and an unfolding"; "character is not cut in marble - it is not something solid and unalterable. It is something living and changing, and may become diseased as our bodies do"; "every limit is a beginning as well as an ending"; "there is no creature whose inward being is so strong that it is not greatly determined by what lies outside it"; "is there not a genius for feeling nobly which also reigns over human spirits?" (etc.). British novelist Robert McCrum once called Middlemarch "a cathedral of words" and it certainly is long (my copy, printed in the 1920s, clocks in around 1350 pages, although more modern editions are around 800). Yet Eliot needed that vast structure to house the many fascinating characters she created, to portray their interrelationships, and to resolve their conflicts. Brava!...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
