<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2020-06-19</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophy and Anger</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1641.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1641</id>
    <issued>2020-06-19</issued>
    <modified>2020-06-19</modified>
    <summary>The world is full of anger, both well-founded and ill-founded. In a future post I'll talk about well-founded anger, but this time I'll provide some reflections on ill-founded anger....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Dialogue and Deliberation</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1640.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1640</id>
    <issued>2020-06-19</issued>
    <modified>2020-06-19</modified>
    <summary>One of Aristotle’s characteristic methods for solving philosophical problems is dialectic: upon (i) reaching an impasse (aporia), he (ii) surveys existing explanations (logoi) and reputable opinions (endoxa), (iii) engages in analysis to remove paradoxes and draw distinctions, then (iv) formulates a synthesis that harmonizes the explanations and saves the appearances (phainomena)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Crisis Investing</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1639.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1639</id>
    <issued>2020-05-28</issued>
    <modified>2020-05-28</modified>
    <summary>Exactly four years ago I wrote a post entitled "Investing for the Rest of Us", in which I discussed the permanent portfolio investing method, invented by Harry Browne. The permanent portfolio has two additional benefits that I've come to fully appreciate only this year: uncorrelated assets and forced rebalancing....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Serenity</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1638.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1638</id>
    <issued>2020-02-09</issued>
    <modified>2020-02-09</modified>
    <summary>Just as people used to ask me how I accomplish so much, recently a few people have asked me how I stay so serene. Although this question is harder to answer, I'll give it a try....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Zamyatin's WE</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1637.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1637</id>
    <issued>2020-01-14</issued>
    <modified>2020-01-14</modified>
    <summary>In 1921, Yevgeny Zamyatin finished writing WE, the Ur-text for most dystopian novels since then (Anthem, 1984, Brave New World, etc.). In 1924, Zamyatin's novel, not yet (in fact never) published in the Soviet Union, was first brought to the world by E.P. Dutton and Company of New York in an English translation by Gregory Zilboorg. Because 95 years have passed since then, Dr. Zilboorg's translation is finally in the public domain - and I have just republished it online at my website for public-domain books, the Monadnock Valley Press....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Jo Walton's Thessaly Trilogy</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1636.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1636</id>
    <issued>2020-01-01</issued>
    <modified>2020-01-01</modified>
    <summary>Fresh from a re-reading of Plato's dialogues, recently I dove into Jo Walton's Thessaly trilogy (The Just City, The Philosopher Kings, and Necessity), a speculative epic set in a society consistent with Plato's Republic. It's an enjoyable, thought-provoking blend of science fiction, ancient Greek myth, and Platonic philosophy. Although I recommended Walton's trilogy if you like philosophical novels, I do take issue with several aspects of her story....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
