<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2017-01-29</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Ism Book Updates</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1575.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1575</id>
    <issued>2017-01-29</issued>
    <modified>2017-01-29</modified>
    <summary>One of the great things about publishing to the Internet, and nowadays print on demand as well, is that you can continually improve what you have written. Among my writings, there is no better example than The Ism Book: A Field Guide to Philosophy. I first wrote this highly interlinked book using HyperCard on my first Macintosh computer, then ported it to the Internet in 1996. Since then it has undergone numerous revisions as I've broadened and deepened my understanding of philosophical history and concepts. Last week while in flight to and from California I marked up a copy of the book with copious amounts of red ink, and today I keyed in a large number of edits (in fact I've been making numerous fixes for the last two months). Now I just need to port all these changes over to the physical book and republish it....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Irrelevance of Government</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1574.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1574</id>
    <issued>2017-01-21</issued>
    <modified>2017-01-21</modified>
    <summary>Imagine life a thousand years ago in, say, France or Italy. The society and culture in which you are immersed is deeply focused on religion. The words of your local priest have great significance, a bishop or archbishop is a personage of divine importance, and the Pope is like a spiritual emperor. Those wishing to effect social change, or tell other people what to do, or pursue their own personal advantage, necessarily use the tool that is ready to hand, and that is the apparatus of the church....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>There's Never Just One Cause</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1573.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1573</id>
    <issued>2017-01-20</issued>
    <modified>2017-01-20</modified>
    <summary>Some years ago I did some intensive research into the origins of the industrial revolution. At the time I was working my way out of the Rand meme, so the starting point of my investigation was her assertion that the cause of the industrial revolution was the philosophy of Aristotle. My conclusion was that Rand was wrong, and that there were multiple causes involved. I presented the fruits of my research in a paper published by the UK Libertarian Alliance, entitled Ayn Rand and the Ascent of Man....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Monadnock Valley Press Annual Report 2016</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1572.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1572</id>
    <issued>2017-01-14</issued>
    <modified>2017-01-14</modified>
    <summary>In 2016 I again spent very little time on posting public-domain texts at the Monadnock Valley Press - only a few works by Henry David Thoreau, Virginia Woolf, and Blaise Pascal. Once I finish my forthcoming book on Thoreau, I plan to clear out a backlog of books, essays, and plays by Ibsen, Confucius, Emerson, Montaigne, Spinoza, Petrarch, Lucretius, Epictetus, Seneca, and Cicero. With revenue of $248.62 and expenses of $181.58, we earned only $67.04 in 2016, too. It's a good thing I don't write philosophy books for the money!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Thoreau on Magnanimity</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1571.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1571</id>
    <issued>2017-01-08</issued>
    <modified>2017-01-08</modified>
    <summary>Reading is one thing; understanding is another. Part of what I do while "working through" the writings of a thinker like Thoreau is to delve deeply into key themes, concepts, and even words. Consider, for example, this sentence from Economy, the first chapter of Walden: "To be a philosopher is not merely to have subtle thoughts, nor even to found a school, but so to love wisdom as to live according to its dictates, a life of simplicity, independence, magnanimity, and trust." When reading on the surface, it's easy to gloss over a sentence like this and merely have a pleasant feeling that it's a good thing to live philosophically. Yet what exactly is Thoreau talking about here? What does he mean by the somewhat vague and uncommon word magnanimity? To figure that out can require quite a bit of digging....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Corporatization</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1570.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1570</id>
    <issued>2017-01-06</issued>
    <modified>2017-01-06</modified>
    <summary>While taking my dog to two different doctors the other day (long story), I discovered that veterinary practices are increasing being bought up by large corporate entities like PetVet and VCA. Your seemingly small, local caregiver just might have sold his or her practice to one of these companies, supposedly while still retaining control over medical decision-making (that little voice in the back of my head is saying "he who pays the piper, calls the tune")....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
