<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2024-11-03</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics IX.9-12</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1917.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1917</id>
    <issued>2024-11-03</issued>
    <modified>2024-11-03</modified>
    <summary>In IX.9-12, Aristotle finishes off his consideration of love and friendship by wondering how many close relationships one really needs, the times in life when such relationships are most valuable, etc....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics IX.8</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1916.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1916</id>
    <issued>2024-10-29</issued>
    <modified>2024-10-29</modified>
    <summary>Up until now Aristotle has considered love for other people, but in IX.8 Aristotle asks some probing questions about love of self. All the central qualities of love (summarized in my post about IX.4-7) seem to apply most of all to oneself, such that love toward others seems to grow out of self-love. But how can this be? After all, it also seems that the unserious/unworthy [phaulos] person whose character is corrupted [mochthēros] acts out of pure selfishness. The conflict between these appearances sets up what Aristotle calls an impasse [aporia], and we'll need to find a way through it in order to make further progress toward wisdom and sagacity....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics IX.4-7</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1915.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1915</id>
    <issued>2024-10-26</issued>
    <modified>2024-10-26</modified>
    <summary>In his translation of the Nicomachean Ethics, Joe Sachs notes that at IX.4 Aristotle turns away from the factors that cause certain relationships to fall short or fall apart and instead turns toward the central factors that unify the experience of philia. These include: loving someone for their own sake, wishing that they might have all good things in life, actually doing or giving some of those good things for them, wanting them to live and to live well, wishing to spend time together and share in the activities of life, valuing the same things, sharing in the joys and sorrows of life, etc....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Visit to the Dentist</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1914.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1914</id>
    <issued>2024-10-25</issued>
    <modified>2024-10-25</modified>
    <summary>During a visit to the dentist the other day, I experimented with what I recently called radical gratitude. Throughout the visit, I asked myself: how much of what I experienced could I perceive as a gift to be enjoyed and appreciated? (To be clear, I actually like going to the dentist, so this wasn't as much of a stretch for me as it might be for others.)...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics VIII.9-IX.3</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1913.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1913</id>
    <issued>2024-10-20</issued>
    <modified>2024-10-20</modified>
    <summary>Moving on from his discussions of ideal relationships and then unequal relationships, Aristotle first takes a detour into different forms of political community (monarchy, aristocracy, democracy, etc.). This likely strikes us as strange, until Aristotle explains that philia holds societies together even more than justice does; in this context, I would translate the term as brotherhood (a somewhat attenuated kind of loving in especially short supply these days, it seems!). The idea is that philia exists to the extent that two or more people share common goals and activities, such as workmates (Aristotle's example is actually shipmates on a commercial venture), fellow soldiers, neighbors, participants in a religious order, or members of a social club. And all of these specific varieties of association exist under the broad framework of the overall society in which you live....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics VIII.6-8</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1912.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1912</id>
    <issued>2024-10-18</issued>
    <modified>2024-10-18</modified>
    <summary>Following up on his presentation of an ideal of human relationships, in Nicomachean Ethics VIII.6-8 Aristotle starts to investigate some of the variables that lead to less than ideal outcomes. Because ideally love and friendship in all their many forms entails a kind of equality, one of these variables is inequality between the two people involved, with respect to common attributes such as wealth, power, social class, fame, beauty, etc. As a modern example, consider the employees of a large corporation: it's highly unlikely, perhaps even unheard of, that the CEO will have a close relationship with the guy in the mailroom; the power gap is simply too wide. Or, to take the example that Aristotle uses, a ruler who is blessed with great wealth, absolute power, noble birth, and good looks usually surrounds himself with those who are useful (henchmen and servants and the like) and those who are pleasant (flatterers and entertainers and the like), but not with people of excellent character who take life seriously. Indeed, although the seriously good person is inherently both useful and enjoyable, such a person is not inclined to befriend a ruler unless the ruler is also superior in virtue, and that doesn't happen often....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
