<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2025-09-03</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Vibe Thinking</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1987.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1987</id>
    <issued>2025-09-03</issued>
    <modified>2025-09-03</modified>
    <summary>Over lunch last week, a friend and I had an interesting discussion about the future of computer programming. At his startup, he makes extensive use of machine learning and large language models but still writes plenty of code. He called this "AI-assisted coding", in contradistinction to "vibe coding”, whereby people who don't know how to code ask the LLM chatbot to generate all the code for them. He also noted that when an LLM generates code, you have to get really good at reading code - a skill that even old-style programmers haven't traditionally cultivated or enjoyed....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Greek Tragedy and American Jazz</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1986.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1986</id>
    <issued>2025-08-25</issued>
    <modified>2025-08-25</modified>
    <summary>Cross-pollination is a wondrous thing. Over the last few months I've been reading about two topics that might seem quite far apart: ancient Greek tragedy and American jazz. In the first category, I'm working my way through all the extant tragedies of Aeschylus, Sophocles, and Euripides, and also reading literary and philosophical analysis of tragic drama, such as Walter Kaufmann's Tragedy and Philosophy. In the second category, I've been reading biographies of great jazz musicians and composers (Armstrong, Ellington, Monk, Mingus, Coltrane, etc.) as well as historical and philosophical analysis of the meaning of jazz and blues in American culture, especially some amazing books by Albert Murray and some essays by Ralph Ellison....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Historical Aspirations</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1985.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1985</id>
    <issued>2025-08-25</issued>
    <modified>2025-08-25</modified>
    <summary>Following up on my post about thinking historically, here are some further reflections on the methodological insights (and, to my mind, shortcomings) of my favorite historian, David Hackett Fischer....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Sunlight and Shadow</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1984.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1984</id>
    <issued>2025-08-24</issued>
    <modified>2025-08-24</modified>
    <summary>Overnight I realized that my post yesterday about Walter Kaufmann's account of love as a virtue could give the impression that my view of life is rather dark. Whereas it seems that Kaufmann had something of a tragic sense of life, my outlook is decidedly sunnier. Since I was quite young, I've wondered at the cosmic improbability of being alive. Several months ago I put it this way to a friend:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What Is This Thing Called Love?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1983.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1983</id>
    <issued>2025-08-16</issued>
    <modified>2025-08-16</modified>
    <summary>The German-born American philosopher Walter Kaufmann, best known for his translations (and postwar rehabilitation) of Nietzsche, also produced original philosophical works of great worth, as well as a fine collection of poems of which I'm quite fond. In his 1961 book The Faith of a Heretic, among other things Kaufmann attempted to sketch out a personal ethic appropriate for contemporary human beings. Although his accounts of virtues like courage and intellectual honesty span only a few pages each, they are dense with meaning. Here I'll try to summarize his perspective on what Cole Porter famously named "this thing called love"....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>AI and I</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1982.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1982</id>
    <issued>2025-08-21</issued>
    <modified>2025-08-21</modified>
    <summary>With all the Sturm und Drang about so-called artificial intelligence right now, I'd like to make it clear that I don't use these technologies. For me, the primary consideration is not that AI will, on balance, degrade humanity's already weakened ability to engage in independent thinking and humane interaction (although I think evidence is mounting that this will be the case). No, I simply find these technologies uninteresting....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
