<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2019-03-07</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #9: τέλος</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1624.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1624</id>
    <issued>2019-03-07</issued>
    <modified>2019-03-07</modified>
    <summary>Part of my goal in writing an epitome of Aristotle's writings on personal excellence is to get closer to their original meaning, which I do by reflecting deeply on how to render crucial Greek words into English. Consider this cluster: τέλος, τελεία, τελειώτατον. In his book Aristotle on the Human Good, Richard Kraut translates them with variations on the English word "perfection". In present-day English, "perfect" has connotations of being absolutely without blemish; thus something perfect seems static and cold and unchanging, not dynamic and warm and living. I get a distinctly unworldly (dare I say Platonic?) feeling from Kraut's translation. Yet in Greek τέλος is something much simpler: the end-marker or finish-line of a racecourse. A τέλος is a goal; you can achieve a goal or complete a race, but you don't perfect a goal or perfect a race. Similarly with τελεία: Aristotle speaks of τελεία ἀρετή, which I would render as complete excellence (not "perfect virtue"). So also with τελειώτατον: in his analysis of εὐδαιμονία or living well Aristotle mentions that the highest goal of human action needs to be the most complete (not "most perfect") because if you could add anything more to it then there would be a more valuable goal. In all of these instances, I am tempted to find the idea of "completing" or "most completing" behind the scenes; in Aristotle's philosophy, the concept of ἐντελέχεια (becoming complete, achieving a goal, completing a task) is always central. And note that the task (ἔργον) you're working at (ἐνέργεια) is not imposed from outside but grows organically from within; Aristotle's teleology (that's that τέλος again) is not universal but particular, individual, personal. Thus my working title: Complete Yourself....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #8: σοφία</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1623.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1623</id>
    <issued>2019-02-18</issued>
    <modified>2019-02-18</modified>
    <summary>In Book V of the Eudemian Ethics [1], Aristotle discusses the excellences of thinking things through (ἀρεταί διανοετικαί, usually translated as "the intellectual virtues"), in contrast to the excellences of character or ἀρεταί ἠθικαί. Recently I wrote about the more practical of the two primary excellences of thought: φρόνησις (which I translate as "wisdom"). Here I take a first glance at the more theoretical of the two: σοφία....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Randian Confusion</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1622.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1622</id>
    <issued>2019-02-16</issued>
    <modified>2019-02-16</modified>
    <summary>After many months of reading Aristotle's philosophy and commentary thereon, recently I decided to re-read Ayn Rand's essay "The Objectivist Ethics", wherein Rand criticizes Aristotle for not considering ethics to be an exact science. I have no idea what that would mean. Consider, for instance, the relevant Wikipedia page (not necessarily reliable, but often a good start), which states:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Virtues Ancient and Modern</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1621.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1621</id>
    <issued>2019-02-07</issued>
    <modified>2019-02-07</modified>
    <summary>In his book Confronting Aristotle's Ethics, Eugene Garver explores how, for Aristotle, personal excellence is also interpersonal excellence: because of the intensely social nature of ancient communities, virtues like courage and moderation had value because they protected and preserved the balance of the community as a whole. Thus courage was really valor in battle against another community that would have enslaved your own people, not the courage of principled resistance (e.g., Rosa Parks) or intellectual integrity (e.g., Galileo). Thus moderation was about controlling your urges (adultery upsets social harmony) and keeping in good physical condition (it's hard to be valorous if you're grossly overweight). And so on....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #7: φρόνησις</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1620.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1620</id>
    <issued>2019-02-05</issued>
    <modified>2019-02-05</modified>
    <summary>For Aristotle, the various excellences of character (courage, moderation, justice, and the like) are all instances of tending to find a balance between overdoing and underdoing a particular kind of action or feeling, either generally or in a particular respect (e.g., becoming angry in the wrong situations, toward the wrong kinds of people, too quickly, too strongly, etc.). Borrowing terminology from archery, he speaks of balance as a matter of hitting the target (σκοπός) and of imbalance as a matter of missing the mark (ἁμαρτία)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Personalism</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1619.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1619</id>
    <issued>2019-01-19</issued>
    <modified>2019-01-19</modified>
    <summary>In my philosophy department talk last October, I said something that might turn out to be more true than I had realized: it's a worthy ambition to become an accomplished person. Recalling that there used to be a philosophical journal called The Personalist, I've started to wonder if "personalism" might be an appropriate name for my approach to philosophy. A quick Internet search revealed that there has been a loose tradition of personalism over the last 200 years, encompassing thinkers as diverse as William James, Karol Wotyla (Pope John Paul II), and, appropriately enough for this weekend, Martin Luther King, Jr. (who studied with personalist theologian Edgar Sheffield Brightman at Boston University)....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
