<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2017-02-12</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Limited Liability</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1582.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1582</id>
    <issued>2017-02-12</issued>
    <modified>2017-02-12</modified>
    <summary>Someone I know who is an avowed socialist told me he'd be much more sympathetic to libertarian views if we didn't need big government to protect us from big business....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Forever Jung</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1581.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1581</id>
    <issued>2017-02-12</issued>
    <modified>2017-02-12</modified>
    <summary>Recently I got to talking with a friend about personality assessments, especially in relation to hiring and talent development. It took me awhile to figure out why we were not in agreement: he was thinking about the Myers-Briggs Type Indicator (MBTI) whereas I was thinking about assessments based on the five-factor model (also called the "big five") of personality traits....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why Do I Think What I Think?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1580.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1580</id>
    <issued>2017-02-11</issued>
    <modified>2017-02-11</modified>
    <summary>Most people seem to believe that their thoughts are right, and that this is so because they are righteous people. Those who disagree with them are wrong and have bad intentions; those who agree with them have the truth on their side and have good intentions....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Thoreau on Genius</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1579.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1579</id>
    <issued>2017-02-04</issued>
    <modified>2017-02-04</modified>
    <summary>Someone who knows that I'm writing a book on Thoreau sent me a link from BrainPickings.org about Thoreau's views on the topic of genius. Drawing on the "Thursday" and "Friday" chapters of A Week on the Concord and Merrimack Rivers, the author focuses her brief essay on the difference between an artisan, an artist, and a genius....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>HTTPS No More</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1578.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1578</id>
    <issued>2017-02-02</issued>
    <modified>2017-02-02</modified>
    <summary>One unfortunate byproduct of shutting down my VPS and moving my websites to GitHub Pages is that I'm no longer hosting the stpeter.im domain via HTTPS. Although I'm not overjoyed about this, I'm also not deeply disturbed by it given that my personal website isn't exactly the kind of information that needs to be encrypted in transit (and someone could retrieve it over HTTPS from GitHub.com if they really wanted to). Mike Linksvayer helpfully pointed out to me that there are some solutions, and I'll look into those soon. In the meantime I've modified all the cross-links within my websites so that they use http instead of https URLs....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>VPS No More</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1577.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1577</id>
    <issued>2017-02-01</issued>
    <modified>2017-02-01</modified>
    <summary>A few weeks ago I spent most of a Sunday trying, and failing, to upgrade the Debian Linux distribution on my virtual private server (VPS). After the Linux experts at my hosting company also failed after 90 minutes of fighting with the thing, I realized that the time had come to shut down my VPS and find simpler solutions. For me, that turned out to be FastMail for my email addresses and GitHub Pages for my websites (I was also hosting a few WordPress sites for friends, which I've moved to WordPress.com). The only things I miss at this point are HTTPS for one of my websites, and the personal XMPP server I was running. Yet the HTTPS wasn't really all that critical (I know, HTTPS Everywhere and all that, but in practice I'm not running transactional websites and in fact all of my sites are even free of JavaScript - I guess I'm a Web 1.0 kind of person). And although the XMPP server was a fine thing, I do run jabber.org and I've had a few addresses there forever, so I might as well use them. Simplify, simplify!...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
