<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2020-11-24</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Who Was Aristotle?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1656.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1656</id>
    <issued>2020-11-24</issued>
    <modified>2020-11-24</modified>
    <summary>Greatness is out of fashion these days -- even suspect because of its seeming elitism. Yet it is an inconvenient truth that talents, opportunities, efforts, and achievements vary greatly. In every field of human endeavor there are only a few people who are remembered even 50 years after their passing; multiply 50 by 50 and we reach 2500 years, nearly the upper limit of recorded history, whose rolls are inhabited by a minuscule percentage of those who have ever lived. Even fewer of those remembered are anything but a name, whose works and deeds are still widely studied to this day. At the very pinnacle of these is Aristotle, whose concepts and insights form the foundation of much of human knowledge, science, art, culture, and society....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It Was Twenty Years Ago Today</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1655.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1655</id>
    <issued>2020-11-21</issued>
    <modified>2020-11-21</modified>
    <summary>On November 21st, 2000, I posted the first entry in this online journal. Although I had tried my hand at writing a weblog even before then (e.g., using a tool for posting entries through a Jabber messaging app), writing at my own website was more appealing. Given that I'm still posting here twenty years later, I declare my original experiment a success. Here's how I characterized this space in that first entry:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle's Dialectical Pedagogy: A Review of Revaluing Ethics by Thomas W. Smith</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1654.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1654</id>
    <issued>2020-11-12</issued>
    <modified>2020-11-12</modified>
    <summary>In my research toward writing Complete Yourself: Aristotle on Human Fulfillment, I have read dozens and dozens of books about Aristotle's ethics and his philosophy in general. A small number of those books stand out in the crowded field of Aristotelian studies, but only one of them has been a revelation to me: Revaluing Ethics: Aristotle's Dialectical Pedagogy by Thomas W. Smith....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Election Survival Guide</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1653.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1653</id>
    <issued>2020-11-01</issued>
    <modified>2020-11-01</modified>
    <summary>Every four years I dread the prospect of yet another election for president of the United States. What a depressing, anxiety-ridden spectacle! It's almost enough to make me a monarchist (if only we could find the right sort of monarch, of course)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Wider Palette</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1652.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1652</id>
    <issued>2020-10-30</issued>
    <modified>2020-10-30</modified>
    <summary>In my most recent post ("Beyond Binary"), I talked about the need to transcend dichotomies and false alternatives. One aspect of doing so is recognizing what I called a wider palette of viewpoints, which is easy to do in philosophy and psychology but not in politics (at least not in American politics with its two-party system)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Beyond Binary</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1651.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1651</id>
    <issued>2020-09-20</issued>
    <modified>2020-09-20</modified>
    <summary>As political polarization proliferates, it's beneficial to explore realms of thought that are not limited to left vs. right and us vs. them. Personally, I'm partial to philosophy: it's impossible to reduce all of philosophical thinking to, say, Epicureans vs. Stoics without ignoring the deep and unique contributions of Platonists, Aristotelians, Taoists, Buddhists, Confucians, Hindus, Christians, humanists, skeptics, existentialists, and many more....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
