<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2025-06-10</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Learning Excellence</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1969.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1969</id>
    <issued>2025-06-10</issued>
    <modified>2025-06-10</modified>
    <summary>In my post about Alasdair MacIntyre the other day, I expressed admiration for his recognition that we need to learn the principles of action from the practices life. Here is a quote on the topic from his last essay:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Living on the Margins</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1968.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1968</id>
    <issued>2025-06-08</issued>
    <modified>2025-06-08</modified>
    <summary>While reading today the final essay published by Alasdair MacIntyre, I was struck by the following two passages:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Utopia Is Not an Option</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1967.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1967</id>
    <issued>2025-06-02</issued>
    <modified>2025-06-02</modified>
    <summary>The recent death of philosopher Alasdair MacIntyre has prompted numerous assessments of his work (which, I'll admit, I have not looked at in decades - an oversight that I plan to remedy soon because of his status as perhaps the most prominent neo-Aristotelian thinker of the last fifty years). Several of the remembrances I've read expressed frustration with the lack of specificity in MacIntyre's political philosophy, which boils down to what my college professor Charles Larmore called "polis envy": the desire to construct communities on the model of the ancient Greek city-states, in which all the citizens worked together for the sake of a common purpose and a common vision of the good life. Only in such a setting, says MacIntyre, can human beings lead an ethically flourishing life....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Universe and Humanverse</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1966.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1966</id>
    <issued>2025-05-30</issued>
    <modified>2025-05-30</modified>
    <summary>As I have continued to read Spinoza's Ethics and at the same time apply Walter Kaufmann's suggestion to rethink every step critically, for a few days there I started to take notes toward a geometrical presentation of propositions I could agree with (e.g., instead beginning with a self-caused God who created the universe, my propositions began on more Aristotelian lines with being itself and an eternal universe)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Self-Deception</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1965.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1965</id>
    <issued>2025-05-26</issued>
    <modified>2025-05-26</modified>
    <summary>One of my personal aphorisms is: "The easiest thing in the world is self-deception."...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Step by Step</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1964.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1964</id>
    <issued>2025-05-24</issued>
    <modified>2025-05-24</modified>
    <summary>Combining threads from recent posts on Spinoza and on Walter Kaufmann, here are a few further thoughts on intellectual honesty and philosophical methodology....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
