<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2018-04-13</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Notes Toward an Aristotelian Philosophy of Music</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1606.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1606</id>
    <issued>2018-04-13</issued>
    <modified>2018-04-13</modified>
    <summary>In Book VIII of his Politics, Aristotle talks about music: its role in ancient Greek education, its differences from the other arts, and its philosophical significance. This is not an in-depth exploration of the philosophy of music (what I wouldn't give for his lost work Ρερὶ Μουσικῆς), but more of a cursory glance. Yet through extrapolation we can tease out some meaning from his discussion....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #4: ἀρετή</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1605.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1605</id>
    <issued>2018-02-12</issued>
    <modified>2018-02-12</modified>
    <summary>I'm starting to see that Aristotle's conception of ἀρετή (which I translate as thriving but which is more commonly translated as excellence or virtue) describes a deliberate practice of good judgment, reasoned choice, and planned activity resulting in a balance between extremes of action and emotional reaction in a particular domain of human life....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotelian Questions</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1604.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1604</id>
    <issued>2018-02-12</issued>
    <modified>2018-02-12</modified>
    <summary>My intent in writing a book on Aristotelian ethics is not to present exactly what Aristotle said (I'll leave that to scholars such as J.O. Urmson in his excellent epitome Aristotle's Ethics), but hopefully what he meant and even more pointedly what he means for us 2300+ years later. The goal is to present my own direct encounter with Aristotle, unmediated by millennia of often misguided scholarship and mistranslation. (Ironically, we need some scholarship to do that, so separating the wheat from the chaff is necessary.) Here are some of the questions I'll be trying answer:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle: A First Encounter</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1603.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1603</id>
    <issued>2018-02-04</issued>
    <modified>2018-02-04</modified>
    <summary>Aristotle's views on living well and doing well - what the ancient Greeks called εὐδαιμονία or eudaimonia - are some of the most enduring insights into ethics ever put into words. Yet the deepest meaning of those words is usually obscured by efforts to translate and interpret Aristotle's thoughts. In part the problem is linguistic, in part it is cultural, but ultimately it is philosophical: ancient Greek world views, Aristotle's among them, are very far from our modern ways of thinking and feeling....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Songs of Zarathustra Now Published</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1602.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1602</id>
    <issued>2018-02-03</issued>
    <modified>2018-02-03</modified>
    <summary>My short book on Friedrich Nietzsche, Songs of Zarathustra, is now published in paperback and ebook formats, and of course also on my website. Once again both the form and the content are unorthodox: I construe Nietzsche in a more humanistic way than most interpreters, and I do so in a cycle of 73 brief poems (including translations of some of Nietzsche's own verse). Neither aspect is likely to endear me to academics, but then I don't write for a scholarly audience - even though my books are based on a deep reading of the original texts....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Privacy FTW</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1601.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1601</id>
    <issued>2018-01-27</issued>
    <modified>2018-01-27</modified>
    <summary>Tomorrow (January 28th) is Data Privacy Day. Why not join in the celebration? Here are some suggestions to prevent absolutely everything you do online from being tracked:...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
