<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2025-04-24</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Slouching Towards Monarchy</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1956.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1956</id>
    <issued>2025-04-24</issued>
    <modified>2025-04-24</modified>
    <summary>Legend has it that after the Constitutional Convention finished its work in September 1787, Elizabeth Willing Powel, one of the most powerful and highly educated women in Philadelphia, asked Benjamin Franklin whether we now had a monarchy or a republic. Great question, Elizabeth! We're still trying to figure out the answer....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Democracy in Decline</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1955.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1955</id>
    <issued>2025-04-22</issued>
    <modified>2025-04-22</modified>
    <summary>Because of the long-running inversion of political power in America from the local level to the national level, these days we hear all about the decline of democracy in Washington, D.C. but very little about the decline of local democracy. This got me to thinking about representation where I live in Douglas County, Colorado....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Romanticism Reconsidered</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1954.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1954</id>
    <issued>2025-04-18</issued>
    <modified>2025-04-18</modified>
    <summary>To follow up on last month's post "Romanticism or Renaissance?", I decided to read two books by scholars for whom I have a great deal of respect: Classic, Romantic, and Modern by cultural historian Jacques Barzun and The Roots of Romanticism by intellectual historian Isaiah Berlin. Although I'm far from sagely on these matters now, I do feel somewhat better informed....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Nation of Many Nations</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1953.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1953</id>
    <issued>2025-04-15</issued>
    <modified>2025-04-15</modified>
    <summary>In Song of Myself, Walt Whitman declared himself to be "one of the great nation, the nation of many nations" - claiming identity as a northerner and a southerner, a Yankee, a Kentuckian, a Hoosier, a Badger, a Buckeye, and a habitan of numerous other places in North America. (Whitman contained multitudes, after all!)...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Four Causes of Fulfillment</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1952.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1952</id>
    <issued>2025-04-11</issued>
    <modified>2025-04-11</modified>
    <summary>Aristotle is famous, or infamous, for what is known as his doctrine of the four causes. As I’ve explained before, there are many misconceptions about these matters, but I’ll go with the traditional description for the purpose of this somewhat fanciful post about what causes an examined life of wisdom and fulfillment....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>He Who Pays the Piper Calls the Tune</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1951.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1951</id>
    <issued>2025-04-09</issued>
    <modified>2025-04-09</modified>
    <summary>Recently my alma mater, Columbia University, was back in the news because the Trump administration threatened to withhold $400 million in federal grants until the university changed some of its internal polocies. The political responses were predictable: populists were pleased about sticking it to leftist academics, faculty fulminated about threats to their intellectual freedom, the interim president lost her job over decisions she made, and a few folks quietly wondered about the wisdom of federal funding for so much educational activity and scientific research....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
