<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2022-10-06</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Thinking Forward</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1739.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1739</id>
    <issued>2022-10-06</issued>
    <modified>2022-10-06</modified>
    <summary>Much of what makes human beings distinctive is what Jacob Bronowski called "a sense of the future" (in addition to his old book by that name, see also more recently Homo Prospectus by Seligman, Railton, Baumeister, and Sripada). Certainly most animals can think at least a few minutes or maybe hours in advance, but they're not actively planning months or years ahead of time as humans can. Yet, perhaps under the influence of modern science, our conception of our intellectual capacities is often retrospective: reason is thought to be a faculty that formulates accurate conclusions and stable laws from the evidence we have painfully gathered in the past through induction, experiment, and the like....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Virtues: One or Many?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1738.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1738</id>
    <issued>2022-09-29</issued>
    <modified>2022-09-29</modified>
    <summary>In a post last week about the value of studying multiple philosophies, I observed that I have not read much Christian theology. As if on queue, I decided to read Augustine's Of the Morals of the Catholic Church, written in 388 CE. The impetus was a footnote on page 179 of Daniel C. Russell's book Practical Intelligence and the Virtues, where he said that he would not consider non-secular arguments for the unity of the virtues, such as Augustine's argument that there really is only one virtue, which is the love of God....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What Is Philosophy For?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1737.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1737</id>
    <issued>2022-09-25</issued>
    <modified>2022-09-25</modified>
    <summary>Occasionally one reads something so singularly misguided that it puts into stark relief a vital concern of human existence. In the case at hand, the vital concern is the place of philosophy in the best life for human beings and the piece of writing is a scholarly paper published just last week by philosopher Hanno Sauer, entitled "The End of History."...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Exploring Philosophies</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1736.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1736</id>
    <issued>2022-09-22</issued>
    <modified>2022-09-22</modified>
    <summary>In his magisterial cultural history of the last 500 years (From Dawn to Decadence), the late Jacques Barzun wrote as follows about the study of history (pp. 568-569):...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Decisions Accumulate</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1735.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1735</id>
    <issued>2022-09-15</issued>
    <modified>2022-09-15</modified>
    <summary>In a recent post entitled "How a Business Wins", Arnold Kling made the following observation:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Means and Ends</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1734.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1734</id>
    <issued>2022-09-08</issued>
    <modified>2022-09-08</modified>
    <summary>Last week we looked at the distinction between internal goods, external goods, and shared goods. At that time I touched on a further distinction between means and ends in life. Here again Aristotle can be of assistance, because he discusses these matters in his two major books about character and action, which have come down to us as the Nicomachean Ethics and the Eudemian Ethics....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
