<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2025-04-07</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Talking vs. Thinking</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1949.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1949</id>
    <issued>2025-04-07</issued>
    <modified>2025-04-07</modified>
    <summary>A friend and I have begun a pair reading of The Faith of a Heretic by Walter Kaufmann. It's the second time through for both of us and we have mutual admiration for Kaufmann, so we're excited about digging into this most personal of Kaufmann's books on philosophy and religion....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle on Freedom</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1948.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1948</id>
    <issued>2025-03-31</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-31</modified>
    <summary>As mentioned two weeks ago in my note "Translation as Thinking", the concepts used across time and space (and, even, across writers) can vary quite significantly in the meanings they capture. This is especially true regarding concepts that are rather vague in the first place, such as virtue, happiness, democracy, and - the subject of today's post - freedom....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Signal Failure</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1947.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1947</id>
    <issued>2025-03-30</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-30</modified>
    <summary>It's rare that I comment on day-to-day political happenings. Not only are they quite distressing of late, but in general I prefer to read not the Times but the Eternities, as Thoreau said. However, the recent kerfuffle regarding use of the Signal messaging app by Trump administration officials is too tempting a target, because I worked on secure messaging systems for 25+ years and can offer some insights....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Translating as Thinking</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1946.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1946</id>
    <issued>2025-03-17</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-17</modified>
    <summary>As noted as far back as 2016, I've been ruminating for years about how to render certain key terms of Aristotle's philosophy from ancient Greek into English. To date, the only outcome has been a glossary that I update regularly as I add more definitions and polish the existing ones. Recently I lighted upon a constructive way to put some of these renderings to the test: by translating a brief Aristotelian work whose title is usually presented as On Virtues and Vices....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Divinity of Being</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1945.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1945</id>
    <issued>2025-03-15</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-15</modified>
    <summary>While continuing my travels in the land of Aristotle (specifically, entering passages from his Metaphysics into my digital commonplace book), I chanced recently upon the shoreline of the vast ocean of theology. Knowing that I would quickly drown if I ventured too far from shore, I merely picked up a few seashells, waded in up to my knees, and enjoyed the view of the endless depths. Even though these are mostly uncharted waters for me (despite a few related posts almost twenty years ago), I'll give a short report on my excursion....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Romanticism or Renaissance?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1944.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1944</id>
    <issued>2025-03-08</issued>
    <modified>2025-03-08</modified>
    <summary>Both Ted Gioia and Ross Barkan (among others) have observed cultural stirrings that indicate we might be moving away from rationalism, in ways similar to the sea change from Enlightenment to Romanticism around 1800. Count me intrigued....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
