<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2025-05-08</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>The Object of the Declaration</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1959.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1959</id>
    <issued>2025-05-08</issued>
    <modified>2025-05-08</modified>
    <summary>Exactly two hundred years ago today, Thomas Jefferson wrote a letter to one Henry Lee, who had inquired about the genesis of the Declaration of Independence. Here is what Jefferson had to say (original spelling retained):...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Michelle Marder Kamhi, RIP</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1958.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1958</id>
    <issued>2025-05-03</issued>
    <modified>2025-05-03</modified>
    <summary>I was saddened to learn the other day that my friend and mentor Michelle Marder Kamhi has passed away. Chris Sciabarra has written a more complete remembrance of our mutual friend, so I will add only a few personal notes....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Thinking Freely</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1957.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1957</id>
    <issued>2025-04-24</issued>
    <modified>2025-04-24</modified>
    <summary>While collectively we slouch towards tyranny, individually I continue to ponder some of the many methods people have proposed for counteracting that trend. Amidst all the particular suggestions, one thing I have not seen mentioned is adopting the attitude of a free person. This strikes me as seemingly simple but in fact both difficult and fundamental....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Slouching towards Monarchy</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1956.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1956</id>
    <issued>2025-04-24</issued>
    <modified>2025-04-24</modified>
    <summary>Legend has it that after the Constitutional Convention finished its work in September 1787, Elizabeth Willing Powel, one of the most powerful and highly educated women in Philadelphia, asked Benjamin Franklin whether we now had a monarchy or a republic. Great question, Elizabeth! We're still trying to figure out the answer....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Democracy in Decline</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1955.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1955</id>
    <issued>2025-04-22</issued>
    <modified>2025-04-22</modified>
    <summary>Because of the long-running inversion of political power in America from the local level to the national level, these days we hear all about the decline of democracy in Washington, D.C. but very little about the decline of local democracy. This got me to thinking about representation where I live in Douglas County, Colorado....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Romanticism Reconsidered</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1954.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1954</id>
    <issued>2025-04-18</issued>
    <modified>2025-04-18</modified>
    <summary>To follow up on last month's post "Romanticism or Renaissance?", I decided to read two books by scholars for whom I have a great deal of respect: Classic, Romantic, and Modern by cultural historian Jacques Barzun and The Roots of Romanticism by intellectual historian Isaiah Berlin. Although I'm far from sagely on these matters now, I do feel somewhat better informed....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
