<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2020-09-05</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #14: The Faults of Aristotle</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1650.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1650</id>
    <issued>2020-09-05</issued>
    <modified>2020-09-05</modified>
    <summary>Although I think Aristotle was the greatest mind who ever lived, he did have his faults. In modern times, he is especially criticized for supposedly being anti-science, anti-democracy, pro-slavery, and anti-women. Let us briefly consider these charges....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Compounding Wisdom</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1649.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1649</id>
    <issued>2020-08-28</issued>
    <modified>2020-08-28</modified>
    <summary>This weekend, in honor of Warren Buffett's 90th birthday, I'd like to consider the phenomenon of compounding. It's a little-known fact that Buffett earned almost 90% of his $82 billion fortune after the age of 65. Yet supposedly he has been fascinated by compounding since the age of 10, when he had an epiphany about how wealth could grow over time through the steady effects of return on investment....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Speaking Freely</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1648.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1648</id>
    <issued>2020-08-26</issued>
    <modified>2020-08-26</modified>
    <summary>Emerson was really onto something when he spoke about the high freedom of great conversation. I've been thinking about two more aspects of such freedom....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Fascinated with Conversation</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1647.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1647</id>
    <issued>2020-08-21</issued>
    <modified>2020-08-21</modified>
    <summary>Since posting about Emerson's thoughts on friendship and conversation a few weeks ago, I've continued to reflect on the actual practices involved (spurred by an email exchange with my friend Adrian Lory). Beyond just good listening, what can we do to cultivate the high freedom of conversation?...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophy and Money</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1646.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1646</id>
    <issued>2020-08-06</issued>
    <modified>2020-08-06</modified>
    <summary>Some great thinkers - Plato, Aristotle, Gautama Siddhartha, Epicurus, Thoreau, Rand, and many more - have reflected deeply on the place of money and wealth in human life. The reasons are not hard to find:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How Useful Is Philosophy, Really?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1645.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1645</id>
    <issued>2020-08-03</issued>
    <modified>2020-08-03</modified>
    <summary>It's a commonplace of research into human behavior that most of what you do is caused by your inborn personality traits, your underlying biology, the society and location and class and family into which you're born and in which you're raised, and so on - plus a smattering of luck and chance events. It can seem that all these causes conspire to leave little room for your ideals and aspirations and worldview and conscious choices to have much of an impact....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
