<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - philosopher, technologist, musician.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2026-02-03</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Elegy for Elisa</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2029.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2029</id>
    <issued>2026-02-03</issued>
    <modified>2026-02-03</modified>
    <summary>
Her sands have run; her thread has reached its end.
The woman whom I singled out to stride
With me through time, together at my side,
Is wife no more, nor life, nor soul, nor friend.
...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Flattery vs. Freedom</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2028.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2028</id>
    <issued>2026-01-26</issued>
    <modified>2026-01-26</modified>
    <summary>Related to my post "Aristotle on Freedom" last year, here is a timely quote from Book V of Aristotle's Politics on the free person's innate resistance to tyranny, founded in that illustrious but elusive character trait known as greatness of soul:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Back to the Future</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2027.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2027</id>
    <issued>2026-01-25</issued>
    <modified>2026-01-25</modified>
    <summary>About 110 years ago (in America we can conveniently date it from the 1913 Armory Show), the shock troops of aesthetic Modernism blew it all up. Disgusted with third-rate late Romantics, this self-proclaimed avant-garde decreed the destruction of meter in poetry, tonality in music, depiction in painting and sculpture, and in all the arts what they derided as the banality of beauty. Instead of seeking regeneration through artistic movements within the broad framework of what had been built up and bequeathed to them over thousands of years, they decided (for reasons I don't fully understand) that we needed to destroy everything first in order to create anew....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophy and Psychology Redux</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2026.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2026</id>
    <issued>2026-01-21</issued>
    <modified>2026-01-21</modified>
    <summary>Yesterday my friend Adrian Lory and I had an enjoyable and thought-provoking dialogue on Substack Live about philosophy and psychology as complementary paths to wisdom and fulfillment - so much so that we plan to have a follow-up chat in the coming weeks. Inspired by our conversation, here are some further questions I'm pondering about the interface between philosophy and psychology:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Writing Blank Verse</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2025.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2025</id>
    <issued>2026-01-13</issued>
    <modified>2026-01-13</modified>
    <summary>For my slowly-progressing epic poem about Pyrrho and Alexander the Great, I'm writing in blank verse, i.e., unrhymed iambic pentameter. Many of the great English-language poets have written in blank verse, including Shakespeare, Milton, Wordsworth, and Frost. Blank verse is especially appropriate, if you ask me, for epic poetry, since it's something like the equivalent in English of ancient Greek dactylic hexameter (another option is to employ fourteeners, as Matthew Arnold preferred for translations of Homer and as A.E. Stallings did in her amazing translation of Lucretius). Aside from its epic and dramatic pedigree, one of the attractions of blank verse is that it steers clear of the chimey sound and forced rhymes of heroic couplets, yet still maintains a regular pulse....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Discipline of Reading</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2024.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2024</id>
    <issued>2026-01-12</issued>
    <modified>2026-01-12</modified>
    <summary>A friend asked me yesterday how it is that I am so disciplined about reading. I perceive a few reasons....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
