<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2023-01-27</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>The Emergency Disaster Crisis</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1763.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1763</id>
    <issued>2023-01-27</issued>
    <modified>2023-01-27</modified>
    <summary>One reason I don't pay much attention to the news is that just about everything being reported on is an emergency, a disaster, a crisis! I like to run them all together and say that we're in the midst of an Emergency Disaster Crisis....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Circles of Friendship</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1762.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1762</id>
    <issued>2023-01-25</issued>
    <modified>2023-01-25</modified>
    <summary>As noted last week, Robin Dunbar, who has done amazing research into close personal relationships, is best known for "Dunbar's Number" - his finding that the typical friends network contains about 150 people (as discussed in a recent post by Arnold Kling). Yet as I also noted long ago in my blog post "Joining the Band", there are actually multiple Dunbar numbers, each roughly 3x more or less than the next one in the series....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Metaphysics in Verse II</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1761.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1761</id>
    <issued>2023-01-23</issued>
    <modified>2023-01-23</modified>
    <summary>Among the strangest conceptions of metaphysics is Aristotle's fanciful (or perhaps deadly serious) hypothesis of the Unmoved Mover. It's difficult to understand quite what he was getting at, and I'm not about to formulate a scholarly exegesis of the idea. But I did compose a little poem about it:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Seven Pillars of Friendship</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1760.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1760</id>
    <issued>2023-01-19</issued>
    <modified>2023-01-19</modified>
    <summary>Love, friendship, and other close personal relationships have been ill-served in the philosophical literature. Aside from Aristotle's foundational discussion and the occasional essay by the likes of Montaigne, Bacon, and Emerson, few philosophers have contributed deep insights to human relationships. This is disappointing, because as Aristotle observed 2400 years ago we are social creatures for whom close personal relationships are fundamental to our way of life....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Best Self vs. True Self</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1759.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1759</id>
    <issued>2023-01-12</issued>
    <modified>2023-01-12</modified>
    <summary>As previously mentioned, I am skeptical about the notion of the true self. Recently I've done some reading that has reinforced this skepticism. In particular, research by the likes of Roy Baumeister shows that human beings tend to identify with the activities and desires that they think are best (either individually or socially) and to disown the activities and desires that they think aren't so admirable....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Metaphysics in Verse</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1758.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1758</id>
    <issued>2023-01-12</issued>
    <modified>2023-01-12</modified>
    <summary>One of the things I do to avoid exposure to the news is immerse myself in poetry. Most recently I've been reading English and American poets from the 1500s and 1600s, such as Anne Bradstreet, Samuel Daniel, and Thomas Traherne. At the same time, I've started an intensive re-reading of Aristotelian texts and commentary in preparation for writing an epitome of Aristotle's views on human flourishing. Putting the two together can yield some intriguing combinations!...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
