<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2024-11-18</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Simplicity</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1921.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1921</id>
    <issued>2024-11-18</issued>
    <modified>2024-11-18</modified>
    <summary>Not long ago I ran across a wonderful quote from Frédéric Chopin:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics X.9</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1920.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1920</id>
    <issued>2024-11-11</issued>
    <modified>2024-11-11</modified>
    <summary>Here at the very end of the Nicomachean Ethics, after tens of thousands of words about human fulfillment, Aristotle somewhat wryly observes that words are powerless to encourage most people to understand and enact what is good and beautifully right, for they live by their feelings and respond more readily to correction and punishment than to wisdom and insight....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics X.6-8</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1919.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1919</id>
    <issued>2024-11-09</issued>
    <modified>2024-11-09</modified>
    <summary>In these rather dense chapters, the last of the Nicomachean Ethics except for X.9, Aristotle returns to the topic of human fulfillment [εὐδαιμονία / eudaimonia], drawing several conclusions that sound surprising to modern ears:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics X.1-5</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1918.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1918</id>
    <issued>2024-11-07</issued>
    <modified>2024-11-07</modified>
    <summary>In X.1-5 Aristotle revisits the topic of pleasure, reiterating some of the points he made in VII.11-14 (e.g., that every activity has its own inherent pleasure) but also extending them in several ways....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics IX.9-12</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1917.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1917</id>
    <issued>2024-11-03</issued>
    <modified>2024-11-03</modified>
    <summary>In IX.9-12, Aristotle finishes off his consideration of love and friendship by wondering how many close relationships one really needs, the times in life when such relationships are most valuable, etc....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics IX.8</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1916.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1916</id>
    <issued>2024-10-29</issued>
    <modified>2024-10-29</modified>
    <summary>Up until now Aristotle has considered love for other people, but in IX.8 Aristotle asks some probing questions about love of self. All the central qualities of love (summarized in my post about IX.4-7) seem to apply most of all to oneself, such that love toward others seems to grow out of self-love. But how can this be? After all, it also seems that the unserious/unworthy [phaulos] person whose character is corrupted [mochthēros] acts out of pure selfishness. The conflict between these appearances sets up what Aristotle calls an impasse [aporia], and we'll need to find a way through it in order to make further progress toward wisdom and sagacity....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
