<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2024-04-13</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Tao Te Ching ยง44: Ageless Life</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1858.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1858</id>
    <issued>2024-04-13</issued>
    <modified>2024-04-13</modified>
    <summary>I continue to ponder various poems from the Tao Te Ching with an eye toward perhaps setting them to music. Here is my provisional rendering of chapter 44:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Modernizing Aristotle's Ethics: A Review</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1857.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1857</id>
    <issued>2024-04-01</issued>
    <modified>2024-04-01</modified>
    <summary>This is just a brief note that folks interested in Aristotle, Ayn Rand, the psychology of happiness, or any combination thereof might enjoy my review of Roger E. Bissell and Vinay Kolhatkar's new book Modernizing Aristotle's Ethics: Toward a New Art and Science of Self-Actualization, just published in Issue 44, No. 1 of the interdisciplinary journal Reason Papers. Check it out!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics I.6</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1856.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1856</id>
    <issued>2024-03-29</issued>
    <modified>2024-03-29</modified>
    <summary>After the preliminaries in Nicomachean Ethics I.1-5, Aristotle considers a rather abstract question: is there some universal good or "Form of the Good" that is common to all good things? Aristotle's friends in Plato's Academy thought so, but in pursuit of truth Aristotle finds that he must disagree, for several reasons....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics I.1-5</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1855.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1855</id>
    <issued>2024-03-27</issued>
    <modified>2024-03-27</modified>
    <summary>Here in the late stages of preparation for writing my book Complete Yourself: Aristotle on Human Fulfillment, I've started a close re-reading of Aristotle's Nicomachean Ethics (to be followed by a similar reading of his Eudemian Ethics). Because it might prove useful both to myself and to others, I'll post notes on my readings as I go along, in a new series entitled "Walking with Aristotle"....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Nietzsche's Teachings</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1854.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1854</id>
    <issued>2024-03-26</issued>
    <modified>2024-03-26</modified>
    <summary>The other day a friend of mine asked me for my overall assessment of Friedrich Nietzsche. At first I jokingly replied that each of the seventy-two poems in my book Songs of Zarathustra might present a unique perspective, whereas all together they might not yield a unitary view. Then I decided to re-read the book, which led me to identify six main themes in what I take to be Nietzsche's positive philosophy of life:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Work as a Gift</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1853.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1853</id>
    <issued>2024-03-11</issued>
    <modified>2024-03-11</modified>
    <summary>While reading British anthropologist Alan Macfarlane's fascinating book Japan through the Looking Glass recently, I was introduced to a conception of economic interaction almost entirely different from that in the West:...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
