<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2023-08-17</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Self-Government</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1811.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1811</id>
    <issued>2023-08-17</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-17</modified>
    <summary>As noted the other day in my post on the death of democracy, Thomas Jefferson held that the townships of New England were "the wisest invention ever devised by the wit of man for the perfect exercise of self-government." If indeed they are an ideal, it would benefit us to understand what they are and how they work. Toward that end, I'll introduce a somewhat extraordinary example: Monhegan Island, Maine....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Act Locally</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1810.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1810</id>
    <issued>2023-08-16</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-16</modified>
    <summary>Because my last post about the supposed death of democracy was rather theoretical, I figured I'd follow it up with something more practical....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Death of Democracy?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1809.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1809</id>
    <issued>2023-08-13</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-13</modified>
    <summary>Is democracy in peril? Apparently many pundits think so. Yet 'democracy' is notoriously difficult to define. Although I strive to stay away from political topics in this journal, perhaps by applying some philosophical elbow grease we can lessen our worries about yet another emergency disaster crisis....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Daily Reflection</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1808.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1808</id>
    <issued>2023-08-09</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-09</modified>
    <summary>As a counterpart to my morning practice of daily forethought, I've also been engaging in daily reflection every evening. This habit was made famous by the ancient Stoic Seneca in Book III of his dialogue On Anger, where he mentions that his teacher Sextius asked himself these three probing questions before going to sleep: "What bad habit of yours have you cured today? What vice have you checked? In what respect are you better?" Some of my questions are more positive, but still geared toward living a more examined life:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Daily Forethought</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1807.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1807</id>
    <issued>2023-08-07</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-07</modified>
    <summary>In pursuit of a more examined life, I've been honing my daily habits. Taking a hint from the ancient Stoics, first thing in the morning I've been thinking about the day ahead and then at the end of the day I've been reflecting on how the day went. Here's a snapshot of what this looks like for me (I'll split this up into two posts, one prospective and one retrospective)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tao Te Ching ยง11: Emptiness</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1806.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1806</id>
    <issued>2023-08-03</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-03</modified>
    <summary>Following up on yesterday's post about the Tao Te Ching, here's another poem that I might set to music (chapter 11 in the standard order). My provisional rendering is as follows:...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
