<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2025-08-24</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Sunlight and Shadow</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1984.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1984</id>
    <issued>2025-08-24</issued>
    <modified>2025-08-24</modified>
    <summary>Overnight I realized that my post yesterday about Walter Kaufmann's account of love as a virtue could give the impression that my view of life is rather dark. Whereas it seems that Kaufmann had something of a tragic sense of life, my outlook is decidedly sunnier. Since I was quite young, I've wondered at the cosmic improbability of being alive. Several months ago I put it this way to a friend:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What Is This Thing Called Love?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1983.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1983</id>
    <issued>2025-08-16</issued>
    <modified>2025-08-16</modified>
    <summary>The German-born American philosopher Walter Kaufmann, best known for his translations (and postwar rehabilitation) of Nietzsche, also produced original philosophical works of great worth, as well as a fine collection of poems of which I'm quite fond. In his 1961 book The Faith of a Heretic, among other things Kaufmann attempted to sketch out a personal ethic appropriate for contemporary human beings. Although his accounts of virtues like courage and intellectual honesty span only a few pages each, they are dense with meaning. Here I'll try to summarize his perspective on what Cole Porter famously named "this thing called love"....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>AI and I</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1982.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1982</id>
    <issued>2025-08-21</issued>
    <modified>2025-08-21</modified>
    <summary>With all the Sturm und Drang about so-called artificial intelligence right now, I'd like to make it clear that I don't use these technologies. For me, the primary consideration is not that AI will, on balance, degrade humanity's already weakened ability to engage in independent thinking and humane interaction (although I think evidence is mounting that this will be the case). No, I simply find these technologies uninteresting....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Imitation and Individuality</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1981.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1981</id>
    <issued>2025-08-20</issued>
    <modified>2025-08-20</modified>
    <summary>These propositions, quoted in Albert Murray's book The Blue Devils of Nada, "preclude imitation in favor of individuality", as Murray observes. Here I'm especially interested in Hemingway's statement that schools of art serve to classify their members as failures. What exactly does that mean?...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Thinking Historically</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1980.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1980</id>
    <issued>2025-08-16</issued>
    <modified>2025-08-16</modified>
    <summary>Over the last few months I've read three books by my favorite historian, David Hackett Fischer: Historians' Fallacies: Toward a Logic of Historical Thought (1970), Albion's Seed: Four British Folkways in America (my third reading of this book, published in 1989), and African Founders: How Enslaved People Expanded American Ideals (2022)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Words, Words, Words</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1979.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1979</id>
    <issued>2025-08-15</issued>
    <modified>2025-08-15</modified>
    <summary>Here's something I'm struggling with: if talk is cheap and values are overrated, what's the worth of writing?...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
