<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2022-01-01</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Cultivating Empathy</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1690.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1690</id>
    <issued>2022-01-01</issued>
    <modified>2022-01-01</modified>
    <summary>If you ask those I work with or mentor what my distinctive personal qualities are, I suspect that on the short list you might find empathy. For instance, I often reach out to work colleagues if I know that they face significant challenges, if their skills aren't being fully utilized, if they're not appreciated as much as they should be, if someone on their team has resigned, or on the positive side if they've been doing great work....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Monadnock Valley Press Annual Report 2021</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1689.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1689</id>
    <issued>2022-01-01</issued>
    <modified>2022-01-01</modified>
    <summary>Happy Public Domain Day!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Questions and Answers</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1688.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1688</id>
    <issued>2021-12-29</issued>
    <modified>2021-12-29</modified>
    <summary>Consider the following statements... "There are no answers, only questions." "Life is all about the journey, not the destination." "A teacher or a counselor should encourage dialogue, not provide direction." All true as far as they go. And yet....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2021 Readings</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1687.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1687</id>
    <issued>2021-12-29</issued>
    <modified>2021-12-29</modified>
    <summary>As best I can reconstruct it, here are the books I read in 2021. Not included are scholarly papers, essays, and other short works. I've provided links to books that are available online at my monadnock.net website for works in the public domain....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weekly Wisdom</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1686.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1686</id>
    <issued>2021-12-27</issued>
    <modified>2021-12-27</modified>
    <summary>Although I don't make New Year's resolutions, at this time of year I do tend to reconsider some of my goals and practices. One thing I'd like to improve on is the frequency of entries in my online journal, because writing them pushes me to think about how I'm living and what I'm learning. Thus going forward I'll strive to post such reflections at least once a week - most likely on Friday evenings or over the weekend, when it's easier to find time for reflection. You can receive these missives in your inbox by visiting my philosopher.coach website and typing your email address in the subscription form at the bottom of the page....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Meditations on Bach #9: Musical Monadology</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1685.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1685</id>
    <issued>2021-12-26</issued>
    <modified>2021-12-26</modified>
    <summary>In meditation #7 of this series, I took note of some similarities between the aesthetics of Aristotle and the music of Bach. Another intriguing influence might be the monadology of Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz (1646-1716), who directly influenced philosophers and musical theorists in the Bach's orbit: for instance, Bach's student Lorenz Mizler (1711-1778) was a follower of the Leibniz scholar Christian Wolff (1679-1754). In chapter 5 of his book Music in the Culture of the Renassiance and Other Essays, Edward Lowinsky makes the following observations:...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
