<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2023-08-22</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Attuning to Beauty</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1817.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1817</id>
    <issued>2023-08-22</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-22</modified>
    <summary>When describing recently my practice of daily forethought, I mentioned that every day I try to attune myself to the beauty of the world around me. This might sound pompouse and grandiose because often we associate beauty only with the fine arts, but for me it's much more practical and prosaic. Here are some of the activities I engage in toward this end:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Snares and Attachments</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1816.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1816</id>
    <issued>2023-08-23</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-23</modified>
    <summary>Having posted enough semi-political entries of late to last me quite a while, it's time to return to reflections on living....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Tao of Freedom</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1815.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1815</id>
    <issued>2023-08-23</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-23</modified>
    <summary>Many defenses of a free society are based on assumptions of certainty regarding human nature; for instance, human beings are so constituted that they must have maximal autonomy in order to discover scientific truths or invent and produce the goods and services that improve human life....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Wisdom vs. Ideology</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1814.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1814</id>
    <issued>2023-08-22</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-22</modified>
    <summary>Following up on my post about Washington's wisdom, I've been thinking about the contrast between wisdom and ideology as a basis for making decisions....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Washington's Wisdom</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1813.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1813</id>
    <issued>2023-08-18</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-18</modified>
    <summary>Recently I carved out time to read Ron Chernow's 800-page biography of George Washington. We tend to have only vague notions about Washington, but Chernow's biography truly brings him to life. Far from being the wooden, mythical figure we imagine, Washington was a man of great passions and strong emotions, which he worked hard to direct into productive channels throughout his long career in private life and public service....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Political Animals</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1812.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1812</id>
    <issued>2023-08-18</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-18</modified>
    <summary>One of Aristotle's most famous observations is that human beings are "political animals"; yet the meaning of this phrase is not widely understood or appreciated. Let's take a closer look....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
