<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2020-01-14</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Zamyatin's WE</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1637.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1637</id>
    <issued>2020-01-14</issued>
    <modified>2020-01-14</modified>
    <summary>In 1921, Yevgeny Zamyatin finished writing WE, the Ur-text for most dystopian novels since then (Anthem, 1984, Brave New World, etc.). In 1924, Zamyatin's novel, not yet (in fact never) published in the Soviet Union, was first brought to the world by E.P. Dutton and Company of New York in an English translation by Gregory Zilboorg. Because 95 years have passed since then, Dr. Zilboorg's translation is finally in the public domain - and I have just republished it online at my website for public-domain books, the Monadnock Valley Press....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Jo Walton's Thessaly Trilogy</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1636.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1636</id>
    <issued>2020-01-01</issued>
    <modified>2020-01-01</modified>
    <summary>Fresh from a re-reading of Plato's dialogues, recently I dove into Jo Walton's Thessaly trilogy (The Just City, The Philosopher Kings, and Necessity), a speculative epic set in a society consistent with Plato's Republic. It's an enjoyable, thought-provoking blend of science fiction, ancient Greek myth, and Platonic philosophy. Although I recommended Walton's trilogy if you like philosophical novels, I do take issue with several aspects of her story....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2019 Readings</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1635.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1635</id>
    <issued>2019-12-31</issued>
    <modified>2019-12-31</modified>
    <summary>Here are the ~110 books I had a chance to read in 2019, divided into a few categories. Most of these are related to my project of writing an epitome of Aristotle's ethics (and most of the rest are related to my project of writing a novel about Pyrrho, the founder of ancient Greek skepticism)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #13: Phase One Complete</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1634.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1634</id>
    <issued>2019-12-26</issued>
    <modified>2019-12-26</modified>
    <summary>Yesterday I finished phase one of my research into Aristotle's ethics, in preparation for writing Complete Yourself: Aristotle on Personal Excellence. As I described in a blog post over five years ago, for me the process of "working through" a thinker initially involves absorbing all of his or her writings, supplemented by some of the secondary literature. Since I started this project about two years ago, I've read everything by Aristotle and Plato, as well as numerous scholarly books on Aristotle, totalling around 120 distinct works. To give you a sense of the magnitude, here's a photo of the relevant books in my own collection (not counting all the ones I've checked out of libraries throughout Colorado and Wyoming, thanks to the wonders of Prospector, our regional inter-library loan system):...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #12: A Eudemian Thread</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1633.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1633</id>
    <issued>2019-12-08</issued>
    <modified>2019-12-08</modified>
    <summary>At the very end of Aristotle's Eudemian Ethics there is a puzzling passage about the standard (ὅρος) according to which the "good and beautifully right" person (καλοκαγαθός) makes choices with regard to natural goods such as wealth, health, strength, honor, power, good fortune, and personal relationships. Surprisingly, he says that whatever conduces to the cultivation (θεραπεία) and awareness (θεωρία) of god is best and is the most beautifully right standard, whereas anything that hinders such cultivation and awareness is unworthy, trifling, and bad (φαῦλος - the opposite of what is σπουδαῖος, i.e. worthy, serious, and good). Until these last few paragraphs, nothing in the Eudemian Ethics had obviously pointed in this startlingly "theological" direction or had advocated a godlike, superhuman existence; yet if we pay careful attention to the text, we can patiently unravel a thread of inquiry that elucidates Aristotle's last word on the topic of the best human life....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Cooperative Thinking</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1632.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1632</id>
    <issued>2019-08-16</issued>
    <modified>2019-08-16</modified>
    <summary>A few years ago I did a bunch of research and thinking about alternative forms of organizational structure, focused especially on cooperatives (at the time I was thinking about setting up a co-op to run the Jabber.org messaging service). The approach I found most interesting was funding a co-op through something called a direct public offering. This can be done for much less money and with much greater control than VC funding or angel investing or whatever - it's basically a kind of more advanced crowdfunding. Companies that have done this include My Trail (an outdoor clothing company in Boulder, Colorado), Real Pickles (a food co-op in Massachusetts), and Equal Exchange (the original fair trade coffee company, also located in Massachusetts). Other co-ops I investigated are self-funded and haven't pursued the DPO route (e.g., Namasté Solar, Plausible Labs, and Isthmus Engineering)...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
