<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2022-03-28</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>The Meanings of Meaning</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1707.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1707</id>
    <issued>2022-03-28</issued>
    <modified>2022-03-28</modified>
    <summary>If you tell people that you're interested in philosophy, inevitably someone will ask you about the meaning of life. Although the question might predate The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy, ancient philosophers in the Greek, Indian, and Chinese traditions didn't raise it. Personally I adhere to the aphorism that it's best not to puzzle over the meaning of life, but instead work to create a life of meaning....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Rules of Friendship</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1706.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1706</id>
    <issued>2022-03-22</issued>
    <modified>2022-03-22</modified>
    <summary>While doing some research recently on relationships, I came across an old but classic scholarly paper entitled "The Rules of Friendship" by Michael Argyle and Monika Henderson (Journal of Social and Personal Relationships, Vol. 1 (1984), pp. 211-237). Using populations from Britain, Italy, Hong Kong, and Japan, the authors studied several related topics:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Self as an Achievement</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1705.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1705</id>
    <issued>2022-03-16</issued>
    <modified>2022-03-16</modified>
    <summary>What is the self? Naturally this question invokes vast reflections spanning philosophy, psychology, cognitive science, sociology, biology, and many other fields. Although I claim no special insight, in my Aristotle readings over the last few years I chanced upon a fascinating perspective that I thought I'd share....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How Much Is Enough?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1704.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1704</id>
    <issued>2022-03-06</issued>
    <modified>2022-03-06</modified>
    <summary>As mentioned in my post "Delphic Wisdom and Modern Science", on the walls of the ancient Greek temple at Delphi could be found the inscription μηδὲν ἄγαν, meaning "nothing too much". Yet how can one know how much is enough? Naturally it's hard to say precisely - after all, if it were easy, life wouldn't be so messy and complicated, now would it?...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Read the Eternities</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1703.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1703</id>
    <issued>2022-02-27</issued>
    <modified>2022-02-27</modified>
    <summary>One of my favorite Thoreau aphorisms goes like this: "Read not the Times; read the Eternities." Yet in times of turmoil - war, revolution, depression, pandemic, and the like - it can be difficult to focus on the timeless questions of how to live well because merely living take precedence. On the other hand, there's invariably something bad happening somewhere, and it's difficult to draw the line between what requires urgent attention and what is an ephemeral distraction or news-industry sensation....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A New Focus</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1702.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1702</id>
    <issued>2022-02-17</issued>
    <modified>2022-02-17</modified>
    <summary>After 25 years in the tech industry, I've decided it's time for a new focus in life. Last Friday was my last day at Mozilla, and my wife Elisa and I are already hard at work on a non-tech venture: a training program that we hope will help people develop professionally by applying the insights of psychological research and the great wisdom traditions to the challenges and opportunities of work and career....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
