<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2022-02-17</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>A New Focus</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1702.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1702</id>
    <issued>2022-02-17</issued>
    <modified>2022-02-17</modified>
    <summary>After 25 years in the tech industry, I've decided it's time for a new focus in life. Last Friday was my last day at Mozilla, and my wife Elisa and I are already hard at work on a non-tech venture: a training program that we hope will help people develop professionally by applying the insights of psychological research and the great wisdom traditions to the challenges and opportunities of work and career....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Opinions, Expectations, and Emotions</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1701.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1701</id>
    <issued>2022-02-15</issued>
    <modified>2022-02-15</modified>
    <summary>Following up on my series of posts about the phenomenon of opinion, I've been pondering the relationship between opinions, expectations, and emotions....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Meditations on Bach #10: Philosophy in Music</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1700.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1700</id>
    <issued>2022-02-10</issued>
    <modified>2022-02-10</modified>
    <summary>In the second edition of his extremely intriguing book Bach: The Fencing Master, cellist Anner Bylsma writes as follows:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Jealousy and Envy</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1699.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1699</id>
    <issued>2022-02-10</issued>
    <modified>2022-02-10</modified>
    <summary>A friend recently asked me how I would characterize the difference between jealousy and envy. Here's how I see it: jealousy is when I want to gain something you have, and envy is when I want you to lose something you have. If I'm jealous of your new Tesla, I want a Tesla too. If I'm envious of the superyacht that Jeff Bezos is building, I don't want him to have that yacht even if I'll never be able to have such a thing....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Delphic Wisdom and Modern Science</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1698.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1698</id>
    <issued>2022-02-04</issued>
    <modified>2022-02-04</modified>
    <summary>Carved into the walls of the ancient Greek temple at Delphi were two proverbs: γνῶθι σεαυτόν ("know thyself") and μηδὲν ἄγαν ("nothing too much"). Plato mentions them in his dialogue Protagoras, set around 434 BCE, but most likely they were common among the Greeks as far back as 600 BCE or even earlier. Although they are so very old, recently I've been pondering their connection to the latest research in the modern science of psychology....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophical Professionalism</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1697.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1697</id>
    <issued>2022-02-01</issued>
    <modified>2022-02-01</modified>
    <summary>Robin Hanson recently suggested that we need more generalist thinkers, and that they can be found among the ranks of polymaths, public intellectuals, and professional philosophers. Although I might post again on the topic of generalists vs. specialists, today I'd like to focus instead on the concept of philosophical professionalism....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
