<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2023-12-13</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>More on Ancient Friends</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1838.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1838</id>
    <issued>2023-12-13</issued>
    <modified>2023-12-13</modified>
    <summary>Less than two nights after quoting Niccolò Machiavelli's reflections on his ancient friends, I came upon a similar passage in the Essays in Idleness (Tsurezuregusa), written by the Japanese poet-monk Yoshida Kenkō around the year 1330. Here's what Kenkō had to say, in the translation by Donald Keene:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Planning to Be Old</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1837.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1837</id>
    <issued>2023-12-12</issued>
    <modified>2023-12-12</modified>
    <summary>Earlier this year at a family gathering, I overheard an uncle of mine (who is in his late 80s) say something in passing to one of his siblings about the importance of planning to be old. This set me to thinking: what might such planning involve? Here are some possible considerations:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ancient Friends</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1836.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1836</id>
    <issued>2023-12-10</issued>
    <modified>2023-12-10</modified>
    <summary>On this day 510 years ago (December 10th, 1513), Niccolò Machiavelli wrote a now-famous letter to his friend Francesco Vettori about his life in exile from Florence - and about a little book he was writing, which has come down to us as The Prince. After relating what had happened that day on his farm and in the village, he described his evening routine, when he would "visit" with Plutarch, Polybius, Livy, Aristotle, and other great minds of antiquity:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Reality is Messy</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1835.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1835</id>
    <issued>2023-12-09</issued>
    <modified>2023-12-09</modified>
    <summary>The usually reasonable Arnold Kling, one of my favorite bloggers going back 25 years, has been using ChatGPT to build an essay-grading app and might have taken one too many sips of the Kool-Aid. Consider:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>An Aristotelian Glossary</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1834.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1834</id>
    <issued>2023-12-06</issued>
    <modified>2023-12-06</modified>
    <summary>Of late I've been working on the first serious contribution to my forthcoming book about Aristotle's conception of human fulfillment: a glossary of key terms. Those curious enough to peruse it will quickly discover that some of my renderings are rather non-standard. In my defense, usually these translations are rooted in ancient Greek etymology and usage or modern academic scholarship (e.g., both Aryeh Kosman and Myles Burnyeat recommended "understanding" instead of "knowledge" for epistēmē, as noted in my recent post "Understanding What You Know"); however, in a few instances I go farther out on a limb (e.g., "thriving" instead of "virtue" for aretē and, most centrally of all, "fulfillment" instead of "happiness" for eudaimonia). Although all of these renderings are subject to change, I'm quite satisfied with them so far (having pondered them for years) and in fact they provide a good indication of the interpretive direction I'm taking....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Understanding What You Know</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1833.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1833</id>
    <issued>2023-11-29</issued>
    <modified>2023-11-29</modified>
    <summary>Recently I discovered two ancient philosophy papers from the 1970s (by Aryeh Kosman and Myles Burnyeat) drawing a distinction between knowledge and understanding. As far as I can tell, Kosman was the first to propose that the Greek word epistēmē is best translated as understanding, and that in fact it means understanding how to explain what you know, in other words understanding why the thing you know is the way it is....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
