<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2025-12-15</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophy and Psychology</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2013.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2013</id>
    <issued>2025-12-15</issued>
    <modified>2025-12-15</modified>
    <summary>Sometime in the next few weeks my friend Adrian Lory and I will hold a Substack Live video conversation about philosophy and psychology as complementary paths to wisdom and fulfillment. In preparation, I've been thinking up some questions about the relationship between philosophy and psychology, as well as their respective contributions to the good life. Here's what I have so far:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Change and Revolution</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2012.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2012</id>
    <issued>2025-12-14</issued>
    <modified>2025-12-14</modified>
    <summary>In his book First Things, Last Things, Eric Hoffer makes some observations about change and revolution:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Universalist Temptation</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2011.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2011</id>
    <issued>2025-12-10</issued>
    <modified>2025-12-10</modified>
    <summary>The other day in my post about Making It Personal, I wrote as follows:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Making It Personal</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2010.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2010</id>
    <issued>2025-12-08</issued>
    <modified>2025-12-08</modified>
    <summary>My increasingly strong commitment to personalism and particularism has prompted me to make some changes in how I read, think, and act. Specifically, I have taken to translating universal claims and observations into practices that I can apply in my own life (and ignoring them if they cannot be so translated)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Varieties of Beauty</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2009.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2009</id>
    <issued>2025-12-03</issued>
    <modified>2025-12-03</modified>
    <summary>Beauty is not limited to the arts (indeed, art is not always beautiful, but that's another topic). This set me to thinking about the many sorts of things that we humans can call beautiful:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Shakespeare and Santayana on Beauty and Truth</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/2008.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,2008</id>
    <issued>2025-11-30</issued>
    <modified>2025-11-30</modified>
    <summary>Once more unto the breach with Santayana! (Three posts in a day on this topic were not what I expected.) Before saying goodbye to him, at least for now, I thought it would be fun to look at his use - or abuse - of Shakespeare at a crucial point in The Sense of Beauty. As Santayana leads up to this definition of beauty, he quotes Sonnet 54, which runs as follows:...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
