<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2022-08-04</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Controversies</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1728.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1728</id>
    <issued>2022-08-04</issued>
    <modified>2022-08-04</modified>
    <summary>While reading the autobiography of Charles Darwin a few weeks ago, I came across the following passage:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Mental Junk Food</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1727.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1727</id>
    <issued>2022-08-01</issued>
    <modified>2022-08-01</modified>
    <summary>These days every article, video, podcast, or tweet needs to scream for your attention. Even worse, much of what you're shown online is determined by algorithms that put a premium on popularity, which is itself driven by the all-too-human feelings of greed for sensation and fear of disaster. In this brave new world of ours, news is literally a form of mental junk food....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Constraints</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1726.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1726</id>
    <issued>2022-07-28</issued>
    <modified>2022-07-28</modified>
    <summary>Recently I read two interesting quotes about the presence of constraints in life. The first was in a book of interviews on poetic structure entitled Fourteen on Form, in which one of the poets observed that students of his accustomed to writing free verse often didn't like writing in meter or rhyme because they couldn't say exactly what they wanted to say. The second was in an interview with the late, great jazz pianist and composer Lyle Mays, who said that you need to face some restrictions in order to stimulate creativity and have interesting problems to solve (you can hear the results in his final work, entitled Eberhard)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Both Sides, Now</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1725.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1725</id>
    <issued>2022-07-21</issued>
    <modified>2022-07-21</modified>
    <summary>You hear it all the time: "this is a topic that both sides can agree on" ... "both sides are to blame for this mess" ... "she is one of those rare people who appeals to both sides" ... and so on....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Have a Beautiful Life</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1724.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1724</id>
    <issued>2022-07-14</issued>
    <modified>2022-07-14</modified>
    <summary>Last week I explored how we might apply Aristotle's ideas about ethical beauty to the "micro level" of specific virtues and particular situations. This week I'd like to see how we might apply the same basic insights to the "macro level" of living a beautiful life....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Beautifully Right</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1723.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1723</id>
    <issued>2022-07-07</issued>
    <modified>2022-07-07</modified>
    <summary>I seem to have fallen into a natural rhythm of alternating my posts between lighter and heavier topics; last week I talked about substitutions, so this week I figured I'd delve into something I touched on last year: what Aristotle means by acting for the sake of what is beautifully right....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
