<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2018-11-17</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Investing in Life</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1616.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1616</id>
    <issued>2018-11-17</issued>
    <modified>2018-11-17</modified>
    <summary>Recently I got to talking with my friend Dave Jilk about happiness, flourishing, and my future book The Art of Living. While relating my ideas about the goals of life (as captured in a recent blog post), I described the importance of taking a balanced approach and including all or most of these goals in one's life pursuits. He likened this to portfolio management in investing, which is a great analogy. This spurred me to thinking further about the value that each area of life brings to one's overall success in life. Consider a few somewhat fanciful extensions of this analogy:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Impasses</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1615.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1615</id>
    <issued>2018-10-30</issued>
    <modified>2018-10-30</modified>
    <summary>Impasses along the path toward the goals of life can occur in three dimensions:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Goals of Life</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1614.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1614</id>
    <issued>2018-10-30</issued>
    <modified>2018-10-30</modified>
    <summary>There are many ways to categorize and divide up the various areas and activities of life. Here is a six-fold scheme I'm exploring:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Understanding Others</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1613.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1613</id>
    <issued>2018-10-26</issued>
    <modified>2018-10-26</modified>
    <summary>In my recent philosophy talk, I mentioned that thinking philosophically has helped me better understand people. This might seem counterintuitive - after all, don't big thinkers believe they have all the answers? Yes, I used to have that kind of arrogance, too. Yet over time I started to wonder: why do people have so many different opinions about things? Why have these various philosophies of life persisted for so long (Stoicism, Platonism, Buddhism, Taoism, etc.)? Why do I think what I think? Is it really in my control? At some level can you really "blame" people for the contents of their minds?...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophy Video</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1612.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1612</id>
    <issued>2018-10-19</issued>
    <modified>2018-10-19</modified>
    <summary>Video of my talk on philosophy as a foundation for success is now available, in two parts: the talk itself and the question-and-answer session. Thanks to Prof. Mitzi Lee for making the recording and posting it to YouTube!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #5: Three Forms of the Good</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1611.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1611</id>
    <issued>2018-10-12</issued>
    <modified>2018-10-12</modified>
    <summary>In Book Two, Chapter Three of the Nicomachean Ethics, Aristotle distinguishes three forms of the good: what is pleasurable or enjoyable (τό ἡδύ), what is useful or advantageous (τό συμφέρων), and what is right or beautiful (τό καλόν). In other places in his writings on both ethics and biology, he distinguishes three forms of reaching or desire (ὄρεξις): craving or appetite (ἐπιθυμία), feeling or passion (θυμός), and decision or will (βούλησις). Various interpreters (such as John Cooper in his book Reason and Emotion) have attempted to align these two sets of three, whereas other interpreters (such as Giles Pearson in his book Aristotle on Desire) have criticized such attempts as forced, misguided, and not supported by the textual evidence. Although I tend to agree with the integrators because I believe Aristotle was a fairly systematic thinker, I think Cooper's connection of θυμός with τό καλόν isn't right. Instead, it seems to me that craving or appetite is for the pleasant or enjoyable, feeling or passion is for the useful or advantageous, and decision or will is for what's right or beautiful....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
