<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2024-11-30</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Seeing Like an Ideology</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1925.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1925</id>
    <issued>2024-11-30</issued>
    <modified>2024-11-30</modified>
    <summary>In his classic book Seeing Like a State, James C. Scott describes numerous schemes by which what he calls "high-modernist" planners attempted to impose order on the perceived chaos of human societies: collectivized farms in Soviet Russia, compulsory villagization in parts of Africa, unworkable cities like Brasília, etc. All of these schemes to overcome the messy realities of human existence have been able to survive their own manifest failings only because of creative workarounds discovered through human inventiveness and practical know-how (which, borrowing an ancient Greek word that Homer used to describe the wily Odysseus, he calls mētis / μῆτις)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Taking Notes</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1924.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1924</id>
    <issued>2024-11-26</issued>
    <modified>2024-11-26</modified>
    <summary>Since I seem to be on a roll writing about habits, I figured I'd mention another one: taking notes during meetings....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Good Distractions</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1923.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1923</id>
    <issued>2024-11-25</issued>
    <modified>2024-11-25</modified>
    <summary>While talking with a friend today, I described my concept of the "to don't list" as well as a few of my personal best practices related to smartphone usage. In the midst of our conversation, it occurred to me that there's such a thing as a good distraction. It's difficult for even the most disciplined person to stay focused all the time on long-term projects and personal productivity. We all need a mental break! Yet, speaking from experience, all too often I'm wont to pull out my smartphone or computer and check the headlines, even though I've been on a low-information diet for 10-15 years and intellectually I know the news isn't helpful for my state of mind. At least for me, this a bad distraction!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Powerless</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1922.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1922</id>
    <issued>2024-11-24</issued>
    <modified>2024-11-24</modified>
    <summary>Several friends I've talked with recently have expressed despair over the results of the recent U.S. elections, disbelief over Donald Trump's picks for cabinet roles, even a desire to move to Canada or Europe - plus a kind of wonder that I'm able to maintain my equanimity in what they see as a dire situation. In case it might prove helpful to other folks, I'll try to describe my mindset....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Simplicity</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1921.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1921</id>
    <issued>2024-11-18</issued>
    <modified>2024-11-18</modified>
    <summary>Not long ago I ran across a wonderful quote from Frédéric Chopin:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics X.9</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1920.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1920</id>
    <issued>2024-11-11</issued>
    <modified>2024-11-11</modified>
    <summary>Here at the very end of the Nicomachean Ethics, after tens of thousands of words about human fulfillment, Aristotle somewhat wryly observes that words are powerless to encourage most people to understand and enact what is good and beautifully right, for they live by their feelings and respond more readily to correction and punishment than to wisdom and insight....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
