<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2023-04-06</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophy and Grief</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1775.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1775</id>
    <issued>2023-04-06</issued>
    <modified>2023-04-06</modified>
    <summary>Grieving is one of the characteristic activities of human beings. Although it seems that some other species (e.g., members of the corvid family) experience sorrow, grief is a more complex phenomenon. Recently I read a fine book on the topic by Michael Cholbi, entitled Grief: A Philosophical Guide. Here are the essentials of what I gleaned....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Battle of the Bricks</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1774.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1774</id>
    <issued>2023-03-30</issued>
    <modified>2023-03-30</modified>
    <summary>Last year I decided to read War and Peace for the first time. Although Tolstoy's powers of psychological observation are amazing, I got stuck about halfway through (during a lengthy description of a fox hunt), and since then I haven't really been able to get back into it. It didn't help that none of the characters appealed to me strongly, perhaps because so many of them exhibit high levels of pretentiousness or self-deception - or both! Yes, 635 pages is a large investment of time, but getting from there to page 1386 feels like a tough slog and I'm not sure I have the energy....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Intellectual Jousting</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1773.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1773</id>
    <issued>2023-03-17</issued>
    <modified>2023-03-17</modified>
    <summary>In my recent post on intelligence vs. wisdom, I used the phrase "intellectual jousting" to describe the modern practice of doing philosophy. Here's a bit of psychological speculation about how that activity comes to be valued....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Intelligence vs. Wisdom</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1772.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1772</id>
    <issued>2023-03-17</issued>
    <modified>2023-03-17</modified>
    <summary>Ever since I left behind the high arrogance of my teenage years, I have valued wisdom over intelligence. This is likely why I'm much more drawn to the ancient conception of philosophy as a way of life than to the modern conception of philosophy as an exercise in argumentation....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Information is Overrated</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1771.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1771</id>
    <issued>2023-03-09</issued>
    <modified>2023-03-09</modified>
    <summary>It's said that we live in the Information Age. Yet what is the purpose of information? I see at least three possibilities......</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Counter-Cultural Contemplation</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1770.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1770</id>
    <issued>2023-03-02</issued>
    <modified>2023-03-02</modified>
    <summary>We live in a culture that glorifies action, busy-ness, and constant activity. "Don't just stand there, do something." "Idle hands are the devil's workshop." "Pull your head out of the clouds." "Get real." "Think globally, act locally." "Knowledge is power."...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
