<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2023-03-09</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Information is Overrated</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1771.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1771</id>
    <issued>2023-03-09</issued>
    <modified>2023-03-09</modified>
    <summary>It's said that we live in the Information Age. Yet what is the purpose of information? I see at least three possibilities......</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Counter-Cultural Contemplation</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1770.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1770</id>
    <issued>2023-03-02</issued>
    <modified>2023-03-02</modified>
    <summary>We live in a culture that glorifies action, busy-ness, and constant activity. "Don't just stand there, do something." "Idle hands are the devil's workshop." "Pull your head out of the clouds." "Get real." "Think globally, act locally." "Knowledge is power."...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle on States of Character</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1769.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1769</id>
    <issued>2023-02-23</issued>
    <modified>2023-02-23</modified>
    <summary>One of the distinctive features of Aristotle's philosophy of human affairs is his analysis of the various states of character, of which he identifies at least four: the corrupted person, the unrestrained person, the self-restrained person, and the good person. I might describe them briefly as follows:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I Get Around</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1768.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1768</id>
    <issued>2023-02-18</issued>
    <modified>2023-02-18</modified>
    <summary>As a brief addendum to my post about digital moderation, I'll mention another longtime habit of mine: analog wayfinding. I have never used automated navigation systems like GPS; instead, if I'm going someplace new I look at a map beforehand and commit the route to memory. (For example, last year I drove from Camden, Maine to Ottawa, Canada in this way.) It helps that my spatial memory is strong: I seem to keep a schematic picture of the route in my head so that I can essentially walk through the whole thing and recall the necessary decision points when I come to an intersection. In addition, I have a general idea of my interim destinations (e.g., towns I need to pass through or roads I need to drive on), so if I go off course I have an intuitive sense of how to correct the situation. Yes, occasionally I get slightly lost, but I always pretty much know where I am. Give it a try sometime! :-)...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Of Cigarettes and Smartphones</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1767.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1767</id>
    <issued>2023-02-16</issued>
    <modified>2023-02-16</modified>
    <summary>Have you ever watched an old movie from perhaps 75 years ago in which it seems that everyone was smoking cigarettes? We - who are, of course, far wiser - shake our heads at their benighted behavior because we recognize the horrendous health effects of smoking....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Best Friend Books</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1766.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1766</id>
    <issued>2023-02-12</issued>
    <modified>2023-02-12</modified>
    <summary>It occurs to me that, just as we have circles of friendship, so also we sometimes have circles of influence and affection in the books we read. Certain books and authors are like best friends that we revisit again and again: think of those who cherish the novels of Jane Austen, the Meditations of Marcus Aurelius, the Confessions of Augustine, or the plays of Shakespeare....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
