<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2024-05-11</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics II.5-9</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1865.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1865</id>
    <issued>2024-05-11</issued>
    <modified>2024-05-11</modified>
    <summary>Following up on his initial inquiry into ἀρετή, Aristotle digs further into thrivings of character. Are they feelings or emotions like anger, fear, and jealousy? No, because those are ephemeral motions in the psyche that we experience without having chosen them, which is why people aren't praised or blamed for what they happen to feel. Are they capacities or predispositions? No, because although an irritable person (say) might be predisposed to be annoyed, irritability is something like a temporary mood founded in a capacity that everyone has. Are they stable traits (ἕξεις)? Yes, because traits are formed through a long series of actions and commitments and therefore can be described as chosen; this is why people are responsible for their character. It is the serious (σπουδαῖος) thrivings and unworthy (φαῦλος) failings of character that cause us to actively conduct ourselves well or badly in relation to the feelings, all of which involve either pleasure (e.g., affection) or pain (e.g., hatred)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Sweet Milk of Adversity</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1864.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1864</id>
    <issued>2024-05-10</issued>
    <modified>2024-05-10</modified>
    <summary>As I work my way through all the plays of Shakespeare, I've had an idea for another book, entitled The Sweet Milk of Adversity: On Shakespeare and Philosophy. It turns out that philosophical insights figure significantly throughout the plays. The title comes from Romeo and Juliet, in which Romeo and Friar Laurence have the following exchange:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics I.13-II.4</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1863.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1863</id>
    <issued>2024-05-04</issued>
    <modified>2024-05-04</modified>
    <summary>In Book I, Chapter 13 of the Nicomachean Ethics, Aristotle turns in earnest to an investigation of ἀρετή - traditionally translated as 'virtue', more recently by some scholars as 'excellence', and by yours truly as 'thriving'. I have my reasons for this novel rendering, among them a similarity between the ancient Greek verb ἀρετάω (attested several times in Homer's Odyssey) and the core meaning of the English verb thrive as "to grow or develop well" (OED). Interestingly, the OED points out that thrive can also mean "to be successful or eminent in arms or war", which is akin to ἀρετή in the sense of martial strength and excellence (cf. Latin virtūs)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics I.9-12</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1862.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1862</id>
    <issued>2024-04-26</issued>
    <modified>2024-04-26</modified>
    <summary>Having mentioned in Nicomachean Ethics I.8 the desirability of external goods such as wealth and reputation, Aristotle naturally moves on to consider the causes of human flourishing. Is fulfillment something that can be learned through training and habituation, or is it a matter of fate or even chance? Well, he says, if flourishing and fulfillment consist in a certain kind of activity (ἐνέργεια), specifically working at the task (ἔργον) of living a complete human life in accordance with inherent thrivings of mind and character, then there must be effort involved. Although this kind of beautifully right (καλός) activity is consistent with human nature, still it needs to be acquired and practiced. This is why we don't say that a child has attained fulfillment: it's necessary to achieve reasonably complete excellence (ἀρετή) of mind and character in a reasonably complete life in order to be truly fulfilled....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Poetry Reading</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1861.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1861</id>
    <issued>2024-04-25</issued>
    <modified>2024-04-25</modified>
    <summary>Yesterday evening I was honored to have a conversation with folks from the poetry circle of the Boulder Writers Alliance, at the invitation of poet Laura Border. Although I don't consider myself a poet or even primarily a writer, it was quite a pleasure to talk with such a welcoming group about the relationship between philosophy and poetry as well as the challenges of poetry translation and the differences between ancient and modern poetry. I also read aloud some poems from my books Ancient Fire and Songs of Zarathustra. Because this is a conclave of writers, we also took time toward the end of the session for each participant to write and then read aloud a short poem. Having discoursed a bit during the discussion on the attitudes of Socrates and Plato toward poetry, here's what I composed on the spot with reference to Plato's dialogues Republic and Phaedo:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics I.8</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1860.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1860</id>
    <issued>2024-04-20</issued>
    <modified>2024-04-20</modified>
    <summary>Amidst all the excitement (for philosophy scholars!) about the "function argument" in Nicomachean Ethics I.7, Chapter 8 is often overlooked. Yet there are valuable insights here, too....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
