<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2020-08-03</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>How Useful Is Philosophy, Really?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1645.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1645</id>
    <issued>2020-08-03</issued>
    <modified>2020-08-03</modified>
    <summary>It's a commonplace of research into human behavior that most of what you do is caused by your inborn personality traits, your underlying biology, the society and location and class and family into which you're born and in which you're raised, and so on - plus a smattering of luck and chance events. It can seem that all these causes conspire to leave little room for your ideals and aspirations and worldview and conscious choices to have much of an impact....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The High Freedom of Great Conversation</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1644.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1644</id>
    <issued>2020-07-25</issued>
    <modified>2020-07-25</modified>
    <summary>Aside from Montaigne and perhaps Plato, few philosophers have reflected deeply on conversation, especially the one-to-one, heart-to-heart exchange of thoughts between friend and friend. A shining exception is Ralph Waldo Emerson, who wrote as follows in his essay on friendship:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Power of Reflection</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1643.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1643</id>
    <issued>2020-07-13</issued>
    <modified>2020-07-13</modified>
    <summary>In a journal entry composed a few years ago on philosophy as a way of life, I observed:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Justifying Anger</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1642.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1642</id>
    <issued>2020-07-08</issued>
    <modified>2020-07-08</modified>
    <summary>In my last post, I extrapolated from the philosophy of Epicurus to indicate how to avoid unjustified anger and its less virulent siblings (annoyance, frustration, disappointment, etc.). Indeed, Epicurus seems to have been the first person to identify what centuries later became the seven deadly sins - one of which was anger....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Philosophy and Anger</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1641.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1641</id>
    <issued>2020-06-19</issued>
    <modified>2020-06-19</modified>
    <summary>The world is full of anger, both well-founded and ill-founded. In a future post I'll talk about well-founded anger, but this time I'll provide some reflections on ill-founded anger....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Dialogue and Deliberation</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1640.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1640</id>
    <issued>2020-06-19</issued>
    <modified>2020-06-19</modified>
    <summary>One of Aristotle’s characteristic methods for solving philosophical problems is dialectic: upon (i) reaching an impasse (aporia), he (ii) surveys existing explanations (logoi) and reputable opinions (endoxa), (iii) engages in analysis to remove paradoxes and draw distinctions, then (iv) formulates a synthesis that harmonizes the explanations and saves the appearances (phainomena)....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
