<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2019-07-21</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Hummus Recipe</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1631.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1631</id>
    <issued>2019-07-21</issued>
    <modified>2019-07-21</modified>
    <summary>One of my favorite things to eat in the summer (and in truth all year round) is hummus. Because multiple people have requested my recipe over the years, I figured I'd share it here....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #11: εὐπραξία</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1630.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1630</id>
    <issued>2019-07-07</issued>
    <modified>2019-07-07</modified>
    <summary>One of the lesser-known terms in Aristotle's ethical treatises is εὐπραξία (eupraxia) along with its sister εὐπραγία (eupragia). Both terms mean doing well, faring well, having success. Aristotle's use is connected to εὐδαιμονία, which he defines as "living well and doing well" (τὸ εὖ ζῆν καὶ τὸ εὖ πράττειν). But what are the metrics for "success" here? He leaves us several clues. First is the verb πράττειν, which for Aristotle means not merely engaging in activity but taking action, typically as the outcome of making a decision (this is why he thinks that, strictly speaking, animals and children do not "take action" even though they are clearly active physically and biologically). Second is that Aristotle contrasts εὐπραξία with εὐτυχία or good fortune; success is a matter of achievement, not luck....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>RFC 8600: XMPP Grid</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1629.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1629</id>
    <issued>2019-06-26</issued>
    <modified>2019-06-26</modified>
    <summary>Sometimes you provide so much feedback on an Internet-Draft that the authors ask you to become a co-author. Such was the case with draft-ietf-mile-xmpp-grid, which defines a method for using XMPP to exchange information about security incidents (e.g., via the IODEF format) on a controlled-access network. The resulting standard (RFC 8600) is a rare example of what the IETF standards process document defines as an "Applicability Statement" (another recent example is RFC 8036). This is the 45th RFC I've authored or co-authored, which shockingly enough is one more than Vint Cerf - not that my contributions to the Internet are nearly as important as his!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #10: σχολή</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1628.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1628</id>
    <issued>2019-05-15</issued>
    <modified>2019-05-15</modified>
    <summary>In Nicomachean Ethics X.7, Aristotle mentions almost in passing that "we engage in unleisured pursuits so that we may be at leisure" (1177b5). In Politics Book VIII, where he discusses the role of music in human life, he expands on this idea:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tales of Slow Time</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1627.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1627</id>
    <issued>2019-04-28</issued>
    <modified>2019-04-28</modified>
    <summary>I've been thinking about writing a set of linked short stories entitled Tales of Slow Time, set in the early 22nd century. As I see it, this will be a time of extremely rapid change and constant flux. Because humans won't be able to absorb change at that rate, they will be even further dumbed down and domesticated compared to today, living as they will in a culture of convenience, pleasure, entertainment, and post-literacy. The influence of raw intelligence will be even more keenly felt (cf. the seven tribes), resulting in extreme inequality. Governments everywhere will have implemented a universal basic income to placate the great mass of people who would otherwise have no livelihood. However, most people will therefore have too much free time: some will use that time to cause trouble, meddle, protest; others will play immersive video games or plug into virtual worlds; others will engage in simulacra of productivity (incubators of nothing). The human population will be both smaller and older. Information technology will be pervasive: robots will perform many routine and non-routine tasks; algorithms will rule the day; people will be subject to ubiquitous tracking, profiling, surveillance, and manipulation through advertising, marketing, nudging, and helpthink; we will experience the gamification of all activities and human/machine interactions; news, information, audio, video, AR/VR, holography - anything presented or represented through networks or computers - will be essentially made up (fiat everything); people will have little certainty about what is real. Everything and everyone will be mapped, tracked, annotated, recorded via the hypermap and the ledger. Robots will be our friends and teachers; machines will perceive our moods; all of our choices will be "suggested" by algorithms. Corporations and governments will engage in lifelong observation and manipulation of each and every individual. There will be no privacy, no autonomy, no serenity, no humanity. We will live in a materially abundant spiritual wasteland ruled by impersonal forces of government, science, technology, corporations, insurers, medicine, politics, even the arts....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle's Way: A Review</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1626.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1626</id>
    <issued>2019-04-28</issued>
    <modified>2019-04-28</modified>
    <summary>There is much to like about Aristotle's Way, a new book by Edith Hall subtitled "How Ancient Wisdom Can Change Your Life". Hall does an excellent job of showing how Aristotle is still relevant today, which she does by drawing a sympathetic picture of ancient ways of life, by describing how she has applied Aristotelian insights in her own life, and by using examples drawn from contemporary fiction and film. Her explanations of Aristotle's views on human action and character are engaging and, for the most part, accurate. She even gives due consideration to Aristotle's biological works and to the Eudemian Ethics, the often-ignored little brother of Aristotle's Nicomachean Ethics....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
