<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2024-05-28</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Brotherhood</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1869.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1869</id>
    <issued>2024-05-28</issued>
    <modified>2024-05-28</modified>
    <summary>A few months ago, Eric Hoel published a fascinating post about the nature of 21st-century society (read the whole thing, linked below, as background to what I write here). Hoel used Hegel (by way of Francis Fukuyama) and Nietzsche (by way of James Dale Davidson and William Rees-Mogg) as the jumping-off points for an analysis of what ails us. His dialectical thesis is the centrality of mob psychology in our current moment, and his antithesis is the sovereign individual who can rise above the mob....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Virtue and Happiness</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1868.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1868</id>
    <issued>2024-05-18</issued>
    <modified>2024-05-18</modified>
    <summary>One of Aristotle's signature claims in ethics is that virtue and happiness go hand in hand. To our ears this sounds questionable at best, because we think of virtue as a matter of following rules and doing your duty, whereas we think of happiness as a matter of having fun and experiencing pleasure. "Do your duty and you'll have lots of fun?" Um, no!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Scholē is Wasted on the Scholars</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1867.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1867</id>
    <issued>2024-05-15</issued>
    <modified>2024-05-15</modified>
    <summary>Exactly five years ago today I published a brief research report on the ancient Greek concept of σχολή. Illustrating the twists and turns that words can take over the millennia, for the ancients scholē meant leisure, but centuries later it also served as the root of our word 'school' - not a place that we associate with leisure!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Deep Reading</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1866.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1866</id>
    <issued>2024-05-12</issued>
    <modified>2024-05-12</modified>
    <summary>Recently someone asked me how I approach the reading of timeless books, so here are a few thoughts; perhaps you'll find this post helpful in your own reading practice. (I read "timely" books differently, but it's the timeless ones that I care about most.)...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics II.5-9</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1865.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1865</id>
    <issued>2024-05-11</issued>
    <modified>2024-05-11</modified>
    <summary>Following up on his initial inquiry into ἀρετή, Aristotle digs further into thrivings of character. Are they feelings or emotions like anger, fear, and jealousy? No, because those are ephemeral motions in the psyche that we experience without having chosen them, which is why people aren't praised or blamed for what they happen to feel. Are they capacities or predispositions? No, because although an irritable person (say) might be predisposed to be annoyed, irritability is something like a temporary mood founded in a capacity that everyone has. Are they stable traits (ἕξεις)? Yes, because traits are formed through a long series of actions and commitments and therefore can be described as chosen; this is why people are responsible for their character. It is the serious (σπουδαῖος) thrivings and unworthy (φαῦλος) failings of character that cause us to actively conduct ourselves well or badly in relation to the feelings, all of which involve either pleasure (e.g., affection) or pain (e.g., hatred)....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Sweet Milk of Adversity</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1864.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1864</id>
    <issued>2024-05-10</issued>
    <modified>2024-05-10</modified>
    <summary>As I work my way through all the plays of Shakespeare, I've had an idea for another book, entitled The Sweet Milk of Adversity: On Shakespeare and Philosophy. It turns out that philosophical insights figure significantly throughout the plays. The title comes from Romeo and Juliet, in which Romeo and Friar Laurence have the following exchange:...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
