<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2017-11-26</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Joining Mozilla</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1596.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1596</id>
    <issued>2017-11-26</issued>
    <modified>2017-11-26</modified>
    <summary>I'm overjoyed to announce that I'm joining Mozilla, makers of the Firefox web browser. I've been using Mozilla software since Milestone 8 of the original browser release in July of 1999, so this feels like coming home. More important, Mozilla's mission of defending the open web is completely consistent with my own commitment to open source and open standards (as demonstrated through my work on Jabber/XMPP and IETF standards for the past 18 years). I have deep respect for what the Mozilla team has accomplished, both architecturally and organizationally, and I'm extremely excited about helping to make Mozilla an even stronger force for good in the world!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Songs of Zarathustra: First Draft</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1595.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1595</id>
    <issued>2017-11-09</issued>
    <modified>2017-11-09</modified>
    <summary>About eight months ago, even before I published The Upland Farm as the fourth volume in my series on the art of living, I started to read Nietzsche's books for a third time, writing poems for Songs of Zarathustra as I worked my way chronologically from The Birth of Tragedy through Ecce Homo. Last weekend, I completed work on the first draft of this poetry cycle on Nietzsche's philosophy of life, which I plan to publish in early 2018. Before then, I'll read his letters and notebooks (including the ever-controversial collection called "The Will to Power") as well as some of the vast literature on Nietzsche's life and thought, such as:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ultra-Short Poems</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1594.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1594</id>
    <issued>2017-10-08</issued>
    <modified>2017-10-08</modified>
    <summary>Reading a book on Matsuo Bashō has renewed my interest in ultra-short poems. The best-known form here is haiku, which in Japanese consists of three sections of 5, 7, and 5 syllables each. The most famous haiku is probably this one written by Bashō in 1686:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Internationalized RFCs</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1593.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1593</id>
    <issued>2017-10-05</issued>
    <modified>2017-10-05</modified>
    <summary>Ever since the first "Request for Comments" (RFC 1) was published in 1969, the RFC series has been typeset exclusively in ASCII text. It's almost a running joke among technologists and programmers. Yet that is finally changing. The recently-published RFC 8187 marks the first time that RFCs have included Unicode characters and an encoding other than ASCII (i.e., UTF-8). Today, RFCs 8264, 8265, and 8266 take that a step further by using non-ASCII characters in a more thorough-going way; appropriately enough, these three RFCs define revised versions of the PRECIS specifications for the preparation, enforcement, and comparison of internationalized strings in application protocols (thus replacing RFCs 7564, 7613, and 7700, which I authored in 2015). I'm sure many readers never thought they'd see a symbol like ∞ (INFINITY, Unicode code point U+221E) in an RFC, but we did it! Many thanks to the RFC Editor team for making this day possible, and to my co-authors Marc Blanchet and Alexey Melnikov for making this day necessary. ;-)...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Asymmetries</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1592.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1592</id>
    <issued>2017-09-23</issued>
    <modified>2017-09-23</modified>
    <summary>Having done a lot of hiring and recruiting lately, I've been struck by the deep asymmetries of information and power involved in the process of building a team. Because the organization has the money, it can compel the applicant (supplicant?) to complete intelligence tests and personality assessments, ask lots of questions about background and knowledge and experience, require completion of a sample work task or delivery of a short-term project, perform background checks, call character references, and just about whatever else the hiring manager or HR department can dream up. Yet how much information does the applicant get to truly learn about the organization or, especially, the hiring manager? Consider that, supposedly, 50% of voluntary terminations occur because the employee does not like or agree with or get along with the employee's manager - yet the fundamental asymmetry of the hiring process means that the employee is mostly in the dark about potential problems in this key aspect of the employment relationship....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Providing an Alternative</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1591.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1591</id>
    <issued>2017-08-16</issued>
    <modified>2017-08-16</modified>
    <summary>Although I pay no attention to the news, I'm vaguely aware that perhaps the world is becoming more negative and irrational. Rather than getting lost in despair and confusion, I try to model a positive, reasonable alternative by living the best life I can and by writing philosophical books that are clear, concise, and constructive. I've written six such books, with a seventh half done and an eighth outlined. Even though each of these books takes 500-1000 hours to research and write, I make them all available for free on my website (however, I do charge for the paperback and ebook versions). To date I've also made no effort to market them, so I depend on word of mouth. If you have found value in any of these books, I'd greatly appreciate it if you could tell a friend, write a review at Amazon, or give a copy as a gift. Thanks. :-)...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
