<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2024-10-05</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Whole Wheat Pancake Recipe</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1905.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1905</id>
    <issued>2024-10-05</issued>
    <modified>2024-10-05</modified>
    <summary>Every once in a while I post a recipe here, almost as much for my own reference as for sharing. Because several people have asked me about my whole wheat pancakes recently, I figured I'd write up how I make them....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Criticism vs. Cultivation</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1904.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1904</id>
    <issued>2024-10-04</issued>
    <modified>2024-10-04</modified>
    <summary>So much of what one reads online these days consists of social and cultural criticism, even when it avoids the cesspool of partisan vitriol. Case in point: over the last few days I've run across several essays that bemoan the decline of reading and the seemingly inexorable emergence of a post-literate society. Although I've made similar observations over the years, it strikes me that at a personal level such forms of criticism are nearly devoid of value. Instead, what matters are the practices that I cultivate in my own life. I grant that exposing oneself to social and cultural criticism can, at times, inspire a change in behavior; yet, all too often, criticism without cultivation is "sound and fury, signifying nothing". Marx proclaimed that "Philosophers have hitherto only interpreted the world in various ways; the point is to change it." Yet I agree more with Tolstoy, who contended that "Everyone thinks of changing the world, but no one thinks of changing himself." If you ask me, changing oneself is the true function of philosophy....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics VII.11-14</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1903.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1903</id>
    <issued>2024-09-24</issued>
    <modified>2024-09-24</modified>
    <summary>Early on in the Nicomachean Ethics, Aristotle observed that thrivings and corruptions of character are centrally concerned with managing life's pleasures and pains, joys and distresses; as two examples, the cowardly person fails to act courageously out of a desire to avoid even necessary pains, whereas the decadent person fails to act moderately out of a desire to pursue even unnecessary pleasures. Here in Book VII, Aristotle expands on those observations and provides a stronger foundation for his claims....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics VII.1-10</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1902.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1902</id>
    <issued>2024-09-21</issued>
    <modified>2024-09-21</modified>
    <summary>At the end of Nicomachean Ethics Book VI, Aristotle sketched out an ideal of human flourishing, in the form of the seriously good person who seamlessly combines excellence of mind and character, practical wisdom [phronēsis] and ethical thriving [aretē]. Yet human experience is not always so seamless. There are many ways to go astray in life, which in Book VII Aristotle boils down to three: corruption [mochthēria] of character, lack of self-restraint [akrasia], and, rarely, a deficient state that borders on an animal-like existence [theriotēs]....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tao Te Ching §33: Know Yourself</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1901.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1901</id>
    <issued>2024-09-17</issued>
    <modified>2024-09-17</modified>
    <summary>Here's another of my renderings from the Tao Te Ching:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics VI.12-13</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1900.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1900</id>
    <issued>2024-09-15</issued>
    <modified>2024-09-15</modified>
    <summary>In the final two chapters of Nicomachean Ethics Book VI, Aristotle asks some probing questions about thrivings of mind and character....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
