<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2019-06-26</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>RFC 8600: XMPP Grid</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1629.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1629</id>
    <issued>2019-06-26</issued>
    <modified>2019-06-26</modified>
    <summary>Sometimes you provide so much feedback on an Internet-Draft that the authors ask you to become a co-author. Such was the case with draft-ietf-mile-xmpp-grid, which defines a method for using XMPP to exchange information about security incidents (e.g., via the IODEF format) on a controlled-access network. The resulting standard (RFC 8600) is a rare example of what the IETF standards process document defines as an "Applicability Statement" (another recent example is RFC 8036). This is the 45th RFC I've authored or co-authored, which shockingly enough is one more than Vint Cerf - not that my contributions to the Internet are nearly as important as his!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #10: σχολή</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1628.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1628</id>
    <issued>2019-05-15</issued>
    <modified>2019-05-15</modified>
    <summary>In Nicomachean Ethics X.7, Aristotle mentions almost in passing that "we engage in unleisured pursuits so that we may be at leisure" (1177b5). In Politics Book VIII, where he discusses the role of music in human life, he expands on this idea:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tales of Slow Time</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1627.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1627</id>
    <issued>2019-04-28</issued>
    <modified>2019-04-28</modified>
    <summary>I've been thinking about writing a set of linked short stories entitled Tales of Slow Time, set in the early 22nd century. As I see it, this will be a time of extremely rapid change and constant flux. Because humans won't be able to absorb change at that rate, they will be even further dumbed down and domesticated compared to today, living as they will in a culture of convenience, pleasure, entertainment, and post-literacy. The influence of raw intelligence will be even more keenly felt (cf. the seven tribes), resulting in extreme inequality. Governments everywhere will have implemented a universal basic income to placate the great mass of people who would otherwise have no livelihood. However, most people will therefore have too much free time: some will use that time to cause trouble, meddle, protest; others will play immersive video games or plug into virtual worlds; others will engage in simulacra of productivity (incubators of nothing). The human population will be both smaller and older. Information technology will be pervasive: robots will perform many routine and non-routine tasks; algorithms will rule the day; people will be subject to ubiquitous tracking, profiling, surveillance, and manipulation through advertising, marketing, nudging, and helpthink; we will experience the gamification of all activities and human/machine interactions; news, information, audio, video, AR/VR, holography - anything presented or represented through networks or computers - will be essentially made up (fiat everything); people will have little certainty about what is real. Everything and everyone will be mapped, tracked, annotated, recorded via the hypermap and the ledger. Robots will be our friends and teachers; machines will perceive our moods; all of our choices will be "suggested" by algorithms. Corporations and governments will engage in lifelong observation and manipulation of each and every individual. There will be no privacy, no autonomy, no serenity, no humanity. We will live in a materially abundant spiritual wasteland ruled by impersonal forces of government, science, technology, corporations, insurers, medicine, politics, even the arts....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle's Way: A Review</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1626.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1626</id>
    <issued>2019-04-28</issued>
    <modified>2019-04-28</modified>
    <summary>There is much to like about Aristotle's Way, a new book by Edith Hall subtitled "How Ancient Wisdom Can Change Your Life". Hall does an excellent job of showing how Aristotle is still relevant today, which she does by drawing a sympathetic picture of ancient ways of life, by describing how she has applied Aristotelian insights in her own life, and by using examples drawn from contemporary fiction and film. Her explanations of Aristotle's views on human action and character are engaging and, for the most part, accurate. She even gives due consideration to Aristotle's biological works and to the Eudemian Ethics, the often-ignored little brother of Aristotle's Nicomachean Ethics....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Never Finished</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1625.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1625</id>
    <issued>2019-03-07</issued>
    <modified>2019-03-07</modified>
    <summary>Last weekend I went to an exhibit related to Leonardo da Vinci at the Denver Museum of Nature and Science. Amidst the reconstructions of his inventions and at the entrance to a whole room about the Mona Lisa I came across this quote: "Art is never finished, only abandoned." Although it's not clear to me if Leonardo actually said that (Vasari mentions something similar in his Life of Leonardo), I like the sentiment....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #9: τέλος</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1624.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1624</id>
    <issued>2019-03-07</issued>
    <modified>2019-03-07</modified>
    <summary>Part of my goal in writing an epitome of Aristotle's writings on personal excellence is to get closer to their original meaning, which I do by reflecting deeply on how to render crucial Greek words into English. Consider this cluster: τέλος, τελεία, τελειώτατον. In his book Aristotle on the Human Good, Richard Kraut translates them with variations on the English word "perfection". In present-day English, "perfect" has connotations of being absolutely without blemish; thus something perfect seems static and cold and unchanging, not dynamic and warm and living. I get a distinctly unworldly (dare I say Platonic?) feeling from Kraut's translation. Yet in Greek τέλος is something much simpler: the end-marker or finish-line of a racecourse. A τέλος is a goal; you can achieve a goal or complete a race, but you don't perfect a goal or perfect a race. Similarly with τελεία: Aristotle speaks of τελεία ἀρετή, which I would render as complete excellence (not "perfect virtue"). So also with τελειώτατον: in his analysis of εὐδαιμονία or living well Aristotle mentions that the highest goal of human action needs to be the most complete (not "most perfect") because if you could add anything more to it then there would be a more valuable goal. In all of these instances, I am tempted to find the idea of "completing" or "most completing" behind the scenes; in Aristotle's philosophy, the concept of ἐντελέχεια (becoming complete, achieving a goal, completing a task) is always central. And note that the task (ἔργον) you're working at (ἐνέργεια) is not imposed from outside but grows organically from within; Aristotle's teleology (there's that τέλος again) is not universal but particular, individual, personal. Thus my working title: Complete Yourself....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
