<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2025-07-31</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Values Are Overrated</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1977.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1977</id>
    <issued>2025-07-31</issued>
    <modified>2025-07-31</modified>
    <summary>Modern society is filled with incessant talk about the importance of good values. Yet talk is cheap and values are overrated. Much more important than values are commitments, practices, and actions....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>All, Some, One</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1976.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1976</id>
    <issued>2025-07-21</issued>
    <modified>2025-07-21</modified>
    <summary>A recent essay by Fasil Merawi about Ethiopian philosophy set me to thinking (and to ordering a copy of the Hatatas). According to Merawi, there are two opposing philosophical camps in Ethiopia:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Greatness in Philosophy</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1975.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1975</id>
    <issued>2025-07-12</issued>
    <modified>2025-07-12</modified>
    <summary>In ยง25 of his book Critique of Religion and Philosophy, Walter Kaufmann wrote:...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Culture Streams</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1974.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1974</id>
    <issued>2025-07-11</issued>
    <modified>2025-07-11</modified>
    <summary>Here are a few more thoughts on the flavorful gumbo that is American culture. This time I'll introduce a different metaphor: a great river that is formed from numerous streams, each with its own sources, rapids, eddies, and, ultimately, individual droplets of water....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>American Gumbo</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1973.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1973</id>
    <issued>2025-07-04</issued>
    <modified>2025-07-04</modified>
    <summary>While slowly writing a long poem about America as the nation of many nations, I've been reading widely about the peoples who have come together to form the American people - the numerous tribes of indigenous American Indians of course, and then a vast, continuing, 400-year migration of East Anglian Puritans, West Country Cavaliers, Dutch Calvinists, North Midland Quakers, German Pietists, enslaved Africans, British convicts, Scottish Presbyterians, French Huguenots, Irish Catholics, Norwegian and Swedish Lutherans, Jews, Italians, French Canadians, Portuguese, Finns, Russians, Poles, Ukrainians, Japanese, Filipinos, Puerto Ricans, Jamaicans, Mexicans, Cubans, Brazilians, Chinese, Koreans, Vietnamese, Hmong, Lebanese, Egyptians, Persians, Indians, Ethiopians, Nigerians, and folks from every other nation of the world....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Go There, Do It, Write It</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1972.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1972</id>
    <issued>2025-06-22</issued>
    <modified>2025-06-22</modified>
    <summary>I've just started reading David Hackett Fischer's massive book African Founders: How Enslaved People Expanded American Ideals, a worthy follow-up to the magisterial Albion's Seed (which I also happen to be re-reading as background to my in-progress poem "Song of the Nations"). In the introduction, Fischer cites three rules for historical research that were originally formulated by Francis Parkman: "Go There", "Do It", and "Write It" (advice that Parkman followed in spades, for example in his well-known work on the Oregon Trail)....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
