<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2018-09-26</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>You're Majoring in What?!?</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1610.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1610</id>
    <issued>2018-09-26</issued>
    <modified>2018-09-26</modified>
    <summary>On October 10th I'll give a talk entitled "You're Majoring in What?!? Why Philosophy is a Foundation for Success" at the University of Colorado Boulder (Hellems Arts and Sciences building, room 199, 6 PM). Although I don't believe it will be recorded, at the least I'll post the slides afterward. And if you live in the vicinity, feel free to stop by - I'll use my typical "performance art" presentation style, so it might even be mildly entertaining. :-)...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Foundations for Philosophical Practice</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1609.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1609</id>
    <issued>2018-09-24</issued>
    <modified>2018-09-24</modified>
    <summary>Recently I've revisited a field that's intrigued me for some time: philosophical counselling, or more broadly philosophical practice. Most of those active in this field are almost anti-method, and what methods they do employ are derived from hermeneutics, phenomenology, existentialism, Stoicism, and Socratic questioning - some of which I find interesting but none of which I find deeply congenial. Philosophical practice emerged in Europe around 1980 among thinkers influenced by hermeneutics and existentialism, and even the American philosophers in this area are mostly existentialists (associated with the American Philosophical Practitioners Association) or Stoics (associated with the National Philosophical Counseling Association) - for instance, Elliot Cohen, the progenitor of logic-based therapy, was a disciple of Albert Ellis (inventor of Rational Emotive Behavior Therapy). By contrast, my philosophical orientation is toward eudaimonia (the ancient Greek term for happiness, flourishing, living well) and the focus of my writing and living is on solving problems that hinder the pursuit of happiness. Upon reflection, I'm starting to see the possibility of developing a more joyous approach to philosophical practice that takes its inspiration from positive thinkers - especially the six I'm writing books about: Rand, Nietzsche, Aristotle, Thoreau, Epicurus, and Lao Tzu....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Perspectives on the Path</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1608.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1608</id>
    <issued>2018-09-05</issued>
    <modified>2018-09-05</modified>
    <summary>An essential lesson of philosophy is the ancient Greek formula "know yourself". It sounds easy, but it's immensely difficult. One model of self-knowledge I'm exploring is to look at your path in life from six different perspectives: beginning, end, above, below, side, within....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Intensive Reading</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1607.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1607</id>
    <issued>2018-07-23</issued>
    <modified>2018-07-23</modified>
    <summary>As previously mentioned, I have in mind to write a novel about the ancient Greek philosopher Pyrrho and his journey to central Asia and northwestern India with the army of Alexander the Great. As part of my research I'm reading a great deal of philosophy, history, and fiction. It's been fascinating to return to the reading of fiction after a lapse of many years - I feel like I have fresh eyes for everything. My readings in the genre of philosophical fiction have ranged all over the map - during a business trip last week I devoured The Name of the Rose by Umberto Eco, before that I re-read The Left Hand of Darkness by Ursula K. Le Guin, and I'm currently reading both The Picture of Dorian Gray by Oscar Wilde and The Awakening by Kate Chopin. Alongside these works of fiction I'm reading books of philosophical scholarship (the latest were a full-length study of Pyrrho and an exploration of epistemology after Protagoras) and I'm starting to explore the historical background to the massive cultural change from classical to hellenistic Greece. Umberto Eco's book in particular has given me a new ambition of combining the story of Pyrrho's intellectual development with a mystery novel about the still unexplained death of Alexander the Great! It turns out the Pyrrho was probably not quite the radical skeptic he's usually taken to be (although he did believe that the entities we encounter in reality are indefinite and thus hard to pin down in many ways). Combine this with political intrigue on an imperial scale and perhaps regicide (indeed, there's an ancient legend that Aristotle himself was somehow involved in the assassination of his former pupil Alexander, perhaps in revenge for Alexander's execution of Aristotle's nephew Kallisthenes), and we might have the makings of large-scale novel that hinges in part on the validity of the law of non-contradiction! This is all quite speculative at this point because I have over 200 more books to read during the research phase, and I would also need to intensively study how the better authors construct their novels (an art of which I am mostly ignorant). Although I'm not sure if I have a book this big in me, I'm enjoying the exploration of possibilities. And all this reading has kept me from blogging, thus my absence here. Hopefully the results will be worth waiting for......</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Notes Toward an Aristotelian Philosophy of Music</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1606.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1606</id>
    <issued>2018-04-13</issued>
    <modified>2018-04-13</modified>
    <summary>In Book VIII of his Politics, Aristotle talks about music: its role in ancient Greek education, its differences from the other arts, and its philosophical significance. This is not an in-depth exploration of the philosophy of music (what I wouldn't give for his lost work Ρερὶ Μουσικῆς), but more of a cursory glance. Yet through extrapolation we can tease out some meaning from his discussion....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Aristotle Research Report #4: ἀρετή</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1605.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1605</id>
    <issued>2018-02-12</issued>
    <modified>2018-02-12</modified>
    <summary>I'm starting to see that Aristotle's conception of ἀρετή (which I translate as thriving but which is more commonly translated as excellence or virtue) describes a deliberate practice of good judgment, reasoned choice, and planned activity resulting in a balance between extremes of action and emotional reaction in a particular domain of human life....</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
