<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>https://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>https://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2024-09-10</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Information vs. Wisdom</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1899.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1899</id>
    <issued>2024-09-10</issued>
    <modified>2024-09-10</modified>
    <summary>The world is awash with information. Some information is misinformation (falsehoods), and some misinformation is disinformation (deliberate falsehoods), but all of it is stuff that needs to processed in order to be useful, otherwise it's not much better than gossip or rumor....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Homeric Ambiguity</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1898.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1898</id>
    <issued>2024-09-08</issued>
    <modified>2024-09-08</modified>
    <summary>One of the many fascinating aspects of both the Iliad and the Odyssey is the fundamental ambiguity of Homer's stories. Is the Iliad a great war poem - or a great anti-war poem? Is Achilles really the hero of the Iliad, or is it perhaps Hector (whose death and funeral mark the end of the poem)? Are the gods the sources and enforcers of justice, or are they just as often capriciously unjust (e.g., in causing the ten-year wanderings of Odysseus after the Trojan War)? And so on....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics VI.9-11</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1897.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1897</id>
    <issued>2024-09-05</issued>
    <modified>2024-09-05</modified>
    <summary>Here toward the end of Book VI Aristotle looks at several skills and traits that are either constituents of wisdom or similar to wisdom in certain respects: deliberative excellence [euboulia], astuteness [sunesis], thoughtfulness [gnōmē], and sensitivity [sungnōmē]....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics VI.6-8</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1896.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1896</id>
    <issued>2024-09-03</issued>
    <modified>2024-09-03</modified>
    <summary>In the most recent installment of our walk with Aristotle, we puzzled through the beginnings of his analysis of wisdom [phronēsis]. In Book VI.6-8 he climbs further up this steep section of the trail to discuss not only wisdom but also sagacity [sophia]....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Republic If You Can Keep It</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1895.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1895</id>
    <issued>2024-08-30</issued>
    <modified>2024-08-30</modified>
    <summary>Every year around Independence Day, I carve out time to read and reflect on the Declaration of Independence and the Constitution; and every year I notice something new. This year it was the first clause in Article IV, Section 4: "The United States shall guarantee to every State in this Union a Republican Form of Government." As with everything else in the Constitution, this "guarantee clause" has been analyzed historically, legally, and philosophically over the last 200+ years. Although I'm not a scholar of the Constitution and don't plan to become one, my curiosity was piqued, so I decided to gain a slightly better understanding of republicanism (with a small "r")....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Pyrrho in the Light of Homer</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://stpeter.im/journal/1894.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1894</id>
    <issued>2024-08-28</issued>
    <modified>2024-08-28</modified>
    <summary>Only the merest wisps of evidence remain for the thoughts of Pyrrho, the founder of ancient Greek skepticism and, perhaps, the bringer of Buddhism to Greece. Like Socrates, Pyrrho wrote nothing. His disciple Timon of Phlius did some writing, but almost all of it is lost. The primary text that has survived from antiquity is a brief passage in the Preparation for the Gospel by the Christian polemicist Eusebius of Caesarea (4th century AD), who quotes from Book VIII of On Philosophy by the Peripatetic philosopher Aristocles of Messene (1st century AD), who in turn cites but doesn't seem to precisely quote Timon. That's not much to go on!...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
