<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>One Small Voice</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/"/>
  <author>
    <name>Peter Saint-Andre</name>
    <url>http://stpeter.im/</url>
  </author>
  <tagline>The journal of Peter Saint-Andre - technologist, musician, philosopher.</tagline>
  <id>http://stpeter.im/journal/</id>
  <copyright>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</copyright>
  <modified>2023-09-30</modified>
  <entry>
    <title>Sentience and Salience</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1825.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1825</id>
    <issued>2023-09-30</issued>
    <modified>2023-09-30</modified>
    <summary>As you might have guessed from yesterday's post about opinion machines, I'm skeptical that so-called artificial intelligence systems will exhibit sentience anytime soon. Thus, although my primary concern is how humans will act in relation to these systems (even more personally, how I will act), I figure it can't hurt to sketch out my thinking on the broader topic....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Opinion Machines</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1824.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1824</id>
    <issued>2023-09-29</issued>
    <modified>2023-09-29</modified>
    <summary>As I've striven over the last few years to hold fewer opinions, those who hold opinions about seemingly everything have become more noticeable to me. Whether it's the prospects for runaway inflation, the underlying causes for increasing loneliness in society, or the likely outcome of the upcoming elections in Ecuador, some bloggers and pundits are like opinion machines, able to crank out a position on anything at a moment's notice....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Outline of Complete Thyself</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1823.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1823</id>
    <issued>2023-09-26</issued>
    <modified>2023-09-26</modified>
    <summary>You might have noticed that the pace of blogging has slowed around here. There are two primary reasons for this state of affairs. One is that we recently got a golden retriever puppy named Chance and he's keeping us busy!...</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Passion vs. Obsession</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1822.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1822</id>
    <issued>2023-09-18</issued>
    <modified>2023-09-18</modified>
    <summary>In my recent post about consuming vs. producing, I mentioned a distinct but semi-related distinction: passion vs. obsession....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Consuming vs. Producing</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1821.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1821</id>
    <issued>2023-09-08</issued>
    <modified>2023-09-08</modified>
    <summary>During my Open Reading interview with Sal Inglima a few months ago, I mentioned my opinion that producing poetry is more fulfilling than reading poetry. Although this is an opinion that it might be best for me to let go of, before doing so I'd like to generalize and expand on the idea....</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Frames of Mind</title>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://stpeter.im/journal/1820.html"/>
    <id>tag:stpeter.im,1820</id>
    <issued>2023-08-31</issued>
    <modified>2023-08-31</modified>
    <summary>In my recent post about snares and attachments (and in my older post about idealism and identity), I observed that it's all too easy to become attached to one's opinions and ideas. In his book On the Wisdom of America (pp. 229-230), Lin Yutang makes a similar point with regard to what he calls frames of mind:...</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
