<journal>
<header><title>XMPP and Social Networking: Two Great Tastes That Taste Great Together!</title><date>2008-06-11</date></header>
<entry>
<p>I've previously mentioned the explosion of interest in adding real-time features to social networking applications using <a href="https://xmpp.org/">XMPP</a> technologies. The list of services that are deploying or even just exploring this combination of technologies reads like a who's who in the space: Twitter, Facebook, Mozilla's Songza and Bloxes and Weave, Yahoo's Fire Eagle, Dopplr, Jaiku, Seesmic, Sharpcast, Threadless, NewBay, Spotify, Gnip, OpenSpime, and many others (including some big ones that have not yet "decloaked").</p>
<p>If you're interested in XMPP and social networking, there are two upcoming events you might want to check out:</p>
<ol>
  <li>On June 25th, I will be participating in a <a href="http://www.jabber.com/CE/XMPPAddingLifetotheSocialInternet_LPPSABlog">free webinar</a> on the topic with Alex King of <a href="https://crowdfavorite.com/">Crowd Favorite</a> and Joe Hildebrand of <a href="https://www.jabber.com/">Jabber Inc.</a>. This will be a good way to dip your toes in the water and see what all the fuss is about.</li>
  <li>If you're a hardcore techno-geek, consider coming to the fifth <a href="https://xmpp.org/summit/summit5.shtml">XMPP Summit</a> to be held on July 21st and 22nd in Portland, Oregon. This small, exclusive technology conference is held twice a year by the <a href="https://xmpp.org/xsf/">XMPP Standards Foundation</a> and brings together some of the best minds in the XMPP developer community, this year including folks from many of the aforementioned companies. And it, too, is free!</li>
</ol>
<p>If you can't make it to either of these events, don't despair: we also have a dedicated mailing list at <a href="https://mail.jabber.org/mailman/listinfo/social">social@xmpp.org</a> for ongoing discussion of XMPP and social networking. They're two great tastes that taste great together! :)</p>
</entry>
</journal>
