<journal>
<header><title>Wandering the Web</title><date>2001-10-29</date></header>
<entry>
<p>Yesterday I surfed around a bit in the first few entries of <a href="http://underwatergirl.blogspot.com/">Moira's blog</a> and I came across a link to the website of <a href="http://www.geocities.com/aestallings/">A.E. Stallings</a>, poetess extraordinaire. Stallings in turn links to the website of <a href="http://www.danagioia.net/">Dana Gioia</a>, one of my favorite living poets. Both <em>Archaic Smile</em> and <em>Interrogations at Noon</em> are on my wish list, you can be sure!</p>
<p>Oracle CEO Larry Ellison is arguing for national ID cards tied to huge government databases (all running his company's software, naturally). The tireless Declan McCullagh <a href="http://www.wired.com/news/print/0,1294,47788,00.html">takes him to task</a>.</p>
<p>In my continuing efforts to broaden my mind and question my assumptions, I paid a brief visit to <a href="http://www.antiwar.com/">Antiwar.com</a>. Rep. Ron Paul has a good essay there on <a href="http://www.antiwar.com/paul/paul11.html">defending the U.S. only</a>, not maintaining a far-flung empire of military installations. The folks at Antiwar.com seem to be what I would call left-libertarians, a direction in which I've tended myself. The recent attack on American soil has generally made people more conservative, I think, so it's good to see that some people are remaining consistent (even though I'm not sure I can agree with those who oppose military action against Osama and the Taliban).</p>
<p>Today's quote from <a href="/heroes/hugo/">Victor Hugo</a>: "Navigation is education. The sea is a hard school. Cohabitation with these unmanageable phenomena produces a rough race of men who deserve to be cherished: the mariners. There are no other conquerors but them. Ulysses the voyager accomplishes more than Achilles the fighter." (<em>The Toilers of the Sea</em>, III.1.iii)</p>
<p>And another: "What is the invasion of kingdoms compared to the opening up of intellects?" (<em>William Shakespeare</em>, III.3.iv)</p>
</entry>
</journal>
