<journal>
<header><title>Consent</title><date>2008-10-04</date></header>
<entry>
<p>As I just quoted, the Declaration of Independence states "That to secure these rights, Governments are instituted among Men, deriving their just powers from the consent of the governed". I observe the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Governments are instituted (they are not natural).</li>
<li>The purpose of that instituting is to secure natural, inalienable rights.</li>
<li>Governments can have just powers and, presumably, unjust powers.</li>
<li>The just powers of governments are granted through the consent of the governed.</li>
</ul>
<p>From these principles, classical liberals tend to draw several conclusions:</p>
<ul>
<li>The unjust powers of governments are not and cannot be granted through the consent of the governed (they are powers taken, not powers granted).</li>
<li>Any powers beyond securing natural, inalienable rights are unjust.</li>
<li>Governments can be just if all they do is secure natural, inalienable rights.</li>
</ul>
<p>Those of a more deeply individualist persuasion might go even farther:</p>
<ul>
<li>Governments cannot be instituted among "the governed" because human beings are naturally sovereign; only to the extent that people are ungoverned can they freely choose to give their consent to any agreement (including especially the agreement to institute a government).</li>
<li>Throughout history, governments have never been instituted solely or even primarily to secure the natural, inalienable rights of the individual.</li>
<li>At any time you have the right to withdraw your consent from any government, even if some part of its activities is devoted to securing individual rights.</li>
<li>After you have withdrawn your consent, you cannot legitimately be governed because, as Lincoln said, "No man is good enough to govern another man without that other's consent."</li>
</ul>
<p>Over time I find myself trending farther away from the classical liberal position and closer to the individualist position. What that implies for my political views is not something I've settled on yet...</p>
</entry>
</journal>
