<journal>
<header><title>Tepid Tea</title><date>2009-04-17</date></header>
<entry>
<p>The Tax Day Tea Party in Denver was quite good, but I was disappointed in the lukewarm advice given by the speakers about how to keep the spirit of liberty alive. Indeed, all I heard was the typical middle-of-the-road twaddle about writing letters to your congresscritter. C'mon folks, I think we're rapidly moving beyond that. Here are some more slightly more radical suggestions they could have made:</p>
<ul>
<li>Network, network, network -- exchange business cards with five people near you in the crowd and follow up with them to strengthen the bonds of community. Do the same on Facebook, MySpace, and other websites.</li>
<li>Exercise <em>all</em> your rights by starting a blog, peacefully assembling on a regular basis, learning to shoot, etc.</li>
<li>Fly the Gadsden flag every day.</li>
<li>Encrypt your email using "Pretty Good Privacy" (PGP).</li>
<li>Spread the idea that April 15th or Tax Freedom Day is a great time to take off from work to show your dissatisfaction with being Taxed Enough Already.</li>
<li>Support <a href="http://www.tenthamendmentcenter.com/2009/02/23/state-sovereignty-resolutions/">state sovereignty resolutions</a> in your state.</li>
<li>Show up in large numbers at city council meetings and state legislative hearings that would expand the scope of government.</li>
<li>Stop voting for politicians of any stripe and instead <em>withdraw your consent</em> from our corrupt political system.</li>
<li>Condemn, ignore, or ridicule those in the political class.</li>
<li>Vote with your feet by moving to a state that is more free than the one you're in now.</li>
<li>Boycott banks that voluntarily take TARP funds, non-profits that accept government grants, etc.</li>
<li>Take some of your purchases out of the system by bartering, trading, completing cash-only transactions, etc.</li>
<li>Take some reasonable percentage of your money out of the funny-money economy by putting it into hard assets like gold and silver.</li>
<li>Take your kids out of the government education system by homeschooling them.</li>
<li>Downsize your expenses by moving to a less expensive home so that you can reduce your taxable income and thus the amount you pay in taxes -- hit the politicians where it hurts most!</li>
</ul>
<p>I'm sure you can think of more...</p>
</entry>
</journal>
