<journal>
<header><title>Hugo and Rand</title><date>2001-11-15</date></header>
<entry>
<p>The other night I posted a <a href="/writings/rand/hugo-rand.html">new essay</a> at the <a href="http://review.monadnock.net/">Monadnock Review</a>, the literary webzine I edit. This essay contains some thoughts of mine on the purpose of art, refracted through a contrast between Ayn Rand and Victor Hugo. There's much more I could have said about Hugo and Rand, but I didn't want to make the essay too long or academic. I see this essay fitting into my ongoing project of a collection of <a href="/wrirings/rand/apfloe.html">essays on Ayn Rand and Objectivism</a>.</p>
<p>The Economist has a <a href="https://www.economist.com/world/na/displayStory.cfm?Story_ID=863432">good perspective</a> on the supposed conflict between the Christian West and Muslim East. I've been skeptical of assertions by writers like <a href="http://www.nationalreview.com/15oct01/johnson101501.shtml">Paul Johnson</a> and <a href="http://www.nationalreview.com/derbyshire/derbyshire111501.shtml">John Derbyshire</a> that we're witnessing the continuation of centuries-old Christian-Muslim conflict, dating back at least as far as the Crusades.</p>
<p>My old friend Jim Robbins is <a href="http://www.nationalreview.com/contributors/robbins111401.shtml">at it again</a> (<a href="http://www.nationalreview.com/search-results/comment/comment-robbins100901.shtml">and again</a>). He's an entertaining writer. Jim's comments about what would happen if Osama Bin Laden were tried in American courts if captured alive are instructive. I wonder if it's the spectre of such a farce that has goaded Bush into <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/15/opinion/15SAFI.html">seizing the dictatorial power</a> to try foreign nationals in military courts using any rules the administration deems convenient -- certainly a dangerous precedent and a serious step on the road to tyranny.</p>
<p>Today's quote from <a href="http://monadnock.net/fanspaces/hugo/">Victor Hugo</a>: "Despotism violates the moral frontier just as foreign invasion violates the geographical frontier." (<em>Les Miserables</em>, IV.13.iii)</p>
</entry>
</journal>
