<journal>
<header><title>To Be a Philosopher</title><date>2011-07-13</date></header>
<entry>
<p>In the ten minutes a day I have for reading something other than work-related emails and protocol specifications, I've been absorbing Pierre Hadot's book <cite>What Is Ancient Philosophy?</cite> There's so much to reflect on here that I'll need to read it again and then post further. However, I wanted to note one small point about the genesis of the term philosophy. </p>
<p>For the ancient Greeks, the "philo-" prefix meant to love a thing or activity, to take great interest in it, to find your highest pleasure in it. Thus a myriad of terms like &#x3C6;&#x3B9;&#x3BB;&#x3CC;&#x3B3;&#x3B1;&#x3B9;&#x3BF;&#x3C2; (earth-lover), &#x3C6;&#x3B9;&#x3BB;&#x3BF;&#x3B3;&#x3CD;&#x3BD;&#x3B7;&#x3C2; (interested in women),  &#x3C6;&#x3B9;&#x3BB;&#x3CC;&#x3B8;&#x3B7;&#x3C1;&#x3BF;&#x3C2; (enjoying the hunt), &#x3C6;&#x3AF;&#x3BB;&#x3BF;&#x3B9;&#x3BD;&#x3BF;&#x3C2; (wine-lover), &#x3C6;&#x3B9;&#x3BB;&#x3CC;&#x3C4;&#x3B5;&#x3C7;&#x3BD;&#x3BF;&#x3C2; (loving or practicing an art), even &#x3C6;&#x3B9;&#x3BB;&#x3CC;&#x3C6;&#x3B9;&#x3BB;&#x3BF;&#x3C2; (taking great pleasure in your friends). So a &#x3C6;&#x3B9;&#x3BB;&#x3CC;&#x3C3;&#x3BF;&#x3C6;&#x3BF;&#x3C2; was someone who loved, took pleasure in, was intensely interested in, was fascinated by, or was otherwise engaged in &#x3C3;&#x3BF;&#x3C6;&#x3AF;&#x3B1;.</p>
<p>But what was this &#x3C3;&#x3BF;&#x3C6;&#x3AF;&#x3B1;? To be &#x3C3;&#x3BF;&#x3C6;&#x3CC;&#x3C2; was to be skillful, clever, cunning, crafty, prudent, shrewd, wise in the sense of streetwise, but also well-taught, knowledgeable, learned, profound, subtle, abstruse. You could have &#x3C3;&#x3BF;&#x3C6;&#x3AF;&#x3B1; &mdash; know-how &mdash; in practical activities like carpentry or shipbuilding or the playing of the lyre. You could also have it in language and discourse, like the Sophists, who would teach you (for a fee) the tricks of the rhetorical trade so that you could be skillful and successful in the public life of the city-state. </p>
<p>Yet merely to be fond of speaking (&#x3C6;&#x3B9;&#x3BB;&#x3CC;&#x3BB;&#x3BF;&#x3B3;&#x3BF;&#x3C2;) was not the same as being fond of wisdom (&#x3C6;&#x3B9;&#x3BB;&#x3CC;&#x3C3;&#x3BF;&#x3C6;&#x3BF;&#x3C2;), because &#x3C6;&#x3B9;&#x3BB;&#x3BF;&#x3C3;&#x3BF;&#x3C6;&#x3AF;&#x3B1; was a way of living &mdash; especially a particular rule of life associated with a school (really a community of like-minded and similarly-instructed fellow seekers-after-wisdom) such as the Platonists or Stoics or Epicureans. To be a philosopher meant to live a philosophical life: not a life of theoretical hair-splitting, but a life of practical wisdom, active reason and reasoned action, deep reflection, true consciousness, vibrant awareness, moral ambition, never-ending spiritual practice, continual striving after self-improvement, the exercise of all your faculties, skillfulness in the great task of living a fully human life. </p>
<p>And that vision is not only ancient. As Thoreau said not so very long ago: "To be a philosopher is not merely to have subtle thoughts, nor even to found a school, but so to love wisdom as to live according to its dictates, a life of simplicity, independence, magnanimity, and trust. It is to solve some of the problems of life, not just theoretically, but practically." </p>
<p>Perhaps, too, there is still space for such a life in our modern society.</p>
</entry>
</journal>
