<journal>
<header><title>A Funeral Poem</title><date>2012-11-20</date></header>
<entry>
<p>When my father died in 1999, I wrote a poem that I recited at his funeral service, entitled <a href='/writings/fire/reflections.html'>Reflections on My Father's Life</a> (more <a href='57.html'>here</a>). Over the years, several people have asked me if I could adapt it slightly for more general use (since only 11 lines are specific to my father). Today someone I know online asked me if I'm aware of an appropriate text that could be read at his own father's funeral, so I have finally adjusted my original poem a bit. Since everything that I write is released without copyright, feel free to use this poem if desired (and note that, although all the pronouns are masculine, they could easily be changed to feminine as needed).</p>
<p>###</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
As the generations of leaves,<br />
so the generations of men.<br />
Down to earth the wind shoots the leaves,<br />
but forest trees burst forth again<br />
in the hour when spring is born:<br />
so one generation of men<br /> 
dies off while another grows strong.<br />
<cite>The Iliad, VI.146-149</cite>
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
As the generations of leaves,<br />
so the generations of men.<br />
Yet what's the value of one leaf?<br />
Can it be just to grow the stem?<br />
I think not, but I'm not sure why:<br />
for if I say, as I am wont,<br />
that meaning's made whenever I<br />
create some value in the world,<br />
then it would seem the worth of one<br />
is only in his strength to serve,<br />
to build the beam and build the bough<br />
so others yet may bud and grow<br />
and, having built, may fall to earth<br />
when winter of their time has come.<br />
</p>
<p>
But so to speak ignores the joy<br />
and pride that comes from bringing new<br />
and unique value to the world<br />
or keeping whole what's come before,<br />
for sake of others and oneself.<br />
For there's no conflict here: we each<br />
pursue an interest in the good<br />
through single acts that are yet whole<br />
and so create without intent<br />
a world that's better for us all.
</p>
<p>
A leaf has fallen from the tree:<br />
and all I ask is that he gain<br />
a due amount of honor from<br />
the ones he touched and left behind.<br />
A leaf has fallen from the tree:<br/>
he lived with pride, he lived with joy,<br/>
and we who gather here today<br/>
are better for his having lived.
</p>
<p>###</p>
</entry>
</journal>
