<journal>
<header><title>Musical Parallels</title><date>2013-06-08</date></header>
<entry>
<p>I've been listening to the <a href='1341.html'>Bach Cello Suites</a> a lot lately, with the intent of applying some of their spirit to the collection of <a href='1435.html'>Yes transcriptions</a> I'm working on. For instance, my transcription of "Turn of the Century" was already more measured than the Yes performance on their 1977 album <cite>Going For The One</cite>, but inspired by the sarabandes of the Cello Suites I'm experimenting with slowing it even further.</p>
<p>Indeed, I'm starting to hear some deeper parallels here. All of the Cello Suites contain six movements, in the following order: a prelude, an allemande, a courante, a sarabande, a menuet or bourée or gavotte, and a gigue. My recording <a href='/music/yes/'>Fundamental Affirmation</a> will also have six pieces, one from each of the albums in what Bill Martin calls the "main sequence" of Yes music (indeed it was Martin, in his book <cite>Music of Yes</cite>, who suggested the idea of Yes transcriptions for bass as a modern counterpart of the Cello Suites). And here is the order I'm planning:</p>
<ol>
  <li>To Be Over</li>
  <li>South Side of the Sky</li>
  <li>Tales from Topographic Oceans</li>
  <li>Turn of the Century</li>
  <li>A Venture</li>
  <li>Close to the Edge</li>
</ol>
<p>
My rendering of "To Be Over" is the most free and improvisatory of the six, and thus fits with the typical nature of a musical prelude. "South Side of the Sky" is serious in tone and heavily arpeggiated, as an allemande usually is, although more driving in its tempo. It might be a stretch to liken "Tales from Topographic Oceans" to a courante -- although a courante was usually grave, majestic, and serious, which Tales certainly is. As mentioned, "Turn of the Century", in the fourth spot, is already feeling more and more like a sarabande. And "A Venture" is a bit like a gavotte, with the characteristic phrase beginning in the middle of a bar. I'm not quite sure about "Close to the Edge" as a gigue (!), but I'll be exploring these analogies further as I complete my transcription of "Close to the Edge" and prepare all of these pieces for recording.</p>
<p>Stay tuned!</p>
</entry>
</journal>
