<journal>
<header><title>Annus Mirabilis</title><date>2015-12-16</date></header>
<entry>
<p>Somehow I managed to publish 15 RFCs at the IETF this year, clustered around security, internationalization, and messaging:</p>
<ol>
<li><a href='https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc7457/'>Summarizing Known Attacks on Transport Layer Security (TLS) and Datagram TLS (DTLS)</a></li>
<li><a href='https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc7525/'>Recommendations for Secure Use of Transport Layer Security (TLS) and Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS)</a></li>
<li><a href='https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc7564/'>PRECIS Framework: Preparation, Enforcement, and Comparison of Internationalized Strings in Application Protocols</a></li>
<li><a href='https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc7565/'>The 'acct' URI Scheme</a></li>
<li><a href='https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc7572/'>Interworking between the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) and the Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP): Instant Messaging</a></li>
<li><a href='https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc7573/'>Interworking between the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) and the Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP): One-to-One Text Chat Sessions</a></li>
<li><a href='https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc7590/'>Use of Transport Layer Security (TLS) in the Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP)</a></li>
<li><a href='https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc7613/'>Preparation, Enforcement, and Comparison of Internationalized Strings Representing Usernames and Passwords</a></li>
<li><a href='https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc7622/'>Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP): Address Format</a></li>
<li><a href='https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc7649/'>The Jabber Scribe Role at IETF Meetings</a></li>
<li><a href='https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc7673/'>Using DNS-Based Authentication of Named Entities (DANE) TLSA Records with SRV Records</a></li>
<li><a href='https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc7700/'>Preparation, Enforcement, and Comparison of Internationalized Strings Representing Nicknames</a></li>
<li><a href='https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc7702/'>Interworking between the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) and the Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP): Groupchat</a></li>
<li><a href='https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc7711/'>PKIX over Secure HTTP (POSH)</a></li>
<li><a href='https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc7712/'>Domain Name Associations (DNA) in the Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP)</a></li>
</ol>
<p>For what it's worth, 96 percent of RFC authors have published less than 15 RFCs in their entire career at the IETF. It's a typical <a href='http://www.arkko.com/tools/rfcstats/authactdistr.html'>power law distribution</a>: 55% have published one, 16% have published two, 8% have published three, and so on. I've published 39 so far, which puts me in the top 1%. (Yes, I'm a one-percenter now!) To be fair, some of the specs I've published are fixes to or updates of older standards, so they're not all that novel.</p>
<p>I hesitate to guess how many hours I've spend working on industry standards at the IETF - maybe 5,000 or more. And that gets to the heart of the matter: standardization is usually less a matter of inspiration and more a matter of perspiration - specifically, the dogged persistence necessary to address the objections that seem to arise every step of the way. So perhaps this "annus mirabilis" is not so impressive after all. ;-)</p>
</entry>
</journal>
