<journal>
<header><title>Investing in Life</title><date>2018-11-17</date></header>
<entry>
<p>Recently I got to talking with my friend Dave Jilk about happiness, flourishing, and my future book <cite>The Art of Living</cite>. While relating my ideas about the goals of life (as captured in a recent blog post), I described the importance of taking a balanced approach and including all or most of these goals in one's life pursuits. He likened this to portfolio management in investing, which is a great analogy. This spurred me to thinking further about the value that each area of life brings to one's overall success in life. Consider a few somewhat fanciful extensions of this analogy:</p>
<ul>
<li>Health and vitality are like cash: a liquid asset you can spend immediately at any time (but if you run out of them, you're bankrupt).</li>
<li>Achievement and projects are like stocks: dependent on great productivity over time.</li>
<li>Love and friendship are like long-term bonds: in fact they literally <em>are</em> bonds of connection you build and maintain with another person.</li>
<li>Wisdom is like gold: a pure, precious, unalloyed value that is never oxidized or corrupted.</li>
<li>Character is like real estate: the underlying ground and home of all the value you create in life.</li>
<li>Beauty is like art: an everlasting value whose experience is at the same time deeply ephemeral.</li>
</ul>
<p>As I mentioned a few years ago, the approach to financial investing I have adopted (the Permanent Portfolio) involve equal weighting of four asset classes: cash, stocks, long-term bonds, and gold. Supposedly, the ultra-rich (who often think of maintaining wealth across generations) typically invest in real estate, gold, and art. Putting these together yields six asset classes, similar to those I'm exploring for investing in life. Although these analogies might be merely suggestive, I find them intriguing nonetheless.</p>
<p><em>FOR FURTHER EXPLORATION</em></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.jilk.com/">Dave Jilk</a></li>
<li><a href="/writings/living/">The Art of Living</a></li>
<li><a href="1614.html">Goals of Life</a> (2018-10-30)</li>
<li><a href="1549.html">Investing for the Rest of Us</a> (2016-05-28)</li>
</ul>
</entry>
</journal>
