<journal>
<header><title>Aristotle Research Report #7: φρόνησις</title><date>2019-02-05</date></header>
<entry>
<p>For Aristotle, the various excellences of character (courage, moderation, justice, and the like) are all instances of tending to find a balance between overdoing and underdoing a particular kind of action or feeling, either generally or in a particular respect (e.g., becoming angry in the wrong situations, toward the wrong kinds of people, too quickly, too strongly, etc.). Borrowing terminology from archery, he speaks of balance as a matter of hitting the target (σκοπός) and of imbalance as a matter of missing the mark (ἁμαρτία).</p>
<p>Because an excellence of character is not a single act but a settled practice or way of being (at times he likens it to a second nature acquired through long experience), it involves stable patterns of intention (προαίρεσις) and thinking things through (διάνοια). It is not only a way of conducting yourself (πράττειν) but also a way of being minded (φρόνειν), in which success involves both acting well (εὐπραξία) and deliberating well (εὐβουλία). This excellent way of being minded is φρόνησις or wisdom (often rendered as "practical wisdom" or, in older translations, as "prudence").</p>
<p>Interestingly, φρόνησις itself is also a balance: in Book II.3 of the <cite>Eudemian Ethics</cite> Aristotle contrasts it with cunning (πανουργία) and simplemindedness (εὐήθεια). Whereas cunning might involve rationalization of your behavioral waywardness (we could call this deliberating badly or δυσβουλία) and simplemindedness or foolishness might involve blindly being led by your emotions and cravings (we could call this not deliberating at all or ὐβουλία), φρόνησις involves straight reasoning (ὀρθός λόγος) in which you correct your bad tendencies toward craving (ἐπιθυμία) for too much pleasure (τό ἡδύ) or wanting (θυμός) to gain too much advantage (τό συμφέρων); instead, you come to see that by doing and choosing what is beautifully right (τό καλόν) you experience a higher kind of enjoyment and advantage. Thus wisdom is a master virtue that guides all the particular excellences of character (more abot them in my next research report and, of course, in my forthcoming book <cite>Complete Yourself: Aristotle on Personal Excellence</cite>).</p>
<p><em>FOR FURTHER EXPLORATION</em></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/writings/aristotle/">Complete Yourself</a></li>
</ul>
</entry>
</journal>
