<journal>
<header><title>Certainty</title><date>2023-07-02</date></header>
<entry>
<p>In my post the other day about the examined life, I observed that some people are certain about their answers to the great questions of life. By contrast, those of a Socratic bent typically doubt that certainty is likely or even possible. The standard rejoinder is this: "It sounds like you're certain that certainty is impossible." Quite the conundrum.</p>
<p>For myself, over time I've become less certain about most things theoretical. Life is complex, and it's difficult to unambiguously define and unpack concepts like courage or justice. Indeed, Aristotle argued that it's foolish to strive for more precision in a domain like ethics than can be reasonably expected. The reason is that we can't merely rely on theory: we need practical wisdom to help us sort out the messy realities we face every day.</p>
<p>At the same time that I've become less certain about most theories, I've become more certain about some facts - even or especially facts with ethical implications, such as that human beings are social animals for whom family, friendship, and community are central features of a human way of life. Similarly for phenomena such as language, discourse, emotion, memory, forethought, and imagination, which undergird excellent practices like empathy, reflection, and deliberation.</p>
<p>It seems to me that the pursuit of certainty has caused endless havoc for societies, organizations, and individuals, in the form of religious dogmas, political absolutism, and overly rigid rules of behavior. Yet perhaps we've been looking for certainty in all the wrong places: perhaps certainty is not to be found in the theoretical clouds, but right here on earth in the deeply human interactions that ground our lives. So here's a heretical thought: the truly philosophical life might require a lot less theory focused on faraway abstractions and a lot more practice focused on what is near and dear.</p>
<p>(<a href='https://philosopher.coach/2023/07/02/certainty/'>Cross-posted</a> at <a href='https://philosopher.coach/'>philosopher.coach</a>.)</p>
<p>FOR FURTHER EXPLORATION</p>
<ul>
<li><a href='1792.html'>The Examined Life (2023-06-29)</a></li>
<li><a href='https://stpeter.im/writings/nietzsche/far-and-near.html'>Far and Near</a> (a poem from my book <cite>Songs of Zarathustra</cite>)</li>
</ul>
</entry>
</journal>
