<journal>
<header><title>Daily Forethought</title><date>2023-08-07</date></header>
<entry>
<p>In pursuit of a more examined life, I've been honing my daily habits. Taking a hint from the ancient Stoics, first thing in the morning I've been thinking about the day ahead and then at the end of the day I've been reflecting on how the day went. Here's a snapshot of what this looks like for me (I'll split this up into two posts, one prospective and one retrospective).</p>
<p>To begin the day, I apply an Epicurean twist and take a moment to appreciate the simple fact of being alive to enjoy another day of existence. This includes being grateful for some of the many beautiful and beneficial aspects of the life I lead. Then I ask myself a series of questions:</p>
<ul>
<li>What are my most important activities today? How will I make them positive, productive and meaningful?</li>
<li>Which relationships will I nurture today?</li>
<li>Which long-term projects will I move forward today?</li>
<li>Which practices will I focus on today to strengthen my character?</li>
<li>What will I do today for the sake of my health?</li>
<li>What will I do today to appreciate the beauty of the world around me?</li>
<li>What opportunities for learning will I have today?</li>
<li>What setbacks might I face today and how will I prepare for them?</li>
<li>What positive experiences will I create today for myself and the people I care about?</li>
</ul>
<p>To make this session as successful as possible, I try to keep the following themes in mind:</p>
<ol>
<li>Raising my <em>awareness</em> throughout the day.</li>
<li>Approaching the day with a greater sense of <em>purpose</em>.</li>
<li>Having more <em>optimism</em> about what I can accomplish.</li>
<li>Facing challenges with greater <em>resilience</em>.</li>
<li>Maintaining a high level of <em>focus</em>.</li>
<li>Putting a premium on effective <em>action</em>.</li>
</ol>
<p>I keep a notes document on my phone to remind me of these questions and themes, which I look at before I peek at ephemera like email, news headlines, or the weather forecast. As Thoreau said, "Read not the Times; Read the Eternities." And what's more eternal than living a good life?</p>
<p>UPDATE: The follow-up post is <a href='1808.html'>Daily Reflection</a></p>
<p>(<a href='https://philosopher.coach/2023/08/07/daily-forethought/'>Cross-posted</a> at <a href='https://philosopher.coach/'>philosopher.coach</a>.)</p>
<p><em>FOR FURTHER EXPLORATION</em></p>
<ul>
<li><a href='1792.html'>The Examined Life (2023-06-29)</a></li>
<li><a href='1703.html'>Read the Eternities (2022-02-27)</a></li>
</ul>
</entry>
</journal>
