<journal>
<header><title>Walking with Aristotle: Nicomachean Ethics VI.3-4</title><date>2024-08-04</date></header>
<entry>
<p>On the last section of our walk, we started to pick our way through a boulder-field of concepts that Aristotle introduced to kick off Book VI. Here we'll glance at two of those concepts: understanding [epistm] and craft [techn]. Aristotle's purpose here is not to examine these phenomena in detail, but to set up a contrast with wisdom [phronsis] and sagacity [sophia], which will become the primary focus later in Book VI.</p>
<p>As Aryeh Kosman and Myles Burnyeat identified years ago in two papers I discussed last November, for Aristotle understanding a thing is actually understanding how to explain or spell out or give an account [logos] of why it is the way it is. As a result, understanding is an "explanatory trait" [hexis apodeixis]. Here and elsewhere, Aristotle states that this kind of knowing applies to things that cannot be otherwise, since it leads to a pure awareness [theoria] of something's nature.</p>
<p>The contrast Aristotle draws is with things that <em>can</em> be otherwise, especially the objects of craft and of action: you deliberate about how to make something or do something only if your deliberations might make a difference in the world. This is why Aristotle says that craft is a production-oriented trait "with an account" or "suffused with thinking" [meta logou] and, similarly, that wisdom is an action-oriented trait <em>meta logou</em>. Whereas providing an account for the way things are is plain and simple what understanding accomplishes, that's not the central purpose or organizing principle for craft and action.</p>
<p>Although many scholars reduce these distinctions to a difference between theoretical knowledge and practical or productive knowledge, or to a difference between the contemplative life and the active life, as I see it that's not exactly what's going on here. In VI.1, Aristotle had talked about two parts or aspects of the mind: the "understanding part", which is aware of [theorein] things that cannot be otherwise, and the "deliberative part", which is aware of [theorein] things that can be otherwise. Looking ahead slightly, in VI.5 he will mention that statesmen like Pericles "are aware of [theorein] what is good for themselves and for human beings" more generally. This indicates that ancient <em>theoria</em> is not exclusively "theoretical" in our modern sense; instead, Aristotle appears to be making use of an underlying concept of conceptual awareness (recall his widespread references to "meta logou"), which plays a key role not only in theoretical inquiry but also in productive making and practical doing.</p>
<p>As we move forward in Book VI and beyond, we'll see that these insights are crucially important to human fulfillment and the examined life.</p>
<p>(<a href='https://philosopher.coach/2024/08/04/walking-with-aristotle-nicomachean-ethics-vi-3-4/'>Cross-posted</a> at <a href='https://philosopher.coach/'>philosopher.coach</a>.)</p>
<p><em>FOR FURTHER EXPLORATION</em></p>
<ul>
<li><a href='1833.html'>Understanding What You Know</a> (2023-11-29)</li>
<li><a href='/writings/aristotle/'>Complete Thyself: Aristotle on Human Fulfillment</a></li>
</ul>
</entry>
</journal>
