<journal>
<header><title>O'Reilly Proposals</title><date>2002-03-01</date></header>
<entry>
<p>I just submitted two proposals to speak at the O’Reilly Open Source Convention this summer.</p>
<p>I spoke at last year's conference but I was filling in for someone else so I didn't prepare a talk ahead of time (besides, my talk was more informal, merely an overview of what was happening in the Jabber community). Here are the two proposals I submitted &mdash; send me feedback if you think they can be improved upon, since I have 24 hours to make changes&hellip;</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Saving Time and Money with Presence and Instant Messaging</p>
<p>Knowing when someone is available and being able to communicate with them immediately can save you time and money. These two concepts &mdash; presence and instant messaging &mdash; are beginning to permeate the electronic world. For example:</p>
<ul>
<li>Cell phones are used for exchanging short text messages.</li>
<li>Company directories show the availability of each employee.</li>
<li>Distributed work teams use online "conference rooms" to meet in real time.</li>
</ul>
<p>This talk focuses on open-source presence and instant messaging technologies that can help organizations cut costs and make teams more productive, without compromising security.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That's the first one &mdash; it's intended to fit in with this year's theme of "Do More With Less" (really, that's the theme of the conference!). The second one is more strategic:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Open Source, Open Standards</p>
<p>While open-source projects can truly thrive only in an environment of open standards, reality is not always so clear-cut. Where the software ecosystem is controlled by closed implementations, open-source projects can survive only at the margins, mainly by reverse-engineering the closed protocols (e.g., Samba). Where open standards rule, open-source projects can attain effective ubiquity (e.g., Apache). Where the situation is more complex, there is an opportunity for open-source projects to drive the standards process (e.g., Jabber). In this session we will explore the dynamics of open source and open standards, focusing on how open-source projects can be successful no matter what environment they find themselves in.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>We'll see if the good folks at O'Reilly find either of those interesting. :-)</p>
</entry>
</journal>
