<journal>
<header><title>Good Distractions</title><date>2024-11-25</date></header>
<entry>
<p>While talking with a friend today, I described my concept of the "to don't list" as well as a few of my personal best practices related to smartphone usage. In the midst of our conversation, it occurred to me that there's such a thing as a good distraction. It's difficult for even the most disciplined person to stay focused all the time on long-term projects and personal productivity. We all need a mental break! Yet, speaking from experience, all too often I'm wont to pull out my smartphone or computer and check the headlines, even though I've been on a low-information diet for 10-15 years and intellectually I know the news isn't helpful for my state of mind. At least for me, this a bad distraction!</p>
<p>By contrast, for me good distractions include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Picking up my guitar to play a song or work my way through a few more measures of a piece I'm learning (currently that's the Trois Gymnopédies of Erik Satie).</li>
<li>Stepping outside to stretch my legs and walk the dogs.</li>
<li>Reading a poem or two (preferably in a book because the ideal distraction happens in the real world, but failing that at my Monadnock website).</li>
<li>Taking a photo of cloud formations and sending it to my friend Paul.</li>
<li>Checking the liner notes of whatever recording I'm listening to.</li>
<li>Leafing through an art book to soak in a few paintings.</li>
<li>Watching the birds at our bird feeder.</li>
</ul>
<p>Thinking about what makes for good distractions will, I suspect, cause me to be even more intentional about seeking them out, thus solidifying the practice.</p>
<p>As another friend of mine likes to say: "Good habits are hard to break." True - but it's forming them in the first place that's the challenge! ;-)</p>
<p>(<a href='https://philosopher.coach/2024/11/25/good-distractions/'>Cross-posted</a> at <a href='https://philosopher.coach/'>philosopher.coach</a>.)</p>
<p><em>FOR FURTHER EXPLORATION</em></p>
<ul>
<li><a href='1466.html'>My To-Don't List</a> (2012-08-20)</li>
<li><a href='1789.html'>More Humanity</a> (2023-06-17)</li>
<li><a href='1767.html'>Of Cigarettes and Smartphones</a> (2023-02-16)</li>
<li><a href='1523.html'>Long-Term Projects</a> (2015-02-25)</li>
<li><a href='1551.html'>Personal Productivity</a> (2016-07-10)</li>
<li><a href='1522.html'>Low Information Diet</a> (2015-02-25)</li>
<li><a href='https://monadnock.net/poems.html'>Monadnock Valley Press: Poems</a></li>
</ul>
</entry>
</journal>
