<journal>
<header><title>Taking Notes</title><date>2024-11-26</date></header>
<entry>
<p>Since I seem to be on a roll writing about habits, I figured I'd mention another one: taking notes during meetings.</p>
<p>Over the last five years of my tech career, I got really good at this. It started when I used to volunteer as a scribe during industry standardization meetings at the IETF, wherein I would jot down the main discussion points and action items so that the working group chairs could provide a session summary to the conference proceedings. Over time, I started doing the same thing in my day job - especially at Mozilla, where I had a huge number of meetings with partners and it became difficult to keep track of it all.</p>
<p>Initially I did this in paper notebooks, but that method had a few major downsides. First, the resulting notes weren't searchable. Second, I can type way faster than I can write. My solution was to keep all my notes in text files on my computer, which I could search through using the `grep` utility at the Unix command line. (Yes, I'm a geek - more normal folks might use a dedicated note-taking app.) For each meeting, I would create a separate file named `partner-yyyy-mm-dd.txt`, thus making it easy to see the entire history of interactions. For each meeting, I would list the participants, write up major discussion points and decisions, list action items (prefaced by "TODO" for improved searchability). If I had time, I would quickly review and correct the notes after the meeting; if I had back-to-back meetings, as was often the case, I would try to do this at the end of the day while my memories were still fresh.</p>
<p>For our most important partners, we kept notes in shared documents, which was good for transparency and collaborative note-taking but more distracting for me because I find it convenient to type in a small terminal window tucked away in the bottom right corner of the screen while most of the screen is devoted to the video conferencing app where the meeting takes place.</p>
<p>Speaking of distracting, you might wonder: doesn't it annoy other participants if I'm typing away during a meeting? I'm a fairly noisy typist, but I've learned to type more quietly and I also mute myself when not speaking (here it helps to have a corded headset with a physical mute button).</p>
<p>Taking notes in this way really helped me to stay organized, follow through on my commitments, and communicate more effectively. If you give it a try, let me know how it goes.</p>
<p>(<a href='https://philosopher.coach/2024/11/26/taking-notes/'>Cross-posted</a> at <a href='https://philosopher.coach/'>philosopher.coach</a>.)</p>
</entry>
</journal>
