<journal>
<header><title>Thinking Freely</title><date>2025-04-24</date></header>
<entry>
<p>While collectively we slouch towards tyranny, individually I continue to ponder some of the many methods people have proposed for counteracting that trend. Amidst all the particular suggestions, one thing I have not seen mentioned is <em>adopting the attitude of a free person</em>. This strikes me as seemingly simple but in fact both difficult and fundamental.</p>
<p>Because I'm deep into Aristotle research these days, I'll point out a dozen of his relevant observations, but rephrase them as actionable advice:</p>
<ol>
<li>Don't flatter a tyrant.</li>
<li>Don't be susceptible to the flattering words of a demagogue.</li>
<li>Don't put up with disrespect and ill treatment from corrupt, unethical, tyrannical rulers.</li>
<li>Don't get in the habit of thinking small; instead, think proudly and freely.</li>
<li>Never forget that you and your fellow citizens don't deserve to be lorded over by all-powerful rulers.</li>
<li>Honor and keep your dignity.</li>
<li>Strengthen the bonds of brotherhood.</li>
<li>Work with and build trust among your friends, neighbors, and other members of your community.</li>
<li>Exercise what power you have to the best of your abilities.</li>
<li>Educate yourself about political philosophy and political history.</li>
<li>Cultivate thrivings of character, especially courage, moderation, justice, and wisdom.</li>
<li>Because politics exists to serve human flourishing, never stop pursuing the highest activities of a free people.</li>
</ol>
<p>The basic idea is this: those who stand straight and tall don't slouch in the first place, whether towards tyranny or any other form of human languishing, injustice, and corruption.</p>
<p>(Cross-posted at <a href='https://beautifulwisdom.substack.com/'>Beautiful Wisdom</a>.)</p>
<p><em>FOR FURTHER EXPLORATION</em></p>
<ul>
<li><a href='1956.html'>Slouching towards Monarchy</a> (2025-04-24)</li>
<li><a href='https://www.ifyoucankeepit.org/p/how-you-can-protect-democracy'>How *you* can protect democracy</a> by Quinn Raymond</li>
<li><a href='1869.html'>Brotherhood</a> (2024-05-28)</li>
<li><a href='1948.html'>Aristotle on Freedom</a> (2025-03-31)</li>
</ul>
</entry>
</journal>
