<journal>
<header><title>Philosophers: Public and Private</title><date>2025-09-17</date></header>
<entry>
<p>We're all familiar with public intellectuals: prominent thinkers who cross over from merely academic research to have an impact on the broader culture through popular books, public debates, influence on government policy, and so on.</p>
<p>Among public intellectuals, some are philosophers; examples might include Peter Singer, Martha Nussbaum, and in previous generations people like Hannah Arendt, Bertrand Russell, John Dewey, William James, and Ralph Waldo Emerson.</p>
<p>This phenomenon set me to thinking about what it might mean to be a <em>private</em> intellectual or a <em>private</em> philosopher. It seems to me that the opposite of someone who seeks and has a public impact isn't someone who toils silently in academia, but someone who seeks and has a private, personal impact. Because I have no desire to be famous, being a "private philosopher" would have definite appeal - if I could figure out what that phrase means. Here are some ideas:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Take a reflective approach to my projects and activities (even if they are outside the discipline of philosophy per se).</li>
  <li>Regularly reflect on and improve my behaviors, habits, actions, and commitments.</li>
  <li>Ponder the philosophical aspects and implications of a wide range of human endeavors (e.g., current events, technological developments, cultural trends, science, art, music).</li>
  <li>Read widely in philosophy, literature, psychology, history, religion, and the like.</li>
  <li>Continually work to clarify my thinking processes, question and shed unwarranted beliefs, moderate my opinions, become more reasonable, etc.</li>
  <li>Provide wise counsel (when requested or appropriate!) to my friends, family members, colleagues, neighbors, and other people I interact with.</li>
  <li>Mentor younger people to help them succeed in life.</li>
  <li>Gain an ever deeper understanding of the human condition and how to become better at the task of being human.</li>
</ul>
<p>To my mind, these activities and others seem bound up with a quest for sagacity, but that's a large topic for another day...</p>
<p>(Cross-posted at <a href='https://beautifulwisdom.substack.com/'>Beautiful Wisdom</a>.)</p>
<p><em>FOR FURTHER EXPLORATION</em></p>
</entry>
</journal>
