<journal>
<header><title>Private, Personal, Practical, Passionate, Particular</title><date>2025-10-10</date></header>
<entry>
<p>Following a gap of nearly forty years (!), I'm re-reading Alasdair MacIntyre's influential book <cite>After Virtue</cite>. As I do so, I'll post occasionally on the reflections it inspires.</p>
<p>Right off the bat on page 6, MacIntyre gives three examples of contemporary moral disagreement that, from my recent philosophical perspective, I find questionable: just war, abortion, and rights to health care and education.</p>
<p>Notice that these topics concern politics or public morality, they are general or impersonal, they aren't things I can take action on directly (unless I happen to have a significant role in political governance), we are supposed to deliberate about them in a disinterested or dispassionate manner, and our deliberations should result in policies or rules that are universal. Thus to my mind they are actually matters of <em>statecraft</em>.</p>
<p>Flipping these qualities around, we get a glimpse of what, by contrast, <em>soulcraft</em> is all about: those aspects of life that are private, personal, practical, passionate, and particular. Consider a few of the more momentous matters one might deliberate about in life: Is this the person I want to marry? Do we want to start a family? Is this the line of work that comprises my calling? Should I quit my job and become an entrepreneur? How can I help my best friend, who is facing a personal crisis? I suspect I'm in an abusive relationship, should I move out and start over? Is now the time for me to retire? How can I give back in my community? Is this avocation expressive of who I really am? How can I do justice to my highest potential as a human being? And so on.</p>
<p>Here's how I would unpack these qualities:</p>
<ul>
<li>The private is that which is intimate, uncommon, unknown, hidden from public view.</li>
<li>The personal is that which has meaning and significance to me as an individual.</li>
<li>The practical is that which I can take action on, and where my actions can make a real difference.</li>
<li>The passionate is that which is bound up with my feelings and emotions.</li>
<li>The particular is that which directly affects only myself and the individuals I care about.</li>
</ul>
<p>Statecraft is what most people pontificate about on social media, blogs, Substack, and the like - but what matters most in our pursuit of happiness and fulfillment is soulcraft.</p>
<p>(Cross-posted at <a href='https://beautifulwisdom.substack.com/'>Beautiful Wisdom</a>.)</p>
<p><em>FOR FURTHER EXPLORATION</em></p>
<ul>
<li><a href='1997.html'>Soulcraft</a> (2025-10-05)</li>
</ul>
</entry>
</journal>
