<journal>
<header><title>Twenty-Five Years of Blogging</title><date>2025-11-21</date></header>
<entry>
<p>On this day in the year 2000, I posted the first entry in my online journal. Two thousand posts and 650,000+ words later, I'm still at it. Granted, my journal is not quite of Thoreauvian proportions: our friend Henry produced over 2 million words in 24 years of journaling (all of which I read while encountering Thoreau in preparation for composing my book <cite>The Upland Farm</cite>). Even so, I've done a lot of scribbling over the last quarter century!</p>
<p>Here's how I described the nascent endeavor back then:</p>
<blockquote>I see this space as part diary, part sandbox, and part weblog - a place to explore ideas and events on the web, in real life, and in my head. Hopefully someone other than me will find it interesting. :-)</blockquote>
<p>Some things have changed over the last 25 years: for instance, I don't know what makes a "weblog" distinctive now that so much of modern existence has moved from physical to virtual. Moreover, because I'm a pretty private person I have always shied away from treating this journal like a diary. Thus over time I've gravitated mostly to the sandbox model, in which I try ideas on for size and explore the personal implications of my readings and reflections.</p>
<p>To my mind, this journal isn't writing in a professional sense but the simple act of thinking out loud, which I find enormously helpful in pursuit of greater clarity and wisdom as I travel through life. That a few folks seemingly like to listen in on my dialogue with myself means a great deal to me.</p>
<p>Here's to the next 25 years!</p>
<p>(Cross-posted at <a href='https://beautifulwisdom.substack.com/'>Beautiful Wisdom</a>.)</p>
<p><em>FOR FURTHER EXPLORATION</em></p>
<ul>
<li><a href='74.html'>My First Entry</a> (2000-11-21)</li>
<li><a href='1555.html'>Philosophical Encounters</a> (2016-08-01)</li>
<li><a href='/writings/thoreau/upland-farm.html'>The Upland Farm: Thoreau on Cultivating a Better Life</a></li>
<li><a href='1516.html'>Why I Am Not a Writer</a> (2014-10-02)</li>
<li><a href='1940.html'>Writing as Thinking</a> (2025-03-03)</li>
</ul>
</entry>
</journal>
