<journal>
<header><title>Beauty, Pleasure, Mozart, and Bob Dylan</title><date>2025-11-26</date></header>
<entry>
<p>Since choosing the name Beautiful Wisdom for my Substack earlier this year, I have focused more on wisdom and less on beauty. That might be changing, for several reasons: I've been getting deeper into musical composition, theory, and performance; I've been souring on speculative logorrhea; and in some of my recent readings on aesthetics I've been disappointed with philosophical accounts of beauty.</p>
<p>A case in point regarding the latter is George Santayana's 1896 classic <cite>The Sense of Beauty</cite>. I hasten to mention that I am just getting started with Santayana's vast oeuvre, so I might be misreading him. Unfortunately, right now I find his underlying account of beauty and the arts to be implausible. To wit, Santayana claims that beauty is (aesthetic) pleasure regarded as the quality of a thing: when a person says that an object or experience is beautiful, all they really mean is that it gives them a purely subjective pleasure - which they then shift, with absolutely no justification, onto the object itself and its perceptually salient features (such as color, symmetry, and form). It's almost a kind of aesthetic emotivism; if I say that Michelangelo's David is beautiful, all I really mean is "David Yum!"</p>
<p>If Santayana's account were true, then I could not call something beautiful if I didn't enjoy it, and I could not enjoy something if it weren't beautiful. However, in my experience both of these paradoxical phenomena are not only possible but quite common.</p>
<p>As an example of the first paradox, I recognize that objectively speaking the music of Mozart is quite beautiful: classically balanced, highly melodic, endlessly inventive, and so on. Yet subjectively speaking I concur with Glenn Gould's assessment that most of Mozart's music is so much musical prattle. You might counter that evidently I must be a musical boor: even though I could converse for hours about the wonders of, say, Bach's Cello Suites or Fauré's Nocturnes, I simply <em>should</em> enjoy Mozart. But this aesthetic imperative is even less legitimate than the moral imperatives of Kant or the Stoics.</p>
<p>As an example of the second paradox, I adore the music and, yes, even the singing of Bob Dylan. More evidence of my boorishness! Objectively speaking Dylan's vocal stylings are, at best, an acquired taste; at worst, they are downright grating. Here again you might assert that I simply <em>shouldn't</em> enjoy Dylan's music because it's not beautiful, whereas I again would simply ignore your aesthetic imperatives.</p>
<p>In line with my thoroughgoing particularism, my aesthetic experience is dependent on the individual work at hand, not some hard-and-fast policy that overrides the evidence of my ears and heart. For instance, I'd rather hear Mozart's horn concertos than Dylan's "Idiot Wind" (which to my ear is a decidedly ugly rant set to music).</p>
<p>Where does this leave Santayana? Even though I am not convinced by the foundations of his aesthetic theory, <cite>The Sense of Beauty</cite> contains numerous insights into aesthetic experience, which I am eagerly absorbing as I seek to form my own account of what I'm calling philokalia or the love and practice of beauty.</p>
<p>(Cross-posted at <a href='https://beautifulwisdom.substack.com/'>Beautiful Wisdom</a>.)</p>
<p><em>FOR FURTHER EXPLORATION</em></p>
<ul>
<li><a href='1979.html'>Words, Words, Words</a> (2025-08-15)</li>
<li><a href='1998.html'>Private, Personal, Practical, Passionate, Particular</a> (2025-10-10)</li>
<li><a href='/writings/essays/philokalia.html'>Philokalia: A Manifesto for the Love and Practice of Beauty</a></li>
</ul>
</entry>
</journal>
