<journal>
<header><title>Brief Translation Update</title><date>2026-05-11</date></header>
<entry>
<p>Well, it took me about 8 hours over the course of a few days to translate the first page of Aristotle's <cite>Eudemian Ethics</cite>. Because there are 60 pages in the EE, as it's affectionately known (including the three "common books" shared with the <cite>Nicomachean Ethics</cite>), at this rate it should take me about 500 hours to complete the translation. That's not as long as I expected, and I'll probably gain speed as I make progress up the mountain because here at the start I'm thinking carefully about how I'll render certain words and phrases.</p>
<p>For example, on the very first page we find the following phrase: <em>φιλοσοφίαν μόνον θεωρητικήν</em>. Translators usually render that as something like "purely theoretical philosophy" but to my mind that kin of thing doesn't capture the likely thought behind the Greek words (we can't check all this with Aristotle, so we have to make informed inferences). In the fourth century BCE, philosophy was a new thing in the world and referred to "the love and practice of sagacity"; furthermore, the word θεωρία didn't mean "theory" in our sense (any more than ἐνέργεια meant "energy" or φαντασία meant "fantasy"), but I think instead meant something like "attention". Thus rather loquaciously I've provisionally rendered the phrase as "that passionate practice of sagacity which is devoted to attention alone"; this provides a fitting contrast with the fact that the EE focuses on that passionate practice of sagacity which is devoted to living beautifully and finding fulfillment. I freely grant that in this case I've used quite a few English words to unpack three Greek words, but (a) Greek is a terse language, especially in Aristotle's hands and (b) I'm working hard to make Aristotle's meaning truly understandable for modern readers.</p>
<p>By the way, when I say "page" I mean two columns of the Greek text as edited by August Immanuel Bekker in the 1830s. Although naturally I am closely referencing the most up-to-date scholarship on the Greek text, if you ask me the Bekker version is a thing of beauty.</p>
<p>(Cross-posted at <a href='https://beautifulwisdom.substack.com/'>Beautiful Wisdom</a>.)</p>
<p><em>FOR FURTHER EXPLORATION</em></p>
<ul>
<li><a href='2040.html'>Climbing Mount Aristotle</a> (2026-05-09)</li>
</ul>
</entry>
</journal>
