<journal>
<header><title>Aesthetic as Science of the Perceptual</title><date>1994-01-13</date></header>
<entry>
<p>In our discussion on MDOP of chapter 12 of Peikoff's book <cite>Objectivism: The Philosophy of Ayn Rand</cite> (led off by <a href="/writings/essays/opar12.html">my essay</a>), John Enright says that the original definition of aesthetics as the "science of the beautiful" is not accepted by aestheticians today. I would disagree (Arthur Danto of Columbia, arguably the most famous aesthetician living today, always asks his beginning aesthetics students the following question on exams: "What is beauty?"). But this is beside the point, really.  I think actually that I have misrepresented Baumgarten's original contribution to aesthetics (I have never actually read Baumgarten, only commentary on his work, so I may be writing in ignorance here). From what I know, Baumgarten coined the word aesthetic to be an analog of the word logic. Logic (from the Greek logikos, 'of reason') was originally or primarily developed mainly to interpret the conceptual/linguistic arguments of philosophy (or so it seems to me) &mdash; logic is a tool for analyzing discursive presentation of ideas, esp. philosophical ideas. Similarly, aesthetic from the Greek aisthetikos, 'of perception') was originally envisaged by Baumgarten to be the perceptual counterpart of logic &mdash; to be a tool for analyzing perceptual knowledge, and especially the perceptual presentation of views about man and reality in the form of art.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, aesthetic never really developed along the lines envisaged by Baumgarten. However, I think it might be a fruitful line of investigation. After all, man's knowledge comes in two basic forms: conceptual and perceptual. Do we not need methods for interpreting both forms?  The highest kind of conceptual knowledge is philosophy &mdash; the highest kind of perceptual knowledge is art.  This is all terribly speculative, of course&hellip; </p>
</entry>
</journal>
