<journal>
<header><title>Some Notes</title><date>2003-08-17</date></header>
<entry>
<p>Hi, my name is Peter and I'm a workaholic. For the last few years I've worked especially hard, since I'm blessed to play a leading part in the <a href="http://www.jabber.org/">Jabber</a> community. Unfortunately, working 60-80 hours a week leaves little time for other interests and pursuits, of which I have many. One of the longest-running for me is <a href="/music/">music</a>. I started playing guitar and bass when I was 12 or 13, and I've been writing songs and instrumental pieces since I was 17 or so. I've never found the time (or money) to record my music, nor do I have that real performer's personality or a hunger to be up on stage, so my musical pursuits are not very public. But that doesn't make them any less important to me. Earlier today I had a longish talk about music with my friend Eric Nolte, who is a much more accomplished musician than I am (he is a pianist, violist, and composer when he's not flying airplanes for a living). Talking with Eric has renewed my dedication to becoming more actively involved in music. So I've just requested a number of music theory books from the <a href="http://www.denver.lib.co.us/">Denver public library</a>, as well as songbooks for Hoagy Carmichael, Yip Harburg, and writers of several other songs I've been meaning to learn. Eric pointed me to <a href="http://www.musictheory.net/">musictheory.net</a>, which looks like a great resource. I'm doing some more research on home recording equipment (still leaning towards a <a href="http://www.tascam.com/products/product_information.php?product_id=13">Tascam 428</a> since supposedly it's Linux-compatible, and I'm still lusting after a <a href="http://www.warwickbass.com/basses/_corvette_standard_s4a.html">Warwick</a> electric bass). I need to force myself to participate in the next songwriter's open stage at <a href="http://www.swallowhill.com/">Swallow Hill</a> (on Thursday, September 11 -- not an auspicious date, I must admit), at which local songwriters can sing two or three songs of their own creation (I think I'd sing <a href="/music/hagiography/center.html">Center of the World</a> and either <a href="/music/hagiography/pre-emptive.html">Pre-Emptive Strike</a> or <a href="/music/hagiography/woman.html">She is Woman</a>). I'm thinking I might attend the songwriting workshop being presented by <a href="http://www.wendywaldman.com/">Wendy Waldman</a> on October 24 at Swallow Hill (I'll be at her concert that night, too -- she is an awesome songwriter). Since returning from vacation last week I haven't worked a single night or weekend, and I'm striving hard to keep that up so that I can give some time to my musical (and philosophical) activities. Yes, even a workaholic like me recognizes that balance is important...</p>
</entry>
</journal>
