<journal>
<header><title>The Trouble With Triples?</title><date>2003-08-21</date></header>
<entry>
<p><a href="http://www.dizzyd.com/">Diz</a> links to a <a href="http://usefulinc.com/edd/blog/2003/8/8#13:13">apologia for RDF</a> by Edd Dumbill, who in turns links to <a href="http://www.xml.com/lpt/a/2001/01/24/rdf.html">What is RDF?</a> by Tim Bray. None of these three link to the skeptic's view, best expressed by Cory Doctorow in a rant entitled <a href="http://www.well.com/~doctorow/metacrap.htm">metacrap</a>. RDF uses XML syntax, but is built around the notion of "triples", which should be familiar from logic class (you did take logic, didn't you?): "property P of resource R has value V" (or "entity E has a dimension D whose value is V"). Examples: "the author of JEP-0045 is stpeter", "the blog-URL of stpeter is http://stpeter.im/journal/", "one friend of stpeter is dizzyd". We can often express these in terms of <em>relationships:</em> "stpeter authored JEP-0045", "dizzyd knows stpeter" (should be familiar from the foaf:knows element). In RDF, every resource (or entity, if you prefer that terminology) can be addressed as a URI (HTTP address, mailto, JabberID, what have you). And a value can be (but need not be) a resource. It's the property that captures the relationship. So if you can think in terms of relating a resource to a property by means of a specific value, you're halfway there.</p>
<p>But not all the way. RDF provides a model, but we still need to define the properties and relationships. That's where specific vocabularies like <a href="http://rdfweb.org/mt/foaflog/archives/000051.html">FOAF</a> come in. While there are some missing pieces in the FOAF story, those pieces are being defined and refined over time, which I think will result in a fairly complete language for defining meta-data about people, entities, and their various relationships on the network.</p>
<p>One of the big questions is whether Doctorow's skepticism is warranted. Both Doctorow and Bray seem to be thinking mainly about a web of documents. Doctorow rightly claims that many people are too lazy to define metadata about their web pages, while Bray seems overly pessimistic regarding the ability of brute-force searching (his article was written before Google) and overly optimistic regarding the feasibility of spreading metadata throughout the document web. <em>But the document web is not the whole network.</em> In particular, FOAF concentrates on something new on the network: finding not information but people. Lo and behold, Jabber is mainly focused on people, too. And one thing we've been missing on the Jabber network since day one is a triumphant way to find people (and chatrooms, news feeds, pubsub nodes, etc.). Imagine that you create a Jabber account, provide some information about yourself (or upload an existing FOAF file), including your interests as well as URLs or mailtos for some friends &mdash; and immediately you receive invitations to a chatroom or two, subscription requests from friends who've been waiting for you to create an account, notification of news feeds of interest, and the like &mdash; <em>that</em> is the way we'll truly build a Jabber web.</p>
</entry>
</journal>
