<journal>
<header><title>Reduce, Reuse, Recycle</title><date>2003-09-28</date></header>
<entry>
<p>One mantra of the modern environmental movement is "reduce, reuse, recycle". It's one of those things we just take for granted. Since I'm a contrarian sort of person (some would say an outright curmudgeon), I was fascinated to read <a href="http://www.perc.org/publications/percreports/sept2003/recycling.php?s=2">Recycling Rubbish: Eight Great Myths About Waste Disposal</a> in the latest issue of the newsletter I receive from <a href="http://www.perc.org/">PERC</a>. I've listed the eight myths here and have included the reality:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Myth: our garbage will bury us</p><p>Reality: there is more than enough capacity to meet demand</p></li>
<li><p>Myth: our garbage will poison us</p><p>Reality: garbage is not by nature hazardous to our health or the environment</p></li>
<li><p>Myth: packaging is our problem</p><p>Reality: packaging things in boxes, bottles, and containers reduces the amount of garbage, and packaging has become much lighter over the years</p></li>
<li><p>Myth: we must achive trash independence</p><p>Reality: shipping garbage across state or national borders is often the most efficient use of resources</p></li>
<li><p>Myth: we squander irreplaceable resources when we don't recycle (in fact, most resources are renewable in the sense that we can always find "as much and as good" &mdash; this applies even to things like oil</p></li>
<li><p>Myth: recycling always protects the environment</p><p>Reality: recycling is a manufacturing and distribution process just like any other, and such processes have an environment impact &mdash; often greater than the impact of throwing something away</p></li>
<li><p>Myth: recycling saves resources</p><p>Reality: recycling often uses more resources, in the form of energy and material, than simply discarding something</p></li>
<li><p>Myth: without forced recycling mandates, there wouldn't be recycling</p><p>Reality: scavenging may be the oldest profession, and many industries and individuals engaged in recycling may before politicians got involved in forced recycling</p></li>
</ol>
<p>The <a href="http://www.perc.org/publications/percreports/sept2003/recycling.php?s=2">complete article</a> is well worth reading for those who like to question their assumptions (those who don't might not want to read this weblog).</p>
</entry>
</journal>
