<journal>
<header><title>Reflections on My Father's Life</title><date>1999-09-02</date></header>
<entry>
<blockquote>
<p>
As the generations of leaves,<br />
so the generations of men.<br />
Down to earth the wind shoots the leaves,<br />
but forest trees burst forth again<br />
in the hour when spring is born:<br />
so one generation of men<br /> 
dies off while another grows strong.<br />
<cite>The Iliad, VI.146-149</cite>
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
As the generations of leaves,<br />
so the generations of men.<br />
Yet what's the value of one leaf?<br />
Can it be just to grow the stem?<br />
I think not, but I'm not sure why:<br />
for if I say, as I am wont,<br />
that meaning's made whenever I<br />
create some value in the world,<br />
then it would seem the worth of one<br />
is only in its strength to serve,<br />
to build the beam and build the bough<br />
so others yet may bud and grow<br />
and, having built, may fall to earth<br />
when winter of their time has come.<br />
But so to speak ignores the joy<br />
and pride that comes from bringing new<br />
and unique value to the world<br />
or keeping whole what's come before,<br />
for sake of others and oneself;<br />
for there's no conflict here: we each<br />
pursue an interest in the good<br />
through single acts that are yet whole<br />
and so produce without intent<br />
a world that's better for us all.<br />
Thus my father lived: he healed men<br />
who fought in war then fought again<br />
to gain their health; he sought to save<br />
the land he loved and to preserve<br />
a life long lost through buildings that<br />
the farmers made before our time<br />
(he tried to keep their virtues, too:<br />
straight honesty with all he knew);<br />
he kept his wife till death did part<br />
and raised four children, all with love<br />
and joy in that most awesome task.<br />
And all I ask is that he gain<br />
some small amount of honor from<br />
the ones he left behind. A leaf<br />
has fallen from the tree: he lived<br />
with pride, he lived with joy, and we<br />
are better for his having lived.
</p>
<p>(Read at the memorial service for my father, Christ Church, Gardiner, Maine, on September 2, 1999.)</p>
</entry>
</journal>
