<journal>
<header><title>Haiku</title><date>2000-03-16</date></header>
<entry>
<p>A gentleman named Mark Froemming sent me some waka and haiku that I published in the Monadnock Review at the end of February. Haiku are fairly familiar as the Japanese form containing 17 feet, split into lines of 5, 7, and 5 beats each. Waka are another short Japanese form, though less well-known. Receiving these poems has inspired me to do some research into Japanese poetry, so I headed to the library and read <cite>The Haiku Form</cite> by Joan Giroux and <cite>The Colors of Poetry</cite> by Ooka Mokoto. I've found this reading to be quite fascinating. Although I don't know much about Japanese culture, I have read a great deal of Chinese philosophy, and Zen is really a combination of the three main strands of Chinese thought (Taoism and Confucianism as seen through the lens of Buddhism), so I am finding a lot to like in the Japanese tradition (at least as filtered through translations into English).</p>
<p>Although I usually I go in for longer poetic lines (in fact lately I've been experimenting with "fourteeners", for example in <a href="/writings/fire/rodin.html">On a Visit to the Mus&#233;e Rodin</a> and <a href="/writings/fire/sky.html">Looking up at the Sky</a>), I'm finding myself fascinated by the possibilities of more condensed forms like haiku and waka. So in the last few days I've written two haiku:</p> 
<blockquote>
<p>
Old woman crossing,
<br />two thin legs and a walker:
<br />good it's a long light.
</p>
<p>
Orange city light
<br />reflecting from clouds above
<br />bathes the swirling snow.
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I still remember what Victoria Redel told us in freshman english: write what you know. So I see already that I might like to write a whole bunch of "urban haiku". Most true haiku celebrates rural experience, but why not urban experience, too? I suppose the subjects would be in opposition to the nature focus of most Japanese haiku, but I like to think of it as more complementary than opposed &mdash; the urban yang to the rural yin, if you will. To me, the main thing is to keep the appreciative attitude that these short Japanese forms seem to exhibit. I like the idea of trying to capture certain moments and experiences &mdash; I feel it might make me more attentive to the life swirling around me.</p>
</entry>
</journal>
