<journal>
<header><title>Just Say No</title><date>2005-06-02</date></header>
<entry>
    <p>Since I am half French and half Dutch, I must say it warmed my heart that the French said "non" and the Dutch said "nee" to the European Constitution in the span of a few days. David Carr's <a href="http://www.samizdata.net/blog/archives/007613.html">obituary</a> is classic:</p>
    <blockquote>
      <p>Her all too brief life started out with glamour and hope and ended with controversy and acrimony. But, what she lacked in longevity she made up for in impact, holding an entire continent in her thrall. She was the "It" girl of Europe and there could scarce have been a single Prime Minister, President, King or Bishop who did not want to walk into a room with her draped across his arm.</p>
      <p>But it was her qualities of impeccable breeding that gave rise to resentments as well as plaudits. For everyone that she seduced with her charms, she vexed with her arrogance. For all those that were willing to flirt with her, there were others that feared her embrace. In the end she was brought low by the little people she was born to rule over.</p>
      <p>As much as any analysis of the Constitution is possible at all, then the final one must be that she was a puzzle draped in an enigma. Even those closest to her admitted that she was difficult to read and even harder to interpret. Despite all earnest attempts to present her as something coherent and friendly, she remained stubbornly opaque and inpenetrable; a capricious, whimsical, moody, temperamental, volatile, eccentric, arbitrary, erratic, fickle, inconstant coquette whose last act of defiance is to take her unfathomable mysteries with her to the grave.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p>Whither Europe? Heck if I know, but at least the people have spoken resoundingly against those elitist bureaucrats in Brussels.</p>
    <p><a href="http://www.pattern.com/bennettj-anglosphereprimer.html">Anglosphere</a>, anyone?</p>
</entry>
</journal>
