<journal>
<header><title>Points on the Sphere</title><date>2005-10-12</date></header>
<entry>
    <p>Kevin Phillips has likened the nations and regions of the Anglosphere to cousins. Yet, as in real life, those cousins don't necessarily know each other all that well. One possible way to improve connections between those cousins is through exchanges of people, as is familiar from institutions such as American Field Service (for students) and Sister Cities International. Yet, for instance, the "sister" cities of Denver, Colorado are Brest, France; Takayama, Japan; Nairobi, Kenya; Karmiel, Israel; Potenza, Italy; Cuernavaca, Mexico; Chennai, India; Kunming, China; Axum, Ethiopia; and Ulaanbaatar, Mongolia. Not an Anglosphere location among the bunch! So here's a proposal: let's get at least one Anglosphere town on the "sister city" list for every participating city in America.</p>
    <p>Alternatively, towns with the same name could seek out connections among themselves or even hold reunions of a sort. Consider some town names from different regions of England:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>There are Bristols in England, New Brunswick, Colorado, Connecticut, Florida, Georgia, New Hampshire, Pennsylvania, Rhode Island, South Dakota, Tennessee, Texas, and Vermont.</li>
      <li>There are Cambridges in England, New Zealand, Jamaica, Idaho, Illinois, Maine, Massachusetts, Maryland, Minnesota, Nebraska, New York, Ohio, and Vermont.</li>
      <li>There are Newcastles in England, Australia, New Brunswick, Ontario, Ireland, South Africa, Delaware, Indiana, Oklahoma, Pennsylvania, Texas, Utah, Virginia, and Wyoming.</li>
      <li>There are Richmonds in England, Australia, British Columbia, New Zealand, South Africa, Arizona, California, Illinois, Indiana, Kansas, Kentucky, Louisiana, Maine, Massachusetts, Michigan, Missouri, Minnesota, Ohio, Texas, Utah, and Virginia.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>Folks in these towns could hold a BristolFest or whatever every year, rotating among the towns with that name. It sounds like a good excuse to travel, see new places, make new friends, and experience the different flavors of Anglospheric culture.</p>
    <p>(Cross-posted at <a href="http://anglosphere.com/weblog/">Albion's Seedling</a>.)</p>
</entry>
</journal>
