<journal>
<header><title>Starting a Press</title><date>2001-07-21</date></header>
<entry>
<p>In a <a href='75.html'>journal entry</a> I made almost exactly 8 months ago, I noted that I had started sending poems off to various journals. Nothing really came from that, though I must admit I have not been intensely disciplined about it. One of the options I had considered and rejected before sending off my poems was that of starting a small press. Last night I got to thinking about that idea again, and I concluded that I do in fact want to start a small publishing house (something along the lines of <a href="http://www.graywolf.org/">Graywolf Press</a>). I'm not sure <em>when</em> I'll start this endeavor &mdash; it might not happen for another few years &mdash; but I feel that I could add a tremendous amount of value to the world by doing this.</p>
<p>Obviously it would be a convenient way for me to publish certain of my own writings (such as <a href="/writings/fire/">Ancient Fire</a> and the book I envision writing under the title <a href="http://tao-of-roark.com/">The Tao of Roark</a>). However I am perhaps even more excited about the prospect of seeing to press books that might never otherwise see the light of day &mdash; books such as a volume of short stories by <a href="http://www.monadnock.net/contributors/merrill.html">Ron Merrill</a> (if his literary executors would agree to that &mdash; I had already published two of his stories in the Monadnock Review before he passed away), the <a href="http://www.monadnock.net/stories/nalantei.html">portrait novella</a> by Stephen Marvin that I published, an updated version of the <a href="http://www.monadnock.net/poems/enright.html">poems of John Enright</a> including those included in his earlier volume "Starbound and Other Poems", some translations by <a href="http://www.monadnock.net/contributors/cottrell.html">Leonard Cottrell</a>, and maybe even a volume of poems by <a href="http://www.monadnock.net/poems/moira.html">Moira Russell</a>, the original Cobalt Poetry Goddess! (Not that I presume that any of these writers necessarily want to have me publish their books, it's just that these are the sorts of works I would like to publish.)</p>
<p>I would also like to extend this idea to the pressing of music as well as of books, since I've written a bit of guitar music in my time and I know several composers who have written good music that is not getting an audience.</p>
<p>Well, it'll probably be a few years before I'm ready to start on this, but in the meantime I'll do some preparatory work. Who knows, maybe I'll make faster progress on the idea than I expect.... :)</p>
</entry>
</journal>
